<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<text>
<p id="1">
<s id="1:1">The unfortunate superintendent was at this moment painfully digesting his miserable dinner, whilst awaiting anxiously the termination of this hurricane; he was, however, far from suspecting that its greatest fury was to be spent on himself.</s>
<s id="1:2">Some benevolent persons hastened forward to inform him of his urgent peril.</s>
<s id="1:3">The servants, drawn to the door by the uproar, beheld, in affright, the dense mass advancing.</s>
<s id="1:4">While they listened to the friendly notice, the vanguard appeared; one hastily informed his master; and while he, for a moment, deliberated upon flight, another came to say there was no longer time for it; in hurry and confusion they closed and barricadoed the windows and the doors.</s>
<s id="1:5">The howling without increased; each corner of the house resounded with it; and in the midst of the vast and mingled noise was heard, fearfully and distinctly, the blows of stones upon the door.</s>
<s id="1:6">"The tyrant! the tyrant! the causer of famine! we must have him, living or dead!"</s>
<s id="1:7">The poor man wandered from room to room in a state of insupportable alarm, commending himself to God, and beseeching his servants to be firm, and to find for him some way of escape!</s>
<s id="1:8">He ascended to the highest floor, and, from an opening between the garret and the roof, he looked anxiously out upon the street, and beheld it filled with the enraged populace; more appalled than ever, he withdrew to seek the most secure and secret hiding-place.</s>
<s id="1:9">Here, concealed, he listened intently to ascertain if at any time the importunate transport of passion should weaken, if the tumult should in any degree subside; but his heart died within him to hear the uproar continue with aggravated and savage ferocity.</s>
<s id="1:10">Renzo at this time found himself in the thickest of the confusion, not now carried there by the press, but by his own inclination.</s>
<s id="1:11">At the first proposal of blood-shedding, he felt his own curdle in his veins; as to the plundering, he was not quite certain whether it was right or wrong; but the idea of murder caused him unmixed horror.</s>
<s id="1:12">And although he was greatly persuaded that the vicar was the primary cause of the famine, the grand criminal, still, having, at the first movement of the crowd, heard, by chance, some expressions which indicated a willingness to make any effort to save him, he had suddenly determined to aid such a work, and had therefore pressed near the door, which was assailed in a thousand ways.</s>
<s id="1:13">Some were pounding the lock to break it in pieces; others assisted with stakes, and chisels, and hammers; others, again, tore away the plastering, and beat in pieces the wall, in order to effect a breach.</s>
<s id="1:14">The rest, who were unable to get near the house, encouraged by their shouts those who were at the work of destruction; though, fortunately, through the eagerness with which they pressed forward, they impeded its progress.</s>
<s id="1:15">The magistrates, who were the first to have notice of the fray, despatched a messenger to ask military aid of the commander of the castle, which was then called, from the gate, Giovia; and he forthwith detached a troop, which arrived when the house was encompassed with the throng, and undergoing its tremendous assault; and was therefore obliged to halt at a distance from it, and at the extremity of the crowd.</s>
<s id="1:16">The officer who commanded it did not know what course to pursue;</s>
<s id="1:17">at the order to disperse and make way, the people replied by a deep and continued murmur, but no one moved.</s>
<s id="1:18">To fire on the crowd appeared not only savage, but perilous, inasmuch as the most harmless might be injured, and the most ferocious only irritated, and prepared for further mischief; and moreover his instructions did not authorise it.</s>
<s id="1:19">To break the crowd, and go forward with his band to the house, would have been the best, if success could have been certain; but who could tell if the soldiers could proceed united and in order?</s>
<s id="1:20">The irresolution of the commander seemed to proceed from fear: the populace were unmoved by the appearance of the soldiers, and continued their attacks on the house.</s>
<s id="1:21">At a little distance there stood an ill-looking, half-starved old man, who, contracting an angry countenance to a smile of diabolical complacency, brandished above his hoary head a hammer, with which he said he meant to nail the vicar to the posts of his door, alive as he was.</s>
<s id="1:22">"Oh, shame! shame!" exclaimed Renzo.</s>
<s id="1:23">"Shame! would you take the hangman's business out of his hand? to assassinate a Christian?</s>
<s id="1:24">How can you expect God will give us bread, if we commit such iniquity?</s>
<s id="1:25">He will send us his thunders, and not bread!"</s>
<s id="1:26">"Ah! dog! ah! traitor to the country!" cried one who had heard these words, turning to Renzo with the countenance of a demon.</s>
<s id="1:27">"It is a servant of the vicar's disguised like a countryman; it is a spy!"</s>
<s id="1:28">A hundred voices were heard exclaiming, "Who is it? where is he?"--</s>
<s id="1:29">"A servant of the vicar's--a spy--the vicar himself, escaping in the disguise of a peasant!"--</s>
<s id="1:30">Where is he? where is he?</s>
<s id="1:31">Renzo would have shrunk into nothingness,--some of the more benevolent contrived to help him to disappear through the crowd; but that which preserved him most effectually was a cry of "Make way, here comes our help, make way!" which attracted the attention of the throng.</s>
<s id="1:32">This was a long scaling ladder, supported by a few persons who were endeavouring to penetrate the living mass, and by which they meant to gain entrance to the house.</s>
<s id="1:33">But, happily, this was not easy of execution;</s>
<s id="1:34">the length of the machine precluded the possibility of its being carried easily through such a multitude; </s>
<s id="1:35">it came, however, just in time for Renzo, who profited by the confusion, and escaped to a distance, with the intention of making his way, as soon as he could, to the convent, in search of Father Bonaventura.</s>
<s id="1:36">Suddenly a new movement began at one extremity, and diffused itself through the crowd:--"Ferrer, Ferrer!" resounded from every side.</s>
<s id="1:37">Some were surprised, some rejoiced, some were exasperated, some applauded, some affirmed, some denied, some blessed, some cursed!</s>
<s id="1:38">"Is he here?</s>
<s id="1:39">It is not true; it is not true.</s>
<s id="1:40">Yes, yes, long live Ferrer, he who makes bread cheap.</s>
<s id="1:41">– No, no!</s>
<s id="1:42">He is here--here in a carriage!</s>
<s id="1:43">Why does he come?--we don't want him.</s>
<s id="1:44">– Ferrer! long live Ferrer! the friend of the poor! he comes to take the vicar prisoner. </s>
<s id="1:45">– No, no, we would revenge ourselves, we would fight our own battles; back, back.</s>
<s id="1:46">– Yes, yes, Ferrer!</s>
<s id="1:47">Let him come! to prison with the vicar!"</s>
<s id="1:48">At the extremity of the crowd, on the side opposite to that where the soldiers were, Antonio Ferrer, the high chancellor, was approaching in his carriage, who, probably condemning himself as the cause of this commotion, had come to avert at least its most terrific and irreparable effects, to spend worthily a popularity unworthily acquired.</s>
<s id="1:49">In popular tumults there are always some who, from heated passion, or fanaticism, or wicked design, do what they can to push things to the worst; proposing and promoting the most barbarous counsels, and assisting to stir the fire whenever it appears to slacken.</s>
<s id="1:50">But, on the other hand, there are always those who, perhaps with equal ardour, and equal perseverance, employ their efforts for the production of contrary effects; some led by friendship or partiality for the persons in danger, others without other impulse than that of horror of bloodshed and atrocity.</s>
<s id="1:51">The mass, then, is ever composed of a mixed assemblage, who, by indefinite gradations, hold to one or the other extreme; prompt to rage or compassion, to adoration or execration, according as the occasion presents itself for the developement of either of these sentiments: life and death are the words involuntarily uttered, and with equal facility; and he who succeeds in persuading them that such an one does not deserve to be quartered, has but little more to do, to convince them that he ought to be carried in triumph.</s>
<s id="1:52">While these various interests were contending for superiority in the mob, before the house of the vicar, the appearance of Antonio Ferrer gave instantly a great advantage to the humane, who were manifestly yielding to the greater strength of the ferocious and blood-thirsty.</s>
<s id="1:53">The man himself was acceptable to the multitude, from his having previously favoured their cause, and from his heroic resistance to any arguments against it.</s>
<s id="1:54">Those already favourably inclined towards him were now much more affected by the courageous confidence of an old man, who, without guards or retinue, came thus to confront an angry and stormy multitude.</s>
<s id="1:55">The announcement that his purpose was to take the vicar prisoner, produced at once a wonderful effect; and the fury against that unhappy person, which would have been aggravated by any attempt at defiance, or refusal of concession, now, with the promise of satisfaction, and, to speak in the Milanese fashion, with this bone in the mouth, became in a degree appeased, and gave place to other opposite sentiments, which began to prevail over their minds.</s>
<s id="1:56">The partisans of peace, having recovered breath, aided Ferrer in various ways; those who were near him, while endeavouring by their own to perpetuate the general applause, sought at the same time to keep off the crowd, so as to open a passage for the carriage; others applauded and repeated his words, or such as appeared appropriate to his undertaking and his peril; imposed silence on the obstinately furious, or contrived to turn against them the anger of the fickle assembly.</s>
<s id="1:57">"Who is it that will not say, Long live Ferrer?</s>
<s id="1:58">You don't wish bread to be cheap, then, eh?</s>
<s id="1:59">They are rogues who are not willing to receive justice at the hands of a Christian, and there are some among them who cry louder than the rest, to allow the vicar to escape.</s>
<s id="1:60">To prison with the superintendent!</s>
<s id="1:61">Long live Ferrer!</s>
<s id="1:62">Make way for Ferrer!"</s>
<s id="1:63">The numbers of those who spoke in this manner increasing continually, the numbers of the opposite party diminished in proportion; so that the former, from admonishing, had recourse to blows, in order to silence those who were still disposed to pursue the work of destruction.</s>
<s id="1:64">The menaces and threatenings of the weaker party were of no longer avail; the cause of blood had ceased to predominate, and in its place were heard only the cries of "Prison, justice, Ferrer!"</s>
<s id="1:65">The rebellious spirits were finally silenced: the remainder took possession of the door, in order to defend it from fresh attacks, and also to prepare a passage for Ferrer; and some among them called to those within (openings were not wanting) that succour had arrived, and that the vicar must get ready "to go quickly--to prison--hem! do you hear?"</s>
<s id="1:66">"Is this the Ferrer who helps in making the proclamations?" asked our Renzo of one of his new neighbours, remembering the vidit Ferrera that the doctor had shown him appended to the famous proclamation, and which he had reiterated in his ears with so great a degree of pertinacity.</s>
<s id="1:67">"The same, the high chancellor," replied he.</s>
<s id="1:68">"He is a worthy man, is he not?"</s>
<s id="1:69">"He is more than worthy; it is he who has lowered the price of bread, against the wishes of others in power, and now he comes to carry the vicar to prison, because he has not acted justly."</s>
<s id="1:70">It is unnecessary to say, that Renzo's feelings were immediately enlisted on the side of Ferrer.</s>
<s id="1:71">He was desirous to approach near him, but the undertaking was no easy one; however, with the decision and strength of a mountaineer, he continued to elbow himself through the crowd, and finally reached the side of the carriage.</s>
<s id="1:72">The carriage had already penetrated into the midst of the crowd, but was here suddenly stopped by one of those obstructions, the unavoidable consequence of a journey like this.</s>
<s id="1:73">The aged Ferrer presented, now at one window of his carriage, now at the other, a countenance full of humility, of sweetness, and benevolence; a countenance which he had always kept in reserve for the day in which he should appear before Don Philip IV.; but he was constrained to make use of it on this occasion.</s>
<s id="1:74">He spoke; but the noise and buzzing of so many voices, and the shouts of applause which they bestowed on him, allowed but little of his discourse to be heard.</s>
<s id="1:75">He had recourse also to gestures; now placing his fingers on his lips, to take from thence a kiss, which his enclosed hands distributed to right and left, as if to render thanks for the favour with which the public regarded him; then he extended them, waving them slowly beyond the window as if to entreat a little space; and now again lowering them politely, as if to request a little silence.</s>
<s id="1:76">When he had succeeded in obtaining, in some measure, his last request, those who were nearest to him heard and repeated his words:--"Bread, abundance.</s>
<s id="1:77">I come to do justice; a little space, if you please." </s>
<s id="1:78">Then, as if stifled and suffocated with the press, and the continual buzzing of so many voices, he threw himself back in the carriage, and with difficulty drawing a long breath, said to himself, "Por mi vida, que de gente."</s>
<s id="1:79">"Long live Ferrer; there is no occasion for fear; you are a brave man.</s>
<s id="1:80">Bread! bread!"</s>
<s id="1:81">"Yes, bread, bread," replied Ferrer, "in abundance! I promise you, I do," placing his hand on his heart.</s>
<s id="1:82">"Clear a passage for me," added he, then, in the loudest voice he could command; "I come to carry him to prison, to inflict on him a just punishment;" and he added, in a very low tone, "Si esta culpable."</s>
<s id="1:83">Then leaning forward to the coachman, he said hastily, "Adelante, Pedro, si puedes."</s>
<s id="1:84">The coachman smiled also on the people with an affected politeness, as if he were some great personage; and, with ineffable grace, he waved the whip slowly from right to left, as if requesting his inconvenient neighbours to retire a little on either side.</s>
<s id="1:85">"Be so kind, gentlemen," said he, "a little space, ever so little, just enough to let us pass."</s>
<s id="1:86">Meanwhile the most active and officious employed themselves in preparing the passage so politely requested. Some made the crowd retire from before the horses with good words, placing their hands on their breast, and pushing them gently, "There, there, a little space, gentlemen."</s>
<s id="1:87">Others pursued the same plan at the sides of the carriage, so that it might pass on without damage to those who surrounded it; which would have subjected the popularity of Antonio Ferrer to great hazard.</s>
<s id="1:88">Renzo, after having been occupied for a few moments in admiring the respectable old man, a little disturbed by vexation, overwhelmed with fatigue, but animated by solicitude, embellished, so to speak, by the hope of wresting a fellow-creature from the pains of death,--Renzo, I say, threw away all idea of retreat.</s>
<s id="1:89">He resolved to assist Ferrer in every way that lay in his power, and not to abandon him until he had accomplished his designs.</s>
<s id="1:90">He united with the others to free the way, and he was certainly not one of the least active or industrious.</s>
<s id="1:91">A passage was opened. </s>
<s id="1:92">"Come on, come on," said a number of them to the coachman, retiring in front of the crowd to maintain the passage clear."</s>
<s id="1:93">"Adelante, presto, con juicio," said his master also to him, and the carriage moved forward.</s>
<s id="1:94">In the midst of the salutes which he lavished promiscuously on the public, Ferrer, with a smile of intelligence, bestowed particular thanks upon those whom he beheld busily employed for him; more than one of these smiles was directed to Renzo, who, in truth, deserved them richly, serving the high chancellor on this day with more devoted zeal than the most intrepid of his secretaries.</s>
<s id="1:95">The young mountaineer was delighted with his condescension, and proud of the honour of having, as he thought, formed a friendship with Antonio Ferrer.</s>
<s id="1:96">The carriage, once in motion, continued its way with more or less slowness, and not without being frequently brought to a full stop.</s>
<s id="1:97">The space to be traversed was short, but, with respect to the time it occupied, it would have appeared interminable, even to one not governed by the holy motive of Ferrer.</s>
<s id="1:98">The people thronged around the carriage, to right and left, as dolphins around a vessel, hurried forward by a tempest.</s>
<s id="1:99">The noise was more piercing and discordant than that of a tempest itself.</s>
<s id="1:100">Ferrer continued to speak to the populace the whole length of the way.</s>
<s id="1:101">"Yes, gentlemen, bread in abundance.</s>
<s id="1:102">I will conduct him to prison; he shall be punished-- si esta culpable.</s>
<s id="1:103">Yes, yes, I will order it so; bread shall be cheap.</s>
<s id="1:104">Asi es. </s>
<s id="1:105">So it shall, I mean. </s>
<s id="1:106">The king our master does not wish his faithful subjects to suffer from hunger.</s>
<s id="1:107">Oh, oh! guardaos.</s>
<s id="1:108">Take care that we do not hurt you, gentlemen, </s>
<s id="1:109">Pedro, adelante, con juicio.</s>
<s id="1:110">Abundance! abundance! a little space, for the love of Heaven!</s>
<s id="1:111">Bread, bread!</s>
<s id="1:112">To prison! to prison!</s>
<s id="1:113">What do you want?" demanded he of a man who had thrust himself partly within the window to howl at him some advice, or petition, or applause, no matter what; but he, without having heard the question, had been drawn back by another, who saw him in danger of being crushed by the wheel.</s>
<s id="1:114">Amidst all this clamour, Ferrer at last gained the house, thanks to his kind auxiliaries.</s>
<s id="1:115">Those who had stationed themselves there had equally laboured to procure the desired result, and had succeeded in dividing the crowd in two, and keeping them back, so that between the door and the carriage there should be an empty space, however small.</s>
<s id="1:116">Renzo, who in acting as a scout and a guide had arrived with the carriage, was able to find a place, whence he could, by making a rampart of his powerful shoulders, see distinctly all that passed.</s>
<s id="1:117">Ferrer breathed again on seeing the place free, and the door still shut,</s>
<s id="1:118">or, to speak more correctly, not yet open.</s>
<s id="1:119">However, the hinges were nearly torn from their fastenings, and the panels shivered in many pieces; so that an opening was made, through which it could be seen that what held it together was the bolt, which, however, was almost twisted from its socket.</s>
<s id="1:120">Through this breach some one cried to those within to open the door, another ran to let down the steps of the carriage, and the old man descended from it, leaning on the arm of this benevolent person.</s>
<s id="1:121">The crowd pressed forward to behold him: curiosity and general attention caused a moment's silence.</s>
<s id="1:122">Ferrer stopped an instant on the steps, turned towards them, and putting his hand to his heart, said, "Bread and justice."</s>
<s id="1:123">Clothed in his toga, with head erect, and step assured, he continued to descend, amid the loud applause that rent the skies.</s>
<s id="1:124">In the mean while the people of the house had opened the door, so as to permit the entrance of so desired a guest; taking care, however, to contract the opening to the space his body would occupy.</s>
<s id="1:125">"Quick, quick!" said he, "open, so that I may enter; and you, brave men, keep back the people, do not let them come behind me--for the love of Heaven!</s>
<s id="1:126">Open a way for us, presently.</s>
<s id="1:127">– Eh! eh! gentlemen, one moment," said he to the people of the house; "softly with this door; let me pass.</s>
<s id="1:128">Oh, my ribs, take care of my ribs.</s>
<s id="1:129">Shut now--no, my gown, my gown!"</s>
<s id="1:130">It would have remained caught within the door if Ferrer had not hastily withdrawn it.</s>
<s id="1:131">The doors, closed in the best manner they could be, were nevertheless supported with bars from within.</s>
<s id="1:132">On the outside, those who had constituted themselves the bodyguard of Ferrer worked with their shoulders, their arms, and their voice to keep the place empty, praying from the bottom of their hearts that they would be expeditious.</s>
<s id="1:133">"Quick, quick!" said Ferrer, as he reached the portico, to the servants who surrounded him, crying, "May your excellency be rewarded!</s>
<s id="1:134">What goodness!</s>
<s id="1:135">Great God, what goodness!" </s>
<s id="1:136">"Quick, quick," repeated Ferrer, "where is this poor man?"</s>
<s id="1:137">The superintendent descended the stairs half led, half carried by his domestics, and pale as death.</s>
<s id="1:138">When he saw who had come to his assistance, he sighed deeply, his pulse returned, and a slight colour tinged his cheek.</s>
<s id="1:139">He hastened to meet Ferrer, saying, "I am in the hands of God and your excellency; </s>
<s id="1:140">but how go hence? we are surrounded on all sides by people who desire my death."</s>
<s id="1:141">"Venga con migo usted, and take courage.</s>
<s id="1:142">My carriage is at the door; quick, quick!"</s>
<s id="1:143">He took him by the hand, and, continuing to encourage him, led him towards the door, saying in his heart, however, Aqui esta el busilis!</s>
<s id="1:144">Dios nos valga! </s>
<s id="1:145">The door, opened; Ferrer appeared first; the superintendent followed, shrinking with fear, and clinging to the protecting toga, as an infant to the gown of its mother.</s>
<s id="1:146">Those who had maintained the space free raised their hands and waved their hats; making in this manner a sort of cloud to conceal the superintendent from the view of the people, and to enable him to enter the carriage, and place himself out of sight.</s>
<s id="1:147">Ferrer followed, and the carriage was closed.</s>
<s id="1:148">The people drew their own conclusions as to what had taken place, and there arose, in consequence, a mingled sound of applauses and imprecations.</s>
<s id="1:149">The return of the carriage might seem to be even more difficult and dangerous; but the willingness of the public to suffer the superintendent to be carried to prison was sufficiently manifest; and the friends of Ferrer had been busy in keeping the way open whilst he was at the house, so that he could return with a little more speed than he went.</s>
<s id="1:150">As it advanced, the crowd, ranged on either side, closed and united their ranks behind it.</s>
<s id="1:151">Ferrer, as soon as he was seated, whispered the superintendent to keep himself concealed in the bottom of the carriage, and not to let himself be seen, for the love of Heaven; there was, however, no need of this advice.</s>
<s id="1:152">It was the policy of the high chancellor, on the contrary, to attract as much of the attention of the populace as possible, and during all this passage, as in the former, he harangued his changeable auditory with a great quantity of sound, and very little sense; interrupting himself continually to breathe into the ear of his invisible companion a few hurried words of Spanish.</s>
<s id="1:153">"Yes, gentlemen, bread and justice. To the castle, to prison under my care.</s>
<s id="1:154">Thanks, thanks, a thousand thanks!</s>
<s id="1:155">No, no, he shall not escape!</s>
<s id="1:156">Por ablanderlos.</s>
<s id="1:157">It is too just, we will examine, we will see.</s>
<s id="1:158">I wish you well.</s>
<s id="1:159">A severe punishment.</s>
<s id="1:160">Esto lo digo por su bien.</s>
<s id="1:161">A just and moderate price, and punishment to those who oppose it.</s>
<s id="1:162">Keep off a little, I pray you.</s>
<s id="1:163">Yes, yes; I am the friend of the people.</s>
<s id="1:164">He shall be punished; it is true; he is a villain, a rascal.</s>
<s id="1:165">Perdone usted.</s>
<s id="1:166">He shall be punished, he shall be punished-- si esta culpable.</s>
<s id="1:167">Yes, yes; we will make the bakers do that which is just.</s>
<s id="1:168">Long live the king! long live the good Milanese, his faithful subjects!</s>
<s id="1:169">Animo estamos ya quasi afuera." </s>
<s id="1:170">They had, in fact, passed through the thickest of the throng, and were rapidly advancing to a place of safety; and now Ferrer gave his lungs a little repose, and looking forward, beheld the succours from Pisa, those Spanish soldiers, who had at last rendered themselves of service, by persuading some of the people to retire to their homes, and by keeping the passage free for the final escape.</s>
<s id="1:171">Upon the arrival of the carriage, they made room, and presented arms to the high chancellor, who bowed to right and left; and to the officer who approached the nearest to salute him he said, accompanying his words with a wave of his hand, "Beso à usted las manos," which the officer interpreted to signify, You have given me much assistance!</s>
<s id="1:172">He might have appropriately added, Cedant arma togæ; but the imagination of Ferrer was not at this moment at liberty to occupy itself with quotations, and, moreover, they would have been addressed to the wind, as the officer did not understand Latin.</s>
<s id="1:173">Pedro felt his accustomed courage revive at the sight of these files of muskets, so respectfully raised; and recovering entirely from his amazement, he urged on his horses, without deigning to take further notice of the few, who were now harmless from their numbers."</s>
<s id="1:174">Levantese, levantese, estamos afueras," said Ferrer to the superintendent, who, re-assured by the cessation of the tumult, the rapid motion of the carriage, and these words of encouragement, drew himself from his corner, and overwhelmed his liberator with thanks.</s>
<s id="1:175">The latter, after having condoled with him on account of his peril, and rejoiced at his deliverance, exclaimed, "Ah! que dira de esto su excelencia, who is already weary of this cursed Casale, because it will not surrender? que dira el conde duque? who trembles if a leaf makes more noise than usual?</s>
<s id="1:176">Que dira el rey nuestro señor? who must necessarily be informed of so great a tumult?</s>
<s id="1:177">And is it at an end?</s>
<s id="1:178">Dios lo sabe."--</s>
<s id="1:179">Ah, as for me, I will have nothing more to do with it, said the superintendent.</s>
<s id="1:180">"I wash my hands of it. </s>
<s id="1:181">I resign my office into the hands of your excellency, and I will go and live in a cavern on a mountain, as a hermit, far, very far from this savage people."</s>
<s id="1:182">"Usted will do that which is best por el servicio de su majestad," replied the high chancellor, gravely.</s>
<s id="1:183">His majesty does not desire my death, replied the superintendent. </s>
<s id="1:184">"Yes, yes, in a cavern, in a cavern far from these cruel people."</s>
<s id="1:185">It is not known what became of this project, as, after conducting the poor man in safety to his castle, our author makes no farther mention of him.</s>
</p>
</text>
