<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<text>
<p id="1">
<s id="1:1">After the famous sedition on St. Martin's day, it may be said that abundance flowed into Milan, as if by enchantment.</s>
<s id="1:2">The shops were well stored with bread, the price of which was no higher than in the most fruitful years; those who, on that terrible day, had howled through the streets, and committed every excess in their power, had now reason to congratulate themselves. But, with the cessation of their alarm, they had not resumed their accustomed quiet;</s>
<s id="1:3"> on the squares, and in the inns, there were congratulations and boastings (although in an under tone) at having hit on a mode of reducing the price of bread.</s>
<s id="1:4">However, in the midst of these popular rejoicings, there reigned a vague apprehension and presentiment that this happiness would be of short duration.</s>
<s id="1:5">They besieged the bakers and vendors of flour with the same pertinacity as during the period of the former factitious and transient abundance, produced by the first tariff of Antony Ferrer.</s>
<s id="1:6">He who had some pence by him converted them immediately into bread and flour, which was piled in chests, in small casks, and even in vessels of earthen ware.</s>
<s id="1:7">In thus attempting to extend the advantages of the moment, their long duration was rendered, I do not say impossible, for it was so already; but even their momentary continuance thus became still more difficult.</s>
<s id="1:8">On the fifteenth of November, Antony Ferrer, "by the order of his excellency," published a decree in which it was forbidden to any one, having any quantity of grain or flour in his house, to purchase more; and to the rest of the people to buy bread beyond that which was necessary for two days, "under pecuniary and corporal penalties at the discretion of his excellency."</s>
<s id="1:9">The decree ordered the anziani (officers of justice), and invited every body, as a duty, to denounce the offenders; it commanded the judges to cause search to be made in every house which might be mentioned to them, issuing at the same time a new command to the bakers to keep their shops well furnished with bread, "under penalty of five years in the galleys, and still greater punishment at the discretion of his excellency."</s>
<s id="1:10">A great effort of imagination would be required to believe that such orders were easy of execution.</s>
<s id="1:11">In commanding the bakers to make such a quantity of bread, means ought to have been afforded for the supply of the material of which it was to be made.</s>
<s id="1:12">In seasons of scarcity, there is always an endeavour to make into bread various kinds of aliment, which, under ordinary circumstances, are consumed under other forms.</s>
<s id="1:13">In this way rice was introduced into the composition of a bread which was called mistura.</s>
<s id="1:14">On the 23d of November, there was a decree issued, which placed at the order of the vicar and twelve members of provision the half of the rice that each possessed; under penalty for selling it without the permission of those lords of the loss of the entire commodity, and a fine of three crowns the bushel.</s>
<s id="1:15">But this rice had to be paid for at a price very disproportioned to that of bread.</s>
<s id="1:16">The burden of supplying this enormous difference was imposed on the city: but the council of ten resolved to send a remonstrance to the governor, on the impossibility of sustaining such a tax; and the governor fixed, by a decree of the 13th of December, the price of rice at twelve livres the bushel.</s>
<s id="1:17">It is also probable, though nowhere expressly stated, that the maximum price for other sorts of grain was fixed by other proclamations.</s>
<s id="1:18">Whilst, by these various measures, bread and flour were kept at a low price in Milan, it consequently happened that crowds of people rushed into the city to supply their wants.</s>
<s id="1:19">Don Gonzalo, to remedy this inconvenience, forbade, by another decree of the 15th of December, the carrying out of the city bread to the value of more than twenty pence; the penalty was a fine of "twenty-five crowns, and in case of inability, a public flogging, and greater punishments still, at the discretion of his excellency."</s>
<s id="1:20">The populace wished to procure abundance by pillage and conflagration, the legal power wished to maintain it by the galleys and the rope.</s>
<s id="1:21">Every method was resorted to to accomplish their purpose, but the reader will soon learn the total failure of them all.</s>
<s id="1:22">It is, besides, easy to see, and not useless to observe, that these strange means had an intimate and necessary connection with each other; each was the inevitable consequence of the preceding, and all, in fact, flowed from the first error, that of fixing upon bread a price so disproportioned to that which ought to have resulted from the real state of things.</s>
<s id="1:23">Such an expedient, however, has always appeared to the populace not only conformable to equity, but very simple and easy of execution; it is then very natural that in the agonies and misery which are the necessary effects of scarcity, they should, if it be in their power, adopt it.</s>
<s id="1:24">But as the consequences begin to be felt, the government is obliged to repair the evil by new laws, forbidding men to do that which previous laws had recently prescribed to them.</s>
<s id="1:25">The principal fruits of the insurrection were these; the destruction or loss of much provision in the insurrection itself, and the rapid consumption of the small quantity of grain then on hand, which should otherwise have lasted until the next harvest.</s>
<s id="1:26">To these general effects may be added, the punishment of four of the populace, who were hung as leaders of the sedition, two before the baker's shop of the crutches, and two at the corner of the street in which was situated the house of the superintendent of provision.</s>
<s id="1:27">The historical relations of this epoch are handed down to us with so little clearness, that it is difficult to ascertain when this arbitrary tariff ceased.</s>
<s id="1:28">But we have numerous accounts of the situation of the country, and especially the city, in the winter of that year and the following spring.</s>
<s id="1:29">In every quarter shops were closed; and the manufactories were, for the most part, deserted; the streets afforded a terrible spectacle of sorrow and desolation; mendicants by profession, now the smallest number, were confounded with the new multitude, disputing for alms with those from whom they had formerly been accustomed to receive them; clerks and servants, dismissed by the merchants and shopkeepers, hardly existing upon some scanty savings; merchants and shopkeepers themselves failing and ruined by the stoppage of trade; artificers wandering from door to door, lying along the pavement, by the houses and churches, soliciting charity, and hesitating between want and shame, emaciated and feeble, reduced by long fasting, and the rigours of the cold which penetrated their tattered clothing; servants, dismissed by their masters, who were incapable of maintaining their accustomed numerous and sumptuous establishments; and the numerous dependents upon the labour of these various classes, old men, women, and children, grouped around their former supporters, or wandered in search of support elsewhere.</s>
<s id="1:30">Among the wretched crowds also might be distinguished, by their long lock, by the remnants of their magnificent apparel, by their carriage and gestures, and by the traces which habit impresses on the countenance, many bravoes, who, having lost in the common misery their criminal means of support, were reduced to an equality of suffering, and with difficulty dragged themselves along the city that they had so often traversed with a proud and ferocious bearing, magnificently armed and attired; they now extended with humility the hand which they had so frequently raised to menace with insolence, or to strike with treachery.</s>
<s id="1:31">But the most dense, livid, and hideous swarm was that of the villagers.</s>
<s id="1:32">These were seen in entire families; husbands with their wives, dragging along their little ones, and supporting in their arms their wretched babies, whilst their own aged and helpless parents followed behind,--all flocked into the city in hopes of obtaining bread.</s>
<s id="1:33">Some, whose houses had been invaded and despoiled by the soldiery, had fled in despair; some, to excite compassion, and render their misery more striking, showed the wounds and bruises they had received in defending their homes; and others, whom this scourge had not reached, had been driven, by the two scourges from which no corner of the country was exempt, sterility and the consequent increase on the price of provisions, to the city, as to the abode of abundance and pious munificence.</s>
<s id="1:34">The new comers might be recognised by their air of angry astonishment and disappointment at finding such an excess of misery where they had hoped to be themselves the peculiar objects of compassion and benevolence.</s>
<s id="1:35">Here, too, might be recognised, in all their varieties of ragged habiliments, in the midst of the general wretchedness, the pale dweller of the marsh, the bronzed countenance of the plain or hill countryman, and the sanguine complexion of the mountaineer, all, however, alike in the hollow eye, ferocious or insane countenance, knotted hair, long and matted beard, attenuated body, shrivelled skin and bony breast,--all alike reduced to the lowest condition of languor, of infantine debility.</s>
<s id="1:36">Heaps of straw and stubble were seen along the walls, and by the gutters, which appeared to be a particular provision of charity for these unfortunate creatures; there their limbs reposed during the night; and in the day they were occupied by those who, exhausted by fatigue and suffering, could no longer bear the weight of their emaciated bodies; sometimes, upon the damp straw a dead body lay extended; sometimes, the miserable spark of life was rekindled in its feeble tenement by timely succour from a hand rich in the means and in the disposition to do good, the hand of the pious Frederick.</s>
<s id="1:37">He had made choice of six priests of ardent charity and robust constitution; and, dividing them into three companies, assigned to each the third of the city as their charge; they were accompanied by porters, laden with food, cordials, and clothing.</s>
<s id="1:38">Each morning these worthy messengers of benevolence passed through the streets, approached those whom they beheld stretched on the pavement, and gave to each their kindly assistance.</s>
<s id="1:39">Those who were too ill to be benefited by temporal succour received from them the last offices of religion.</s>
<s id="1:40">Their assistance was not limited to present relief: the good bishop requested them, wherever it was possible, to furnish more efficacious and permanent comfort, by giving to those who should be in some measure restored to strength money for their future necessities, lest returning want should again plunge them into wretchedness and misery; and to obtain shelter for others who lay exposed in the street in the neighbouring houses, by requesting their inhabitants to receive the poor afflicted ones as boarders, whose expenses would be paid by the cardinal himself.</s>
<s id="1:41">Frederick had not waited for the evil to attain its height, in order to exercise his benevolence, and to devote all the powers of his mind towards its amelioration.</s>
<s id="1:42">By uniting all his means, by practising strict economy, by drawing upon the sums destined to other liberalities, and which had now become of secondary importance, he endeavoured to amass money, in order to employ it entirely for those who were suffering from hunger and its consequences.</s>
<s id="1:43">He bought a quantity of grain, and sent it to the most destitute parts of his diocese; but as the succour was far from adequate to the necessity, he sent with it a great quantity of salt, "with which," says Ripamonti, relating the fact, "the herbs of the field and the leaves of trees were made food for men."</s>
<s id="1:44">He distributed grain and money to the curates of the city; and he himself travelled over it, administering alms, and secretly aiding many indigent families.</s>
<s id="1:45">In the episcopal palace, rice was boiled every day, and dealt out to the necessities of the people, to the extent of 2000 measures.</s>
<s id="1:46">Besides these splendid efforts of a single individual, many other excellent persons, though with less powerful means, strove to mitigate the horrible sufferings of the people: </s>
<s id="1:47">of these sufferers, thousands struggled to grasp the broth or other food provided at different quarters, and thus prolong for a day, at least, their miserable lives; but thousands were still left behind in the struggle, and these generally the weakest,--the aged women and children; and these might be seen, dead and dying from inanition, in every part.</s>
<s id="1:48">But in the midst of these calamities not the least disposition to insurrection appeared.</s>
<s id="1:49">The void that mortality created each day in the miserable multitude was each day more than replenished; there was a perpetual concourse, at first from the neighbouring villages, then from the more distant territories, and, finally, from the Milanese cities.</s>
<s id="1:50">The ordinary spectacle of ordinary times, the contrast of magnificent apparel with rags, and of luxury with poverty, had entirely disappeared.</s>
<s id="1:51">The nobility even wore coarse clothing; some, because the general misery had affected their fortune; others, because they would not insult the wretchedness of the people, or because they feared to provoke the general despair by the display of luxury at such a time.</s>
<s id="1:52">Thus passed the winter and the spring; already had the Tribunal of Health remonstrated with the Tribunal of Provision on the danger to which such mass of misery exposed the city.</s>
<s id="1:53">To prevent contagious diseases, a proposal was made to confine the vagabond beggars in the various hospitals.</s>
<s id="1:54">Whilst this project was under discussion, some approving and others condemning, dead bodies incumbered the streets.</s>
<s id="1:55">The Tribunal of Provision, however, proposed another expedient as more easy and expeditious, which was, to shut up all the mendicants, healthy or diseased, in the lazaretto, and to maintain them there at the expense of the city.</s>
<s id="1:56">This measure was resolved upon, notwithstanding the remonstrances of the Tribunal of Health, who objected that, in so numerous an assemblage, the evil to which they wished to apply a remedy would be greatly augmented.</s>
<s id="1:57">The little order that reigned in the lazaretto, the bad quality of the food, and the standing water which was drank plentifully, soon created numerous maladies.</s>
<s id="1:58">To these causes of mortality, so much the more active from operating on bodies already exhausted or enfeebled, was added the unfavourableness of the season; obstinate rains, followed by more obstinate drought, and violent heat.</s>
<s id="1:59">To these physical evils were added others of a moral nature, despair and wearisomeness in captivity, desire for accustomed habits, regret for cherished beings of whom these unfortunate beings had been deprived; painful apprehension for those who were living, and the continual dread of death, which had itself become a new and powerful cause of the extension of disease.</s>
<s id="1:60">It is not to be wondered at that mortality increased in this species of prison to such a degree as to assume the appearance and deserve the name of pestilence.</s>
<s id="1:61">The number of deaths in the lazaretto soon amounted to a hundred daily.</s>
<s id="1:62">Whilst within these wretched walls, grief, fear, anguish, and rage prevailed, in the Tribunal of Provision, shame, astonishment, and irresolution were equally apparent.</s>
<s id="1:63">They consulted, and now listened to the advice of the Tribunal of Health: finding they could do no better than to undo what they had done, at so much expense and trouble, they opened the doors of the lazaretto, and released all who were well enough to leave it.</s>
<s id="1:64">The city was thus again filled with its former cries, but feebler, and more interrupted; </s>
<s id="1:65">the sick were transported to Santa Maria della Stella, which was then the hospital for the poor, and the greater part perished there.</s>
<s id="1:66">However, the fields began to yield the harvest so long desired, and the troops of peasants left the city for their long prayed for and accustomed labours.</s>
<s id="1:67">The ingenious and inexhaustible charity of the good Frederick still exerted itself; he made a present of a giulio and a sickle to each peasant, who solicited it at the palace.</s>
<s id="1:68">With a plentiful harvest, scarcity ceased to be felt; the mortality, however, continued, in a greater or less degree, until the middle of autumn.</s>
<s id="1:69">It was on the point of ceasing, when a new scourge overwhelmed the city and country.</s>
<s id="1:70">Many events of high historical importance had occurred in this interval of time.</s>
<s id="1:71">The Cardinal Richelieu, after having taken Rochelle, and made a treaty of peace with England, had proposed, effected by his powerful influence in the councils of the French king, that efficacious aid should be sent to the Duke of Nevers; he had also persuaded the king to lead the expedition in person.</s>
<s id="1:72">Whilst the preparations were in progress, the Count of Nassau, imperial commissary, suggested to the new duke in Mantua the expediency of replacing his states in the hands of Ferdinand; intimating that, in case of refusal, an army would be immediately sent by the emperor to occupy them.</s>
<s id="1:73">The duke, who in the most desperate circumstances had rejected so hard a condition, encouraged now by the promised succours from France, was determined still longer to defend himself.</s>
<s id="1:74">The commissary departed, declaring that force would soon decide the matter.</s>
<s id="1:75">In the month of March, the Cardinal Richelieu with the king, at the head of an army, demanded a free passage from the Duke of Savoy; he entered into treaties for the purpose, but nothing was concluded.</s>
<s id="1:76">After a rencounter, in which the French obtained the advantage, a new treaty was entered into, in which the duke stipulated that Don Gonzalo de Cordova should raise the siege of Casale, engaging, in case of his refusal, to unite with the French, and invade the duchy of Milan.</s>
<s id="1:77">Don Gonzalo raised the siege of Casale, and a body of French troops entered it, to reinforce the garrison.</s>
<s id="1:78">The Cardinal Richelieu decided to return to France, on business which he regarded as more urgent; </s>
<s id="1:79">but Girolamo Soranzo, envoy from Venice, offered the most powerful reasons to divert him from this resolution. To these the king and the cardinal paid no attention; they returned with the greatest part of the army, leaving only 6000 men at Suza to occupy the passes and maintain the treaty.</s>
<s id="1:80">Whilst this army departed on one side, that of Ferdinand, commanded by the Count of Collato, advanced on the other.</s>
<s id="1:81">It had invaded the country of the Grisons, and the Valtelline, and was preparing to come down on the Milanese.</s>
<s id="1:82">Besides the usual terrors which such an expectation was calculated to excite, the report was spread, that the plague lurked in the imperial army.</s>
<s id="1:83">Alessandro Tadino, one of the conservators of the public health, was charged by the tribunal to state to the governor the frightful danger which threatened the country, if this army should obtain the pass which opened on Mantua.</s>
<s id="1:84">It appears from all the actions of Gonzalo, that he was possessed by a desire to occupy a great place in history; but, as often happens, history has failed to register one of his most remarkable acts, the answer he returned to this Doctor Tadino; which was, "that he knew not what could be done; that reasons of interest and honour, which had induced the march of the army, were of greater weight than the danger represented; that he would, however, endeavour to act for the best, and that they must trust to Providence."</s>
<s id="1:85">In order, then, to act for the best, their two physicians proposed to the tribunal to forbid, under the most severe penalty, the purchase of any articles of clothing from the soldiers who were about to pass.</s>
<s id="1:86">As to Don Gonzalo, his reply to Doctor Tadino was one of his last acts at Milan, as the ill success of the war, which had been instigated and directed by him, caused him to be displaced in the course of the summer.</s>
<s id="1:87">He was succeeded by Marquis Ambrosio Spinola, who had already acquired the military celebrity in the wars of Flanders which still endures.</s>
<s id="1:88">Meanwhile the German troops had received definite orders to march upon Mantua, and in the month of September they entered the duchy of Milan.</s>
<s id="1:89">At this epoch armies were composed, for the greater part, of adventurers, enlisted by condottieri, who held their commission from some prince, and who sometimes pursued the occupation on their own account, so as to be able to sell themselves and followers together.</s>
<s id="1:90">Men were drawn to this vocation much less by the pay which was assigned to them, than by the hope of pillage, and the charms of licence.</s>
<s id="1:91">There was no fixed or general discipline; and as their pay was very uncertain, the spoils of the countries which they over-ran were tacitly accorded to them by their commanders.</s>
<s id="1:92">It was a saying of the celebrated Wallenstein's, that it was easier to maintain an army of 100,000 men than one of 12,000.</s>
<s id="1:93">And this army of which we are now speaking was part of that which in the thirty years' war had desolated all Germany; it was commanded by one of Wallenstein's lieutenants, and consisted of 28,000 infantry, and 7000 horse.</s>
<s id="1:94">it was commanded by one of Wallenstein's lieutenants, and consisted of 28,000 infantry, and 7000 horse.</s>
<s id="1:95">In descending from the Valtelline towards Milan, they had to coast along the Adda, to the place where it empties into the Po; eight days' march in the duchy of Milan.</s>
<s id="1:96">A great proportion of the inhabitants retired to the mountains, carrying with them their most precious possessions; some remained to watch the sick, or to preserve their dwellings from the flames, or to watch the valuable property which they had buried or concealed; and others remained because they had nothing to lose.</s>
<s id="1:97">When the first detachment arrived at the place where they were to halt, the soldiers scattered themselves through the country; and subjected it at once to pillage; all that could be eaten or carried off disappeared; fields were destroyed, and cottages burnt to the ground; every hiding-place, every method to which people had resorted, in their despair, for the defence of their property, became useless, nay, often resulted in the peculiar injury of the proprietor.</s>
<s id="1:98">Strict search was made throughout every house by the soldiers; they easily detected in the gardens the earth which had been newly dug; they penetrated the caverns in search of the opulent inhabitants, who had taken refuge there, and dragging them to their houses, forced them to declare where they had concealed their treasures.</s>
<s id="1:99">At last they departed; their drums and trumpets were heard receding in the distance, and a temporary calm succeeded to these hours of tumult and affright; but, alas! the sound of drums was again heard, announcing the arrival of another detachment, </s>
<s id="1:100">the soldiers of which, furious at not finding booty, destroyed what the first work of desolation had spared; burned the furniture and the houses, and manifested the most cruel and savage disposition towards the inhabitants. This continued for a period of twenty days, the army containing that number of divisions.</s>
<s id="1:101">Colico was the first territory of the duchy that these demons invaded; they then threw themselves on Bellano, from which they entered and spread themselves in the Valsassina, whence they marched into the territory of Lecco.</s>
</p>
</text>
