<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">The shock which the boat received, as it struck against the shore, aroused Lucy from her reverie; they quitted the bark, and Renzo turned to thank and reward the boatman.</s>
    <s id="1:2">"I will take nothing--nothing," said he: "we are placed on earth to aid one another."</s>
    <s id="1:3">The carriage was ready, the driver seated; its expected occupants took their places, and the horses moved briskly on.</s>
    <s id="1:4">Our travellers arrived then at Monza, which we believe to have been the name of the place to which Father Christopher had directed Renzo, a little after sunrise.</s>
    <s id="1:5">The driver turned to an inn, where he appeared to be well acquainted, and demanded for them a separate room.</s>
    <s id="1:6">He, as well as the boatman, refused the offered recompence of Renzo; like the boatman, he had in view a reward, more distant indeed, but more abundant; he withdrew his hand, and hastened to look after his beast.</s>
    <s id="1:7">After an evening such as we have described, and a night passed in painful thoughts both in regard to recent events and future anticipations--disturbed, indeed, by the frequent joltings of their incommodious vehicle,--our travellers felt a little rest in their retired apartment at the inn highly necessary.</s>
    <s id="1:8">They partook of a small meal together, not more in proportion to the prevailing want, than to their own slender appetites; and recurred with a sigh to the delightful festivities, which, two days before, were to have accompanied their happy union.</s>
    <s id="1:9">Renzo would willingly have remained with his companions all the day, to secure their lodging and perform other little offices.</s>
    <s id="1:10">But they strongly alleged the injunctions of Father Christopher, together with the gossiping to which their continuing together would give rise, so that he at length acquiesced.</s>
    <s id="1:11">Lucy could not conceal her tears; Renzo with difficulty restrained his; and, warmly pressing the hand of Agnes, he pronounced with a voice almost choked, "Till we meet again."</s>
    <s id="1:12">The mother and daughter would have been in great perplexity, had it not been for the kind driver, who had orders to conduct them to the convent, which was at a little distance from the village.</s>
    <s id="1:13">Upon their arrival there, the guide requested the porter to call the superior: he appeared, and the letter of Father Christopher was delivered to him.</s>
    <s id="1:14">"Oh, from Father Christopher!" said he, recognising the handwriting.</s>
    <s id="1:15">His voice and manner told evidently that he uttered the name of one whom he regarded as a particular friend.</s>
    <s id="1:16">During the perusal of the letter, he manifested much surprise and indignation, and, raising his eyes, fixed them on Lucy and her mother with an expression of pity and interest.</s>
    <s id="1:17">When he had finished reading, he remained for a moment thoughtful, and then exclaimed, "There is no one but the signora; if the signora would take upon herself this obligation----" and then addressing them, "My friends," said he, "I will make the effort, and I hope to find you a shelter, more than secure, more than honourable; so that God has provided for you in the best manner.</s>
    <s id="1:18">Will you come with me?"</s>
    <s id="1:19">The females bowed reverently in assent; the friar continued, "Come with me, then, to the monastery of the signora.</s>
    <s id="1:20">But keep yourselves a few steps distant, because there are people who delight to speak evil of others, and God knows how many fine stories might be told, if the superior of the convent was seen walking with a beautiful young woman--with women, I mean."</s>
    <s id="1:21">So saying, he went on before: Lucy blushed; the guide looked at Agnes, who could not conceal a momentary smile; and they all three obeyed the command of the friar, and followed him at a distance.</s>
    <s id="1:22">"Who is the signora?" said Agnes, addressing their conductor.</s>
    <s id="1:23">"The signora," replied he, "is not a nun; that is, not a nun like the others.</s>
    <s id="1:24">She is not the abbess, nor the prioress; for they say that she is one of the youngest of them; but she is from Adam's rib, and her ancestors were great people, who came from Spain; and they call her the signora, to signify that she is a great lady,--every one calls her so, because they say that in this monastery they have never had so noble a person; and her relations down at Milan are very powerful, and in Monza still more so; because her father is the first lord in the country; for which reason she can do as she pleases in the convent,--and moreover people abroad bear her a great respect, and if she undertakes a thing, she makes it succeed; and if this good father induces her to take you under her protection, you will be as safe as at the foot of the altar."</s>
    <s id="1:25">When the superior arrived at the gate of the town, which was defended at that time by an old tower, and part of a dismantled castle, he stopped and looked back to see if they followed him--then advanced towards the monastery, and, remaining on the threshold, awaited their approach.</s>
    <s id="1:26">The guide then took his leave, not without many thanks from Agnes and her daughter for his kindness and faithfulness.</s>
    <s id="1:27">The superior led them to the portress's chamber, and went alone to make the request of the signora.</s>
    <s id="1:28">After a few moments he re-appeared, and with a joyful countenance told them that she would grant them an interview: on their way, he gave them much advice concerning their deportment in her presence.</s>
    <s id="1:29">"She is well disposed towards you," said he, "and has the power to protect you.</s>
    <s id="1:30">Be humble, and respectful; reply with frankness to the questions she will ask you, and when not questioned, be silent."</s>
    <s id="1:31">They passed through a lower chamber, and advanced towards the parlour.</s>
    <s id="1:32">Lucy, who had never been in a monastery before, looked around as she entered it for the signora; but there was no one there; in a few moments, however, she observed the friar approach a small window or grating, behind which she beheld a nun standing.</s>
    <s id="1:33">She appeared about twenty-five years of age; her countenance at first sight produced an impression of beauty, but of beauty prematurely faded.</s>
    <s id="1:34">A black veil hung in folds on either side of her face; below the veil a band of white linen encircled a forehead of different, but not inferior whiteness; another plaited band encompassed the face, and terminated under the chin in a neck handkerchief, or cape, which, extending over the shoulders, covered to the waist the folds of her black robe.</s>
    <s id="1:35">But her forehead was contracted from time to time, as if by some painful emotion; now, her large black eye was fixed steadfastly on your face with an expression of haughty curiosity, then hastily bent down as if to discover some hidden thought; in certain moments an attentive observer would have deemed that they solicited affection, sympathy, and pity; at others, he would have received a transient revelation of hatred, matured by a cruel disposition; when motionless and inattentive, some would have imagined them to express haughty aversion, others would have suspected the labouring of concealed thought, the effort to overcome some secret feeling of her soul, which had more power over it than all surrounding objects.</s>
    <s id="1:36">Her cheeks were delicately formed, but extremely pale and thin; her lips, hardly suffused with a feeble tinge of the rose, seemed to soften into the pallid hue of the cheeks; their movements, like those of her eyes, were sudden, animated, and full of expression and mystery.</s>
    <s id="1:37">Her loftiness of stature was not apparent, owing to an habitual stoop; as well as to her rapid and irregular movements, little becoming a nun, or even a lady.</s>
    <s id="1:38">In her dress itself there was an appearance of studied neglect, which announced a singular character; and from the band around her temples was suffered to escape, through forgetfulness or contempt of the rules which prohibited it, a curl of glossy black hair.</s>
    <s id="1:39">These things made no impression on the minds of Agnes and Lucy, unaccustomed as they were to the sight of a nun; and to the superior it was no novelty--he, as well as many others, had become familiarised to her habit and manners.</s>
    <s id="1:40">She was, as we have said, standing near the grate, against which she leaned languidly, to observe those who were approaching.</s>
    <s id="1:41">"Reverend mother, and most illustrious lady," said the superior, bending low, "this is the poor young woman for whom I have solicited your protection, and this is her mother."</s>
    <s id="1:42">Both mother and daughter bowed reverently. "It is fortunate that I have it in my power," said she, turning to the father, "to do some little service to our good friends the capuchin fathers.</s>
    <s id="1:43">But tell me a little more particularly, the situation of this young woman, that I may be better prepared to act for her advantage."</s>
    <s id="1:44">Lucy blushed, and held down her head.</s>
    <s id="1:45">"You must know, reverend mother," said Agnes--but the father interrupted her;--"This young person, most illustrious lady," continued he, "has been recommended to me, as I have told you, by one of my brethren.</s>
    <s id="1:46">She has been obliged to depart secretly from her native place, in order to escape heavy perils; and she has need for some time of an asylum, where she can remain unknown, and where no one will dare to molest her."</s>
    <s id="1:47">"What perils?" demanded the lady.</s>
    <s id="1:48">"Pray, father, do not talk so enigmatically: you know, we nuns like to hear stories minutely."</s>
    <s id="1:49">"They are perils," replied the father, "that should not be told to the pure ears of the reverend mother."</s>
    <s id="1:50">– "Oh, certainly," said the lady, hastily, and slightly blushing.</s>
    <s id="1:51">Was this the blush of modesty?</s>
    <s id="1:52">He would have doubted it, who should have observed the rapid expression of disdain which accompanied it, or have compared it with that which from time to time diffused itself over the cheek of Lucy.</s>
    <s id="1:53">"It is sufficient to say," resumed the friar, "that a powerful lord--it is not all the rich and noble who make use of the gifts of God for the promotion of his glory, as you do, most illustrious lady--a powerful lord, after having persecuted for a long time this innocent creature with wicked allurements, finding them unavailing, has had recourse to open force, so that she has been obliged to fly from her home."</s>
    <s id="1:54">"Approach, young woman," said the signora.</s>
    <s id="1:55">"I know that the father is truth itself; but no one can be better informed than you with regard to this affair.</s>
    <s id="1:56">To you it belongs to tell us if this lord was an odious persecutor."</s>
    <s id="1:57">Lucy obeyed the first command, and approached the grating; but the second, accompanied as it was with a certain malicious air of doubt, brought a blush over her countenance, and a sense of painful embarrassment, which she found it impossible to overcome.</s>
    <s id="1:58">"Lady----mother----reverend----" stammered she.</s>
    <s id="1:59">Agnes now felt herself authorised to come to her assistance.</s>
    <s id="1:60">"Most illustrious lady," said she, "I can bear testimony that my daughter hates this lord as the devil hates holy water.</s>
    <s id="1:61">I would call him the devil, were it not for your reverend presence.</s>
    <s id="1:62">The case is this: this poor maiden was promised to a good and industrious youth; and if the curate had done his duty----"</s>
    <s id="1:63">You are very ready to speak without being interrogated, interrupted the lady, with an expression of anger on her countenance, which changed it almost to deformity.</s>
    <s id="1:64">"Silence; I have not to be informed that parents have always an answer prepared in the name of their children."</s>
    <s id="1:65">Agnes drew back mortified, and the father guardian signified to Lucy by a look, as well as by a movement of the head, that now was the time to rouse her courage, and not leave her poor mother in the dilemma.</s>
    <s id="1:66">"Reverend lady," said she, "what my mother has told you is the truth.</s>
    <s id="1:67">I willingly engaged myself to the poor youth (and here she became covered with blushes)-—</s>
    <s id="1:68">Pardon me this boldness; but I would not have you think ill of my mother.</s>
    <s id="1:69">And as to this lord (God forgive him!) I would rather die than fall into his hands.</s>
    <s id="1:70">And if you do this deed of charity, be certain, signora, none will pray for you more heartily than those whom you have thus sheltered."</s>
    <s id="1:71">"I believe you," said the lady, with a softened voice; "but we will see you alone.</s>
    <s id="1:72">Not that I need farther explanation, nor other motives to accede to the wishes of the father superior," added she, turning to him with studied politeness.</s>
    <s id="1:73">"Nay," continued she, "I have been thinking, and this is what has occurred to me.</s>
    <s id="1:74">The portress of the monastery has bestowed in marriage, a few days since, her last daughter; these females can occupy her room, and supply her place in the little services which it was her office to perform."</s>
    <s id="1:75">The father would have expressed his thanks, but the lady interrupted him.</s>
    <s id="1:76">"There is no need of ceremony; in case of need, I would not hesitate to ask assistance of the capuchin fathers.</s>
    <s id="1:77">In short," continued she, with a smile, in which appeared a degree of bitter irony, "are we not brothers and sisters?"</s>
    <s id="1:78">So saying, she called a nun, her attendant (by a singular distinction she had two assigned for her private service), and sent her to inform the abbess; she then called the portress, and made with her and Agnes the necessary arrangements.</s>
    <s id="1:79">Then taking leave of the superior, she dismissed Agnes to her room, but retained Lucy.</s>
    <s id="1:80">The signora, who, in presence of a capuchin, had studied her actions and her words, thought no longer of putting a restraint on them before an inexperienced country girl.</s>
    <s id="1:81">Her discourse became by degrees so strange, that, in order to account for it, we will relate the previous history of this unhappy and misguided person.</s>
    <s id="1:82">She was the youngest daughter of the Prince ***, a great Milanese nobleman, who was among the wealthiest of the city.</s>
    <s id="1:83">The magnificent ideas he entertained of his rank, made him suppose his wealth hardly sufficient to support it properly; he therefore determined to preserve his riches with the greatest care.</s>
    <s id="1:84">How many children he had does not clearly appear; it is only known that he had destined to the cloister all the youngest of both sexes, in order to preserve his fortune for the eldest son.</s>
    <s id="1:85">The condition of the unhappy signora had been settled even before her birth; it remained only to be decided whether she were to be a monk or a nun.</s>
    <s id="1:86">At her birth, the prince her father, wishing to give her a name which could recall at every moment the idea of a cloister, and which had been borne by a saint of a noble family, called her Gertrude.</s>
    <s id="1:87">Dolls, clothed like nuns, were the first toys that were put into her hands; then pictures of nuns; and these gifts were accompanied with many injunctions to be careful of them, for they were precious things.</s>
    <s id="1:88">When the prince or princess, or the young prince, who was the only one of the children brought up at home, wished to praise the beauty of the infant, they found no way of expressing their ideas, except in exclamations of this sort, "What a mother abbess!"</s>
    <s id="1:89">But no one ever said directly to her, "Thou must be a nun;" such an intention, however, was understood, and included in every conversation regarding her future destiny.</s>
    <s id="1:90">If, sometimes, the little Gertrude betrayed perversity and impetuosity of temper, they would say to her, "Thou art but a child, and these manners are not becoming: wait till thou art the mother abbess, and then thou shalt command with a rod; thou shalt do whatever pleases thee."</s>
    <s id="1:91">At other times, reprehending her for the freedom and familiarity of her manners, the prince would say, "Such should not be the deportment of one like you; if you wish at some future day to have the respect of all around you, learn now to have more gravity; remember that you will be the first in the monastery, because noble blood bears sway every where."</s>
    <s id="1:92">By such conversations as these the implicit idea was produced in the mind of the child, that she was to be a nun.</s>
    <s id="1:93">The manners of the prince were habitually austere and repulsive; and, with respect to the destination of the child, his resolution appeared fixed as fate.</s>
    <s id="1:94">At six years of age she was placed for her education in the monastery where we find her:</s>
    <s id="1:95">her father, being the most powerful noble in Monza, enjoyed there great authority; and his daughter, consequently, would receive those distinctions, with those allurements, which might lead her to select it for her perpetual abode.</s>
    <s id="1:96">The abbess and nuns, rejoicing at the acquisition of such powerful friendship, received with great gratitude the honour conferred in preference on them, and entered with avidity into the views of the prince; Gertrude experienced all sorts of favours and indulgences, and, child as she was, the respectful attention of the nuns towards her was exercised with the same deference as if she had been the abbess herself!</s>
    <s id="1:97">Not that they were all pledged to draw the poor child into the snare; many acted with simplicity, and through tenderness, merely following the example of those around them; if the suspicions of others were excited, they kept silence, so as not to cause useless disturbance; some, indeed, more discriminating and compassionate, pitied the poor child as being the object of artifices, to the like of which they themselves had been the victims.</s>
    <s id="1:98">Things would have proceeded agreeably to the wishes of all concerned, had Gertrude been the only child in the monastery; but this was not the case; and there were some among her school companions who were destined for the matrimonial state.</s>
    <s id="1:99">The little Gertrude, filled with the idea of her superiority, spoke proudly of her future destiny, expecting thereby to excite their envy at her peculiar honours: with scorn and wonder she perceived that their estimation of them was very different.</s>
    <s id="1:100">To the majestic but circumscribed and cold images of the power of an abbess, they opposed the varied and bright pictures of husband, guests, cities, tournaments, courts, dress, and equipage.</s>
    <s id="1:101">New and strange emotions arose in the mind of Gertrude: her vanity had been cultivated in order to make the cloister desirable to her; and now, easily assimilating itself with the ideas thus presented, she entered into them with all the ardour of her soul.</s>
    <s id="1:102">She replied, that no one could oblige her to take the veil, without her own consent; that she could also marry, inhabit a palace, and enjoy the world; that she could if she wished it; that she would wish it, and did wish it.</s>
    <s id="1:103">The necessity of her own consent, hitherto little considered, became henceforth the ruling thought of her mind; she called it to her aid, at all times, when she desired to luxuriate in the pleasing images of future felicity.</s>
    <s id="1:104">But her fancied enjoyment was impaired by the reflection, which at such moments intruded itself, that her father had irrevocably decided her destiny; and she shuddered at the recollection of his austere manners, which impressed upon all around him the sentiments of a fatal necessity as being necessarily conjoined with whatever he should command.</s>
    <s id="1:105">Then would she compare her condition to that of her more fortunate companions;</s>
    <s id="1:106">and envy soon grew into hatred.</s>
    <s id="1:107">This would manifest itself by a display of present superiority, and sometimes of ill-nature, sarcasm, and spite; at other times her more amiable and gentle qualities would obtain a transitory ascendency.</s>
    <s id="1:108">Thus she passed the period allotted for her education, in dreams of future bliss, mingled with the dread of future misery.</s>
    <s id="1:109">That which she anticipated most distinctly, was external pomp and splendour; and her fancy would often luxuriate in imaginary scenes of grandeur, constructed out of such materials as her memory could faintly and confusedly furnish forth, and the descriptions of her companions supply.</s>
    <s id="1:110">There were moments when these brilliant imaginings were disturbed by the idea of religion; but the religion which had been inculcated to the poor girl did not proscribe pride, but, on the contrary, sanctified it, and proposed it as a means of obtaining terrestrial felicity.</s>
    <s id="1:111">Thus despoiled of its essence, it was no longer religion, but a phantom, which, assuming at times a power over her mind, the unhappy girl was tormented with superstitious dread, and, filled with a confused idea of duties, imagined her repugnance to the cloister to be a crime, which could only be expiated by her voluntary dedication.</s>
    <s id="1:112">There was a law, that no young person could be accepted for the monastic life, without being examined by an ecclesiastic, called the vicar of the nuns, so that it should be made manifest that it was the result of her free election; and this examination could not take place until a year after she had presented her petition for admission, in writing, to the vicar.</s>
    <s id="1:113">The nuns, therefore, who were aware of the projects of her father, undertook to draw from her such a petition; encountering her in one of those moments, when she was assailed by her superstitious fears, they suggested to her the propriety of such a course, and assured her, nevertheless, that it was a mere formality (which was true), and would be without efficacy, unless sanctioned by some after-act of her own.</s>
    <s id="1:114">The petition, however, had scarcely been sent to its destination, when Gertrude repented of having written it; she then repented of this repentance, passing months in incessant vicissitude of feeling.</s>
    <s id="1:115">There was another law, that, at this examination, a young person should not be received, without having remained at least a month at her paternal home.</s>
    <s id="1:116">A year had nearly passed since the petition had been sent, and Gertrude had been warned that she would soon be removed from the monastery, and conducted to her father's house, to take the final steps towards the consummation of that which they held certain.</s>
    <s id="1:117">Not so the poor girl; her mind was busied with plans of escape: in her perplexity, she unbosomed herself to one of her companions, who counselled her to inform her father by letter of the change in her views.</s>
    <s id="1:118">The letter was written and sent; Gertrude remained in great anxiety, expecting a reply, which never came.</s>
    <s id="1:119">A few days after, the abbess took her aside, and, with a mixed expression of contempt and compassion, hinted to her the anger of the prince, and the error she had committed; but that, if she conducted herself well for the future, all would be forgotten.</s>
    <s id="1:120">The poor girl heard, and dared not ask farther explanation.</s>
    <s id="1:121">The day, so ardently desired and so greatly feared, came at last.</s>
    <s id="1:122">The anticipation of the trials that awaited her was forgotten in her tumultuous joy at the sight of the open country, the city, and the houses.</s>
    <s id="1:123">She might well feel thus, after having been for eight years enclosed within the walls of the monastery!</s>
    <s id="1:124">She had previously arranged with her new confidant the part she was to act.</s>
    <s id="1:125">Oh! they will try to force me, thought she: but I will persist, humbly and respectfully; the point is, not to say Yes; and I will not say it.</s>
    <s id="1:126">Or, perhaps they will endeavour to shake my purpose by kindness: but I will weep, I will implore, I will excite their compassion, I will beseech them not to sacrifice me.</s>
    <s id="1:127">But none of her anticipations were verified: her parents and family, with the usual artful policy in such cases, maintained a perfect silence with regard to the subject of her meditations;</s>
    <s id="1:128">they regarded her with looks of contemptuous pity, and appeared to avoid all conversation with her, as if she had rendered herself unworthy of it.</s>
    <s id="1:129">A mysterious anathema appeared to hang over her, and to keep at a distance every member of the household.</s>
    <s id="1:130">If, wearied with this proscription, she endeavoured to enter into conversation, they made her understand indirectly, that by obedience alone could she regain the affections of the family.</s>
    <s id="1:131">But this was precisely the condition to which she could not assent: she therefore continued in her state of excommunication, which unhappily appeared to be, at least partially, the consequence of her own conduct.</s>
    <s id="1:132">Such a state of things formed a sad contrast to the radiant visions which had occupied her imagination.</s>
    <s id="1:133">Her confinement was as strict at home as it had been in the monastery; and she, who had fancied she should enjoy, at least for this brief period, the pleasures of the world, found herself an exile from all society.</s>
    <s id="1:134">At every announcement of a visiter, she was compelled to retire with the elderly persons of the family; and always dined apart whenever a guest was present.</s>
    <s id="1:135">Even the servants of the family appeared to concur with the designs of their master, and to treat her with carelessness, ill concealed by an awkward attempt at formality.</s>
    <s id="1:136">There was one among them, however, who seemed to feel towards her respect and compassion.</s>
    <s id="1:137">This was a handsome page, who equalled, in her imagination, the ideal images of loveliness she had so often fondly cherished.</s>
    <s id="1:138">There was soon apparent a change in her manner, a love of reverie and abstraction, and she no longer appeared to covet the favour of her family; some engrossing thought had taken possession of her mind.</s>
    <s id="1:139">To be brief, she was detected one day in folding a letter, which it had been better she had not written, and which she was obliged to relinquish to her female attendant, who carried it to the prince, her father.</s>
    <s id="1:140">He came immediately to her apartment with the letter in his hand, and in few but terrible words told her, that for the present she should be confined to her chamber, with the society only of the woman who had made the discovery; and intimated for the future still darker punishments.</s>
    <s id="1:141">The page was dismissed, with an imperative command of silence, and solemn threatenings of punishment should he presume to violate it.</s>
    <s id="1:142">Gertrude was then left alone, with her shame, her remorse, and her terror; and the sole company of this woman, whom she hated, as the witness of her fault, and the cause of her disgrace.</s>
    <s id="1:143">The hatred was cordially returned, inasmuch as the attendant found herself reduced to the annoying duty of a jailer, and was made the guardian of a perilous secret for life.</s>
    <s id="1:144">The first confused tumult of her feelings having in some measure subsided, she recalled to mind the dark intimations of her father with regard to some future punishment: what could this be?</s>
    <s id="1:145">It most probably was a return to the monastery at Monza, not as the signorina, but as a guilty wretch, who, loaded with shame, was to be inclosed within its walls for ever!</s>
    <s id="1:146">Now, indeed, her fancy no longer dwelt on the bright visions with which it had been so often busied; they were too much opposed to the sad reality of her present condition.</s>
    <s id="1:147">Such an act would repair all her errors, and change (could she doubt it) in an instant her condition.</s>
    <s id="1:148">The only castle in which Gertrude could imagine a tranquil and honourable asylum, and which was not in the air, was the monastery, in which she now resolved to place herself for ever!</s>
    <s id="1:149">Opposed to this resolution rose up the contemplations of many years past: but times were changed, and to the depth in which Gertrude had fallen, the condition of a nun, revered, obeyed, and feared, formed a bright contrast.</s>
    <s id="1:150">She was perpetually tormented also by her jailer, who, to revenge herself for the confinement imposed on her, failed not to taunt her for her misdemeanor, and to repeat the menaces of her father; or whenever she seemed disposed to relent, and to show something like pity, her tone of protection was still more intolerable.</s>
    <s id="1:151">The predominant desire of Gertrude was to escape from her clutches, and to raise herself to a condition above her anger or her pity.</s>
    <s id="1:152">At the end of four or five long days, with her patience exhausted by the bitter railings of her keeper, she sat herself down in a corner of the chamber, and covering her face with her hands, wept in bitterness of soul.</s>
    <s id="1:153">She experienced an absolute craving for other faces and other sounds than those of her tormentor; </s>
    <s id="1:154">and a sudden joy imparted itself to her mind, from the reflection, that it depended only on herself to be restored to the good-will and attentions of the family.</s>
    <s id="1:155">Mingled with this joy, came repentance for her fault, and a desire to expiate it.</s>
    <s id="1:156">She arose, went to a small table, and taking a pen, wrote to her father, expressing her penitence and her hope, imploring his pardon, and promising to do all that might be required of her.</s>
  </p>
</text>
