<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<text>
<p id="1">
<s id="1:1">The castle of the Unknown was situated above a narrow and shady valley, on the summit of a cliff, which, belonging to a rugged chain of mountains, was nevertheless separated from them by banks, caverns, and precipices.</s>
<s id="1:2">It was only accessible on the side which overlooked the valley.</s>
<s id="1:3">This was a declivity rather steep, but equal, and continued towards the summit: it was occupied as pasture ground, and its lower borders were cultivated, having habitations scattered here and there.</s>
<s id="1:4">The bottom was a bed of stones, through which flowed, according to the season, a small brook, or a large torrent, which served for a boundary between the two territories.</s>
<s id="1:5">The opposite chain of mountains, which formed, as it were, the other wall of the valley, was slightly cultivated towards its base; the rest was composed of precipitous rocks without verdure, and thrown together irregularly and wildly.</s>
<s id="1:6">The scene altogether was one of savage grandeur. </s>
<s id="1:7">From this castle, as the eagle from his eyrie, its lawless owner overlooked his domain, and heard no human sound above him.</s>
<s id="1:8">He could embrace at a view all the environs, the declivities, the abyss, the practicable approaches.</s>
<s id="1:9">To the eyes of one viewing it from above, the winding path which ascended towards the terrible habitation could be perceived throughout its whole course, and from the windows and loopholes, the signor could leisurely count the steps of the person ascending, and examine him with the closest scrutiny.</s>
<s id="1:10">With the garrison of bravoes which he kept at the castle he could defy an army, which he would have crushed in the valley beneath, before an individual could reach the summit.</s>
<s id="1:11">But none, except such as were friends with the master of the castle, dared set foot even in the valley.</s>
<s id="1:12">Tragical stories were related of some who had attempted the dangerous enterprise, but these stories were already of times long past, and none of the young vassals could remember to have encountered a human being in this place, except under his lord's authority.</s>
<s id="1:13">Don Roderick arrived in the middle of the valley, at the foot of the cliff, at the commencement of the rugged and winding path; at this point was a tavern, which might have been called a guard-house; an old sign, with a rising sun painted on both sides, was suspended before the door; but the people gave the place the more appropriate name of Malanotte.</s>
<s id="1:14">At the noise of the approaching cavalcade a young boy, well furnished with swords and pistols, appeared on the threshold of the door; and casting a rapid glance at the party, informed three ruffians, who were playing at cards within the house, of its approach.</s>
<s id="1:15">He who appeared to be the chief among them arose, and recognising a friend of his master, saluted him respectfully; </s>
<s id="1:16">Don Roderick returned the salutation with much politeness, and asked if the signor was at the castle.</s>
<s id="1:17">The man replied in the affirmative; and he, dismounting, threw his horse's bridle to Aimwell, one of his retinue.</s>
<s id="1:18">Then, taking his musket from his shoulder, he gave it to Montanarolo, as if to relieve himself from an useless encumbrance, but in reality because he knew that on this cliff none were permitted to bear arms.</s>
<s id="1:19">Drawing from his pocket some berlinghe, he gave them to Tanabuso, saying, "Wait here till my return; and in the mean time amuse yourselves with these honest people."</s>
<s id="1:20">Then presenting to the chief of the band some crowns of gold for himself and his companions, he ascended the path with Griso.</s>
<s id="1:21">Another bravo belonging to the Unknown, who was on his way to the castle, bore him company; thus sparing him the trouble of declaring his name to whomsoever he should meet.</s>
<s id="1:22">When he arrived at the castle (Griso was left at the gate) he was conducted through a long succession of dark galleries, and various halls hung with muskets, sabres, and other weapons of warfare; each of these halls was guarded by a bravo.</s>
<s id="1:23">After having waited some time, he was admitted to the presence of the Unknown, </s>
<s id="1:24">who advanced to meet him, replying to his salutation, and at the same time, as was his custom, even with his oldest friends, eying him from head to foot.</s>
<s id="1:25">He was tall in stature; and from the baldness of his head, and the deep furrows of his countenance, appeared to be much older than sixty, which was his real age; his countenance and movements, the firmness of his features, and the fire which sparkled from his eyes, indicated a vigour of body as well as of mind which would have been remarkable even in a young man.</s>
<s id="1:26">Don Roderick told him he had come for advice and assistance; that, having embarked in a difficult enterprise, from which his honour did not suffer him to withdraw, he had remembered the promises of one who never promised in vain; and he then related his abominable intrigue.</s>
<s id="1:27">The Unknown, who had already heard something of it, listened with much attention to the recital, both because he naturally loved such relations, and because Friar Christopher, that avowed enemy of tyrants, was concerned in it.</s>
<s id="1:28">Don Roderick spoke of the difficulty of the undertaking, the distance of the place, a monastery, the signora,--but the Unknown, as if prompted by the demon in his heart, interrupted him, saying, that he took the charge of the affair on himself.</s>
<s id="1:29">He wrote down the name of the poor Lucy, and dismissed Don Roderick, saying, "In a little while you will receive news from me."</s>
<s id="1:30">The reader may remember the villain Egidio, who lived near the walls of the monastery into which Lucy had been received; now, he was one of the most intimate colleagues in crime of the Unknown; and this accounts for the promptness with which this lord assumed the charge of the undertaking.</s>
<s id="1:31">However, no sooner was he left alone than he repented of his precipitation.</s>
<s id="1:32">He had for some time experienced, not remorse, but a vague uneasiness on account of his crimes; at every new addition to them, the remembrance of those he had previously committed pressed upon his memory, if not upon his conscience, and loaded it with an intolerable weight.</s>
<s id="1:33">An undefinable repugnance to the commission of crime, such as he had experienced and subdued at the outset of his career, returned with all its force to overwhelm his spirit.</s>
<s id="1:34">The thoughts of the future contributed to render the past more painful.</s>
<s id="1:35">To grow old! to die! and then?</s>
<s id="1:36">And the image of death, which he had so often met undaunted, in face of an enemy, and which seemed to inflame his courage and double his energy--this same image now, in the midnight silence of his castle, quelled his spirit, and impressed him with an awe which he in vain endeavoured to resist.</s>
<s id="1:37">Formerly, the frequent spectacle of violence and murder, inspiring him with a ferocious emulation, had served as a kind of authority against his conscience; now the confused but terrible idea arose in his mind of individual responsibility at the bar of God.</s>
<s id="1:38">The idea of having risen above the crowd of vulgar criminals, and of having left them far behind, an idea which once flattered his pride, now impressed him with a sentiment of fearful solitude; </s>
<s id="1:39">and experiencing at certain moments of despondence the power and presence of that God whose existence he had hitherto neither admitted nor denied, having been wholly immersed in himself, his accumulated crimes rose up, to justify the sentence which was about to condemn him to eternal banishment from the divine presence.</s>
<s id="1:40">But this uneasiness was not suffered to appear, either in his words or his actions; he carefully concealed it under the appearance of more profound and intense ferocity.</s>
<s id="1:41">Regretting the time when he was accustomed to commit iniquity without remorse, without any other solicitude than for its success, he made every effort to recall these habits and feelings; to take pleasure in wickedness; and glory in his shame, in order to convince himself that he was still the same man.</s>
<s id="1:42">This accounts for the promptitude of his promise to Don Roderick: he wished to deprive himself of the chance of hesitation;</s>
<s id="1:43">but, scarcely alone, he felt his resolution fail, and thoughts arose in his mind which almost tempted him to break his word, and expose his weakness to an inferior accomplice.</s>
<s id="1:44">But with a violent effort he put an end to the painful conflict.</s>
<s id="1:45">He sent for Nibbio, one of the most skilful and resolute ministers of his atrocities, and of whom he had made use in his correspondence with Egidio,</s>
<s id="1:46">and ordered him to mount his horse, to go to Monza, to inform Egidio of the affair he had undertaken, and to require his assistance for its accomplishment.</s>
<s id="1:47">The messenger returned sooner than his master expected him with the reply of Egidio; the enterprise was easy and safe; the Unknown had only to send a carriage with two or three bravoes, well disguised; Egidio took charge of the rest.</s>
<s id="1:48">The Unknown, whatever passed in his mind, gave orders to Nibbio to arrange every thing, and to set out immediately on the expedition.</s>
<s id="1:49">If, to perform the horrible service which had been required of him, Egidio had depended only on his ordinary means, he would not certainly have sent back so explicit an answer.</s>
<s id="1:50">But in the asylum of the convent, where every thing appeared as an obstacle, the villain had a means known to himself alone; and that which would have been an insurmountable difficulty to others was to him an instrument of success.</s>
<s id="1:51">We have related how the unhappy signora once lent an ear to his discourse, and the reader may have surmised that this was not the last time; it was only the first step in the path of abomination and blood.</s>
<s id="1:52">The same voice which then addressed her, become imperious through crime, now imposed on her the sacrifice of the innocent girl who had been intrusted to her care.</s>
<s id="1:53">The proposition appeared frightful to Gertrude; to lose Lucy in any manner would have seemed to her a misfortune, a punishment; and to deprive herself of her with criminal perfidy, to add to her crimes by dealing treacherously with the confiding girl, was to take away the only gleam of virtuous enjoyment which had shone upon her mysterious and wicked career.</s>
<s id="1:54">She tried every method to avoid obedience; every method, except the only infallible one, that was in her power.</s>
<s id="1:55">Crime is a severe and inflexible master, against whom we are strong only when we entirely rebel.</s>
<s id="1:56">Gertrude could not resolve on that, and obeyed.</s>
<s id="1:57">The day agreed on came; the hour approached; Gertrude, alone with Lucy, bestowed on her more caresses than ordinary, which the poor girl returned with increasing tenderness, as the lamb licks the hand of the shepherd who entices it without the fold into the murderous power of the butcher who there awaits it.</s>
<s id="1:58">"I want you to do me a great favour; many are ready to obey me, but there is none but yourself whom I can trust.</s>
<s id="1:59">I must speak immediately on an affair of great importance, which I will relate to you some other time, to the superior of the capuchins, who brought you hither, my dear Lucy; but no one must know that I have sent for him.</s>
<s id="1:60">I rely on you to carry a secret message----"</s>
<s id="1:61">Lucy was astonished at such a request, and alleged her reasons for declining to perform it; without her mother! without a companion! in a solitary road! in a strange country!</s>
<s id="1:62">But Gertrude, instructed in an infernal school, showed great astonishment and displeasure at her refusal, after having been loaded with so many benefits; she affected to treat her excuses as frivolous.</s>
<s id="1:63">"In open day! a short distance! a road that Lucy had travelled a few days before!"</s>
<s id="1:64">She said so much, that the poor girl, touched with gratitude and shame, enquired, "What was to be done?"</s>
<s id="1:65">"Go to the convent of the capuchins; ask for the superior, tell him to come here immediately, but to let no one suspect that he comes at my request."</s>
<s id="1:66">"But what shall I say to the portress, who has never seen me go out, and will ask me where I am going?"</s>
<s id="1:67">"Endeavour to pass without being seen; and if you cannot, say you are going to some church to perform your orisons."</s>
<s id="1:68">A new difficulty for Lucy! to tell a falsehood! but the signora was so offended at her refusal, and so ridiculed her for preferring a vain scruple to her gratitude, that the unhappy girl, alarmed rather than convinced, replied, "Well, I will go; may God be my guide and protector."</s>
<s id="1:69">Gertrude, from her grated window, followed her with anxious looks, and when she saw her about to cross the threshold, overcome by irresistible emotion, she cried, "Stop, Lucy."</s>
<s id="1:70">Lucy returned to the window; but another idea, the one accustomed to predominate, had resumed its sway over the mind of the unhappy Gertrude.</s>
<s id="1:71">She affected dissatisfaction at the directions she had given; described the road again to Lucy, and dismissed her: "Do exactly as I have told you, and return quickly."</s>
<s id="1:72">Lucy passed the door of the cloister unobserved, and proceeding on her way with downcast eyes, found, with the aid of the directions given, and her own recollections, the gate of the suburb; timid and trembling, she continued on the high road, until she arrived at that which led to the convent.</s>
<s id="1:73">This road was buried, like the bed of a river, between two high banks, bordered with trees, whose branches united to form an arch above it.</s>
<s id="1:74">On finding it entirely deserted, she felt her fears revive; she hurried on, but gained courage from the sight of a travelling carriage which had stopped a short distance before her; before the door of it, which was open, there stood two travellers looking about, as if uncertain of their way.</s>
<s id="1:75">As she approached, she heard one of them say, "Here is a good girl, who will tell us the way."</s>
<s id="1:76">As she came on a line with the carriage, this same man addressed her: "My good girl, can you tell us the way to Monza?"</s>
<s id="1:77">"You are going in the wrong direction," replied the poor girl; "Monza lies there." As she turned to point it out, his companion (it was Nibbio) seized her by the waist, and lifted her from the ground.</s>
<s id="1:78">Lucy screamed from surprise and terror; the ruffian threw her into the carriage; a third, who was seated in the bottom of it, seized her, and compelled her to sit down before him; another put a handkerchief over her mouth, and stifled her cries.</s>
<s id="1:79">Nibbio then entered the carriage, the door was closed, and the horses set off on a gallop.</s>
<s id="1:80">He who had asked her the perfidious question remained behind; he was an emissary of Egidio, who had watched Lucy when she quitted the convent, and had hastened by a shorter road to inform his colleagues, and wait for her at the place agreed on.</s>
<s id="1:81">But who can describe the terror and anguish of the unfortunate girl?</s>
<s id="1:82">Who can tell what passed in her heart?</s>
<s id="1:83">Cruelly anxious to ascertain her horrible situation, she wildly opened her eyes, but closed them again at the sight of those frightful faces.</s>
<s id="1:84">She struggled in vain.</s>
<s id="1:85">The men held her down in the bottom of the carriage:</s>
<s id="1:86">if she attempted to cry, they drew the handkerchief tightly over her mouth.</s>
<s id="1:87">In the mean while, three gruff voices, endeavouring to assume a tone of humanity, said to her, "Be quiet, be quiet: do not be afraid; we do not wish to harm you."</s>
<s id="1:88">After a while her struggles ceased, she languidly opened her eyes, and the horrible faces before her appeared to blend themselves into one monstrous image; her colour fled, and she fell lifeless into their arms.</s>
<s id="1:89">"Courage, courage," said Nibbio; but Lucy was now beyond the reach of his horrible voice.</s>
<s id="1:90">"The devil! she appears to be dead," said one of them.</s>
<s id="1:91">"If she should really be dead!" </s>
<s id="1:92">"Poh!" said the other, "these fainting fits are common to women; they don't die in this way."</s>
<s id="1:93">"Hush," said Nibbio, "be attentive to your duty, and do not meddle with other affairs.</s>
<s id="1:94">Keep your muskets ready, because this wood we are entering is a nest for robbers.</s>
<s id="1:95">Don't keep them in your hands--the devil! put them behind you.</s>
<s id="1:96">Do you not see that this girl is a tender chicken, who faints at nothing?</s>
<s id="1:97">If she sees that you have arms, she may die in reality.</s>
<s id="1:98">When she comes to her senses, be careful not to frighten her.</s>
<s id="1:99">Touch her not, unless I tell you to do so.</s>
<s id="1:100">I can hold her.</s>
<s id="1:101">Keep quiet, and let me talk to her."</s>
<s id="1:102">Meanwhile the carriage entered the wood.</s>
<s id="1:103">Poor Lucy awoke as from a profound and painful slumber.</s>
<s id="1:104">She opened her eyes, </s>
<s id="1:105">and her horrible situation rushed with full force upon her mind.</s>
<s id="1:106">She struggled again in vain, she attempted to scream,</s>
<s id="1:107">but Nibbio said to her, holding up the handkerchief, "Be tranquil; it is the best thing you can do.</s>
<s id="1:108">We do not wish to harm you; but if you do not keep silence, we must make you."</s>
<s id="1:109">"Let me go.</s>
<s id="1:110">Who are you?</s>
<s id="1:111">Where are you taking me?</s>
<s id="1:112">Why am I here?</s>
<s id="1:113">Let me go, let me go."</s>
<s id="1:114">"I tell you, don't be frightened.</s>
<s id="1:115">You are not a child, and you ought to know that we will not harm you.</s>
<s id="1:116">We might have murdered you before this, if such had been our intention.</s>
<s id="1:117">Be quiet, then."</s>
<s id="1:118">"No, no, let me go; I know you not."</s>
<s id="1:119">"We know you well enough, however."</s>
<s id="1:120">"Oh, holy Virgin!</s>
<s id="1:121">Let me go, for charity's sake.</s>
<s id="1:122">Who are you?</s>
<s id="1:123">Why have you brought me here?"</s>
<s id="1:124">"Because we have been ordered to do so."</s>
<s id="1:125">"Who? who? who ordered you to do it?"</s>
<s id="1:126">"Hush!" said Nibbio, in a severe tone.</s>
<s id="1:127">"Such questions must not be answered."</s>
<s id="1:128">Lucy attempted to throw herself from the door of the carriage, but finding the effort vain, she had recourse again to entreaties, and with her cheeks bathed in tears, and her voice broken by sobs, she continued, "Oh, for the love of heaven, and the holy Virgin, let me go!</s>
<s id="1:129">What harm have I done you?</s>
<s id="1:130">I am a poor creature, who have never injured you; I forgive you all that you have done, and will pray to God for you.</s>
<s id="1:131">If you have a daughter, a wife, or a mother, think what they would suffer in my situation.</s>
<s id="1:132">Remember that we must all die, and that one day you will hope that God will show mercy to you.</s>
<s id="1:133">Let me go, let me go; the Lord will guide me on my way."</s>
<s id="1:134">"We cannot."</s>
<s id="1:135">"You cannot?</s>
<s id="1:136">Great God! why can you not?</s>
<s id="1:137">Where are you taking me?"</s>
<s id="1:138">"We cannot; your supplications are useless.</s>
<s id="1:139">Do not be frightened; we will not harm you. </s>
<s id="1:140">Be quiet; no one shall harm you."</s>
<s id="1:141">More than ever alarmed to perceive that her words produced no effect, Lucy turned to Him who holds in his powerful hand the hearts of men, and can, if he sees fit, soften the most ferocious.</s>
<s id="1:142">She crossed her arms on her breast, and prayed from the depth of her heart, fervently; then again vainly implored to be set free: but we have not the heart to relate more at length this painful journey, which lasted four hours, and which was to be succeeded by many hours of still deeper anguish.</s>
<s id="1:143">At the castle, the Unknown was waiting her arrival with extraordinary solicitude and agitation of mind.</s>
<s id="1:144">Strange, that he who had coldly and calmly disposed of so many lives, and had regarded as nothing the torments he inflicted, should now feel an impression of remorse, almost of terror, at the tyranny he exercised over an unknown girl, an humble peasant!</s>
<s id="1:145">From a high window of his castle, he had for some time looked down upon the valley beneath; at last he saw the carriage approaching slowly at a distance, as if the horses were wearied with their rapid journey.</s>
<s id="1:146">He perceived it, and felt his heart beat violently.</s>
<s id="1:147">"Is she there?" thought he.</s>
<s id="1:148">"What trouble this girl gives me!</s>
<s id="1:149">I must free myself from it."</s>
<s id="1:150">And he prepared himself to send one of his ruffians to meet the carriage, and tell Nibbio to conduct the girl immediately to the castle of Don Roderick; but an imperious No, which made itself heard by his conscience, caused him to relinquish his design.</s>
<s id="1:151">Tormented, however, by the necessity of ordering something to be done, and insupportably weary of waiting the slow approach of the carriage, he sent for an old woman who was attached to his service.</s>
<s id="1:152">This woman had been born in the castle, and had passed her life in it.</s>
<s id="1:153">She had been impressed from infancy with an opinion of the unlimited power of its masters; and her principal maxim was implicit obedience towards them.</s>
<s id="1:154">To the ideas of duty were united sentiments of respect, fear, and servile devotion.</s>
<s id="1:155">When the Unknown became lord of the castle, and began to make such horrible use of his power, she experienced a degree of pain, and at the same time a more profound sentiment of subjection.</s>
<s id="1:156">In time she became habituated to what was daily acting before her: the powerful and unbridled will of such a lord she viewed as an exercise of fated justice.</s>
<s id="1:157">When somewhat advanced in years, she had espoused a servant of the house, who being sent on a hazardous expedition, left his body on the high road, and his wife a widow in the castle.</s>
<s id="1:158">The revenge that her lord took for his death imparted to her a savage consolation, and increased her pride at being under his protection.</s>
<s id="1:159">From that day she rarely set foot beyond the castle walls, and by degrees there remained to her no other idea of human beings, than that of those by whom she was daily surrounded.</s>
<s id="1:160">She was not employed in any particular service, but each one gave her something to do as it pleased him.</s>
<s id="1:161">She had sometimes clothes to mend, food to prepare, and wounds to dress.</s>
<s id="1:162">Commands, reproaches, and thanks were equally mingled with abusive raillery: she went by the appellation of the old woman, and the tone with which the name was uttered varied according to the circumstances and humour of the speaker.</s>
<s id="1:163">Disturbed in her idleness and irritated in her self-love, which were her two ruling passions, she returned these compliments with language in which Satan might have recognised more of his own genius than in that of her persecutors.</s>
<s id="1:164">"You see that carriage below there," said the Unknown.</s>
<s id="1:165">"I do," said she.</s>
<s id="1:166">"Have a litter prepared immediately, and let it carry you to Malanotte.</s>
<s id="1:167">Quick, quick; you must arrive before the carriage; it approaches with the slow step of death.</s>
<s id="1:168">In this carriage there is--there ought to be--a young girl.</s>
<s id="1:169">If she is there, tell Nibbio from me, that he must place her in the litter, and that he must come at once to me.</s>
<s id="1:170">You will get into the litter with her; and when you arrive here, you must take her to your room.</s>
<s id="1:171">If she asks you where you are leading her, whose is this castle, be careful----" </s>
<s id="1:172">"Oh, do not doubt me," said the old woman.</s>
<s id="1:173">"But," pursued the Unknown, "comfort her, encourage her."</s>
<s id="1:174">"What can I say to her?"</s>
<s id="1:175">"What can you say to her?</s>
<s id="1:176">Comfort her, I tell you.</s>
<s id="1:177">Have you arrived at this age, and know not how to administer consolation to the afflicted?</s>
<s id="1:178">Have you never had any sorrow?</s>
<s id="1:179">Have you never been visited by fear?</s>
<s id="1:180">Do you not know the language that consoles in such moments?</s>
<s id="1:181">Speak this language to her then; find it in the remembrance of your own misfortunes.</s>
<s id="1:182">Go directly."</s>
<s id="1:183">When she was gone, he remained some time at the window, gazing at the approaching carriage; he then looked at the setting sun, and the glorious display of clouds about the horizon.</s>
<s id="1:184">He soon withdrew, closed the window, and kept pacing the apartment in a state of uneasy excitement.</s>
</p>
</text>
