<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<text>
<p id="1">
<s id="1:1">As Renzo passed without the walls of the lazaretto, the rain began to fall in torrents.</s>
<s id="1:2">Instead of lamenting, he rejoiced at it: he was delighted with the refreshing air, and with the sound of the falling drops from the plants and foliage which seemed to have new life imparted to them; and breathing more freely in this change of nature, he felt more vividly the change that had occurred in his own destiny.</s>
<s id="1:3">But much would his enjoyment have been increased, could he have surmised what would be seen a few days after.</s>
<s id="1:4">This water carried off, washed away, so to speak, the contagion.</s>
<s id="1:5">If the lazaretto did not restore to the living all the living it still contained, at least from that day it received no more into its vast abyss.</s>
<s id="1:6">At the end of a week, shops were opened, people returned to their houses, quarantine was hardly spoken of, and there remained of the pestilence but a few scattered traces.</s>
<s id="1:7">Our traveller proceeded on full of joy, without having thought where or when he should stop for the night; anxious only to go forward to reach the village, and to proceed immediately to Pasturo in search of Agnes.</s>
<s id="1:8">In the midst of the reminiscences of the horrors and the dangers of the day, there was always present the thought, "I have found her! she is well! she is mine!"</s>
<s id="1:9">And then again he recalled his doubts, his difficulties, his fears, his hopes, that had agitated him that eventful morning!</s>
<s id="1:10">He fancied himself with his hand on the knocker of Don Ferrante's house!</s>
<s id="1:11">And the unfavourable answer!</s>
<s id="1:12">And then those fools who were about to attack him in their madness!</s>
<s id="1:13">And the lazaretto, that vast sepulchre!</s>
<s id="1:14">To have hurried thither to find her, and to have found her!</s>
<s id="1:15">And the procession!</s>
<s id="1:16">What a moment!</s>
<s id="1:17">And now it appeared nothing to him!</s>
<s id="1:18">And the quarter set apart for the women!</s>
<s id="1:19">And there, behind that cabin when he least expected it, that voice! that voice itself!</s>
<s id="1:20">And to see her there!</s>
<s id="1:21">But then her vow!</s>
<s id="1:22">It exists no longer.</s>
<s id="1:23">And his violent hatred against Don Roderick, which had augmented his grief, and shed its venom over his hopes!</s>
<s id="1:24">That also was gone.</s>
<s id="1:25">Indeed, had it not been for his uncertainty concerning Agnes, his anxiety about Father Christopher, and the consciousness that the pestilence still existed, his happiness would have been without alloy.</s>
<s id="1:26">He arrived at Sesto in the evening; the rain had as yet no appearance of ceasing.</s>
<s id="1:27">But Renzo did not stop, his only inconvenience was an extraordinary appetite, which the vicinity of a baker's shop enabled him to mitigate the violence of.</s>
<s id="1:28">When he passed through Monza it was dark night; he succeeded, however, in leaving it by the right road; but what a road! buried between two banks, almost like the bed of a river, it might then, indeed, have been called a river, or rather, an aqueduct; in numerous places were deep holes, from which Renzo could with difficulty extricate himself.</s>
<s id="1:29">But he did as well as he could, without impatience or regret.</s>
<s id="1:30">He reflected that every step brought him nearer to the end of his journey; that the rain would cease when God should please; that day would come in its own time; and that in the mean time the road he had passed over he should not have to travel again.</s>
<s id="1:31">At the break of day he found himself near the Adda.</s>
<s id="1:32">It had not ceased raining; there was still a drizzling shower; the light of the dawn enabled Renzo to see around him.</s>
<s id="1:33">He was in his own country!</s>
<s id="1:34">Who can express his sensations?</s>
<s id="1:35">Those mountains, the Resegone, the territory of Lecco, appeared to belong to him, to be his own!</s>
<s id="1:36">But, looking at himself, he felt that his outward aspect was rather at variance with the exuberant joyousness of his heart; his clothes were wet and clinging to his body, his hat bent out of shape and full of water; his hair hanging straight about his face; while his lower man was encased in a dense covering of mud.</s>
<s id="1:37">He reached Pescate; travelled along the Adda, giving a melancholy glance at Pescarenico; passed the bridge, and crossed the fields, to the house of his friend, who, just risen, was at the door, looking out upon the weather.</s>
<s id="1:38">He beheld the strange figure, covered with mud, and wet to the skin, and yet, so joyous and animated! in his life he had never seen a man, so accoutred, appear so satisfied with himself.</s>
<s id="1:39">"How!" said he, "already here! and in such weather!</s>
<s id="1:40">How have things gone with you?"</s>
<s id="1:41">"She is there! she is there! she is there!"</s>
<s id="1:42">"Well and safe?"</s>
<s id="1:43">"Convalescent, which is better!</s>
<s id="1:44">I have wonderful things to tell you."</s>
<s id="1:45">"But what a state you are in!"</s>
<s id="1:46">"A pretty pickle indeed!"</s>
<s id="1:47">"In truth you might squeeze water enough from your upper half to wash away the mud from the lower.</s>
<s id="1:48">But wait a moment; I will make a fire."</s>
<s id="1:49">"I shall be glad to feel its warmth, I assure you.</s>
<s id="1:50">Do you know where the rain overtook me?</s>
<s id="1:51">Precisely at the door of the lazaretto; but no matter, the weather does its business, and I mine."</s>
<s id="1:52">His friend soon kindled a bright blaze.</s>
<s id="1:53">"Now do me another favour," said Renzo, "bring me the bundle I left above; for before my clothes dry----"</s>
<s id="1:54">Returning with the bundle, his friend said, "You must be hungry; you have had drink enough, no doubt, on the way, but as to eating----"</s>
<s id="1:55">I bought two loaves yesterday at dusk, but truly, I have not eaten them.</s>
<s id="1:56">"Well, I will provide for you."</s>
<s id="1:57">He poured some water in a kettle which hung over the fire, adding, "I will go and milk the cow, and when I return with the milk, the water will be ready, and we will have a good polenta.</s>
<s id="1:58">You, in the mean while, change your clothes."</s>
<s id="1:59">After having allowed him time to perform the troublesome operation, his friend returned, and commenced making the polenta.</s>
<s id="1:60">"I have much to tell you," said Renzo.</s>
<s id="1:61">"If you were to see Milan!</s>
<s id="1:62">and the lazaretto!</s>
<s id="1:63">She is there! you will soon see her here; she will be my wife; you shall be at the wedding, and, pestilence or not, we will be happy for a few hours."</s>
<s id="1:64">On the following morning Renzo set out for Pasturo.</s>
<s id="1:65">On his arrival, he asked concerning Agnes, and learnt that she was in health and safety.</s>
<s id="1:66">He approached her residence, which had been pointed out to him, and called her by name from the street.</s>
<s id="1:67">At the sound of his voice, she rushed to the window, and Renzo, without allowing her time to speak, cried, "Lucy is well; I saw her the day before yesterday; she will be at home shortly; oh, I have so many things to tell you."</s>
<s id="1:68">Overcome by various emotions, Agnes could only articulate, "I will open the door for you."</s>
<s id="1:69">"Stop, stop," said Renzo.</s>
<s id="1:70">"You have not had the plague, I believe?"</s>
<s id="1:71">"No.</s>
<s id="1:72">Have you?"</s>
<s id="1:73">"Yes; but you ought to be prudent.</s>
<s id="1:74">I come from Milan; and have been for two days in the midst of it.</s>
<s id="1:75">It is true I have changed my clothes, but the contagion attaches itself to the flesh, like witchcraft; and since God has preserved you until now, you must take care of yourself until all danger is over; for you are our mother, and I trust we shall live long together as a compensation for the sufferings we have endured, I at least."</s>
<s id="1:76">"But----"</s>
<s id="1:77">There is no longer any but;</s>
<s id="1:78">I know what you would say. You will soon see there is no longer any but; come into the open air, where I may speak to you in safety, and I will tell you all about it."</s>
<s id="1:79">Agnes pointed to a garden adjoining the house.</s>
<s id="1:80">Renzo entered it, and was immediately joined by the anxious and impatient Agnes.</s>
<s id="1:81">They seated themselves opposite each other on two benches.</s>
<s id="1:82">The events he described are already known to our reader, and we will leave to his imagination the numerous exclamations of grief, horror, surprise, and joy, that interrupted the progress of the narrative every moment.</s>
<s id="1:83">The result, however, was an agreement to settle all together at Bergamo, where Renzo had already an advantageous engagement; when would depend on the pestilence and other circumstances; Agnes was to remain where she was, until it should be safe for her to return home; and in the interval she should have regular information of all their movements.</s>
<s id="1:84">He departed, with the additional consolation of having found one so dear to him safe and well.</s>
<s id="1:85">He remained the rest of that day and the following night with his friend, and on the morrow set out for the country of his adoption.</s>
<s id="1:86">He found Bortolo in good health, and in less apprehension of losing it, as within a few days things had rapidly changed for the better.</s>
<s id="1:87">The malignity of the distemper had subsided, and given place to fever indeed, accompanied with tumours, but much more easily cured.</s>
<s id="1:88">The country presented a new aspect; those who had survived the pestilence began to resume their business; masters were preparing for the employment of workmen in every trade; and, above all, in that of weaving silk.</s>
<s id="1:89">Renzo made some preparations for the accommodation of his family, by purchasing and furnishing a neat little cottage, from his hitherto untouched treasure, which the ravages of the plague enabled him to do at small cost.</s>
<s id="1:90">After a few days' stay, he returned by the way of Pasturo, and conducted Agnes to her village home: we will not attempt to describe her feelings at beholding again those well remembered places.</s>
<s id="1:91">She found all things in her cottage as she had left them: it seemed as if angels had watched over the poor widow and her child.</s>
<s id="1:92">Her first care was to get ready with all speed an apartment in her humble abode for that kind friend who had been to her child a second mother.</s>
<s id="1:93">Renzo, on his side, was not idle.</s>
<s id="1:94">He laboured alternately at the widow's garden, and in the service of his hospitable friend.</s>
<s id="1:95">As to his own cottage, it pained him to witness the scene of desolation it presented; and he resolved to dispose of it, and transfer its value to his new country.</s>
<s id="1:96">His re-appearance in the village was a cause of much congratulation to those who had survived the plague.</s>
<s id="1:97">All were anxious to learn his adventures, which had given rise to so many reports among the neighbours.</s>
<s id="1:98">As to Don Abbondio, he exhibited the same apprehension of the marriage as before; the mention of which conjured up to his affrighted fancy the dreaded Don Roderick and his train on the one side, and the almost equally feared cardinal and his arguments on the other.</s>
<s id="1:99">We will now transport the reader for a few moments to Milan.</s>
<s id="1:100">Some days after the visit of Renzo to the lazaretto, Lucy left it with the good widow.</s>
<s id="1:101">A general quarantine having been ordered, they passed the period of it together in the house of the latter.</s>
<s id="1:102">The time was employed in preparing Lucy's wedding clothes; and, the quarantine terminated, they set off on their journey.</s>
<s id="1:103">We could add, they arrived, but, notwithstanding our desire to yield to the impatience of the reader, there are three circumstances which we must not pass over in silence.</s>
<s id="1:104">The first is, that while Lucy was relating her adventures more minutely to the good widow, she recurred to the signora, who had afforded her an asylum, in the convent of Monza, and in return learnt many things which afforded her the solution to numerous mysteries, and filled her with sorrow and astonishment.</s>
<s id="1:105">She learnt, too, that the unfortunate signora, falling afterwards under the most horrible suspicions, had been, by order of the cardinal, transferred to a convent at Milan; that there, after having given herself up for a time to rage and despair, she had at last made her confession and repented of her crimes; and that her present life was one of severe and voluntary penance.</s>
<s id="1:106">If any one desires to know the details of her sad history, it will be found in the author we have so often quoted. Ripamonti.</s>
<s id="1:107">The second is, that Lucy, making enquiries concerning Father Christopher, of every capuchin from the lazaretto, learnt with more grief than surprise that he had died of the pestilence.</s>
<s id="1:108">And the third is, that before quitting Milan, Lucy had a desire to know something concerning her former patrons.</s>
<s id="1:109">The widow accompanied her to their house, where they were informed that both had died of the plague.</s>
<s id="1:110">When we say of Donna Prassede she died, we have said all that is necessary; not so with Don Ferrante, he deserves a little more of our attention, considering his learning.</s>
<s id="1:111">From the commencement of the pestilence, Don Ferrante was one of the most resolute in denying its existence, not indeed like the multitude, with cries of rage, but with arguments which none could accuse of want of concatenation.</s>
<s id="1:112">"In rerum natura," said he, "there are but two kinds of things, substances and accidents; and if I prove that the contagion can neither be one nor the other of these I shall have proved that it does not exist; that it is a chimera.</s>
<s id="1:113">Thus, then: substances are either material or spiritual; that the contagion is a spiritual substance, is so absurd an opinion, that no one would presume to advance it; it is, then, useless to speak of it.</s>
<s id="1:114">Material substances are either simple or compound.</s>
<s id="1:115">Now, the contagion is not a simple substance, and I will prove it in three words.</s>
<s id="1:116">It is not an aerial substance, because, if it were, instead of passing from one body to another, it would fly off to its sphere; it is not a watery substance, because it would be dried up by the wind; it is not igneous, because it would burn; it is not earthy, because it would be visible.</s>
<s id="1:117">Moreover, it is not a compound substance, because it would be sensible to the eye, or to the touch; and who has seen it? or touched it?</s>
<s id="1:118">It remains to see if it be an accident.</s>
<s id="1:119">This is still less probable.</s>
<s id="1:120">The doctors say it is communicated from body to body; this is their Achilles; the pretext for so many useless regulations.</s>
<s id="1:121">Now, supposing it an accident, it would be a transferable accident, which is an incongruity.</s>
<s id="1:122">There is not in all philosophy a more evident thing than this, that an accident cannot pass from one subject to another; so if, to avoid this Scylla, they are reduced to call it an accident produced, they avoid Scylla by falling into Charybdis, because if it be produced, it does not communicate itself, it does not propagate, as they declare.</s>
<s id="1:123">These principles allowed, what is the use of talking of botches and carbuncles?"</s>
<s id="1:124">"It is folly," said one of his hearers.</s>
<s id="1:125">"No, no," resumed Don Ferrante, "I do not say so.</s>
<s id="1:126">Science is science; we must only know how to employ it.</s>
<s id="1:127">Swellings, purple botches, and black carbuncles, are respectable terms, which have a good and proper signification; but I say they have nothing to do with the question.</s>
<s id="1:128">Who denies that there may be and are such things?</s>
<s id="1:129">We must only prove whence they come."</s>
<s id="1:130">Here began the vexations of Don Ferrante.</s>
<s id="1:131">So long as he laughed at the contagion, he found respectful and attentive listeners; but when he came to distinguish and demonstrate that the error of the doctors was, not in affirming that there existed a general and terrible disease, but rather in assigning its cause, then he found them intractable and rebellious, then he no longer dared expose his doctrine, but by shreds and patches.</s>
<s id="1:132">"Here is the true reason," said he, "and those even who maintain other fancies are obliged to acknowledge it.</s>
<s id="1:133">Let them deny, if they can, that there is a fatal conjunction of Jupiter and Saturn.</s>
<s id="1:134">And when has it been said that influences propagate?</s>
<s id="1:135">And would these gentlemen deny the existence of influences?</s>
<s id="1:136">Will they say there are no planets? or will they say that they keep up above, doing nothing, as so many pins in a pincushion?</s>
<s id="1:137">But that which I cannot understand from these doctors is, that they confess we are under so malign a conjunction, and then they tell us, don't touch this, don't touch that, and you will be safe! as if, in avoiding the material contact of terrestrial bodies, we could prevent the virtual effect of celestial bodies.</s>
<s id="1:138">And such a work in burning rags!</s>
<s id="1:139">Poor people! will you burn Jupiter? will you burn Saturn?"</s>
<s id="1:140">His fretus, that is to say, on these grounds, he took no precautions against the pestilence; he caught it, and died, like Metastasio's hero, complaining of the stars.</s>
</p>
</text>
