<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<text>
<p id="1">
<s id="1:1">The bravo hastened back with the intelligence, that the Cardinal Frederick Borromeo, Archbishop of Milan, had arrived the evening before at ***, and was expected to pass the day there.</s>
<s id="1:2">The report of his arrival being spread abroad, the people had been seized with a desire to see him; and the bells were rung in testimony of the happiness his presence conferred, and also to give wider notice of his arrival.</s>
<s id="1:3">The Unknown, left alone, continued to look down into the valley--</s>
<s id="1:4">For a man! all crowding, all eager to see a man!</s>
<s id="1:5">And, nevertheless, each one of them has some demon that torments him; but none, none, a demon like mine; not one has passed such a night as I have.</s>
<s id="1:6">What is there in this man to excite such joy?</s>
<s id="1:7">Some silver which he will scatter among them.--</s>
<s id="1:8">But all are not actuated by such a motive.</s>
<s id="1:9">Well, a few words--</s>
<s id="1:10">Oh! if he had a few words of consolation for me!</s>
<s id="1:11">Yes--why should I not go to him?</s>
<s id="1:12">Why not?</s>
<s id="1:13">I will go.</s>
<s id="1:14">What better can I do?</s>
<s id="1:15">I will go and speak to him; speak to him alone.</s>
<s id="1:16">What shall I say to him?</s>
<s id="1:17">Why, why, that which-—</s>
<s id="1:18">I will hear what he will say to me."</s>
<s id="1:19">Having come to this vague determination, he threw over his shoulders a military cloak, put his pistol and dagger in his girdle, and took from the wall, where it hung, a carabine almost as famous as himself; thus accoutred, he proceeded to Lucy's chamber, and leaving his carabine at the door, he knocked and demanded admittance.</s>
<s id="1:20">The old woman hastened to open the door; he entered, and looking around the room saw Lucy tranquil and silent in the corner of it.</s>
<s id="1:21">"Does she sleep?" asked he in a low voice.</s>
<s id="1:22">"Why did you suffer her to sleep there? </s>
<s id="1:23">Were these my orders?"</s>
<s id="1:24">"I did all I could; but she would neither eat nor come----"</s>
<s id="1:25">Let her sleep then in peace; be careful not to trouble her, and when she wakes--</s>
<s id="1:26">Martha will be in the next chamber, and you must send her for whatever she may want--when she wakes--tell her I----that the signor has gone out for a little while, that he will return, and that--he will do all that she wishes.</s>
<s id="1:27">The old woman was astonished; "She must be some princess," thought she.</s>
<s id="1:28">The Unknown departed, took his carabine, gave orders to Martha to be in waiting, and to a bravo to guard the chamber, and not suffer any one to approach; then leaving the castle, with rapid steps he descended into the valley.</s>
<s id="1:29">The bravoes whom he met ascending the hill, stopped respectfully at his approach, expecting and awaiting orders for some expedition, and were astonished at his whole appearance, and the looks with which he returned their salute.</s>
<s id="1:30">When he reached the public road, his presence made a very different impression; at his approach every one gave way, regarding him with looks of suspicion and wonder; each individual whom he met, cast at him a troubled look, bowed, and slackened his pace, in order to remain behind.</s>
<s id="1:31">He arrived at the village in the midst of the throng; his name quickly spread from mouth to mouth, and a passage was instantly made for him to pass.</s>
<s id="1:32">He enquired of one near him where the cardinal was.</s>
<s id="1:33">"In the house of the curate," replied the person, respectfully pointing to it.</s>
<s id="1:34">He went to it, entered a small court where there were several priests, who looked at him with astonishment and suspicion.</s>
<s id="1:35">He saw, opposite to him, a door open, which led to a small hall, in which were also a great collection of priests.</s>
<s id="1:36">He left his carabine in a corner of the court, and entered the hall.</s>
<s id="1:37">He was received here, likewise, with doubting looks, and whispers; and his name was repeated with infinite awe.</s>
<s id="1:38">He accosted one of them, asking to be directed to the cardinal, as he wished to speak with him.</s>
<s id="1:39">"I am a stranger," replied the priest; and looking around upon the assembly, he called the cross-bearer, who at the time was saying to one near him, "He here!--the famous-—</s>
<s id="1:40">What can have brought him here?</s>
<s id="1:41">Make room!"</s>
<s id="1:42">At this call, which resounded in the general silence, he felt himself compelled to advance.</s>
<s id="1:43">He bowed before the Unknown, raised his eyes in uneasy curiosity to his face, and understanding his request, he stammered out, "I do not know if his illustrious lordship--at this time--is--can--</s>
<s id="1:44">however, I will go and see."</s>
<s id="1:45">And he went, against his will, to carry the message to the cardinal.</s>
<s id="1:46">At this period of our history we cannot do otherwise than rest a while, as the traveller worn out and weary with a long journey through a sterile and savage land, refreshes himself for a season under the shade of a tree, near a fountain of living water.</s>
<s id="1:47">We are about to introduce a person whose name and memory cause an emotion of respect and sympathy; and this emotion is the more grateful from our previous contemplation of wickedness and crime.</s>
<s id="1:48">We trust our readers will excuse our devoting a few moments to this great and good man.</s>
<s id="1:49">Frederick Borromeo, born in the year 1564, was one of those rare characters who have employed a fine genius, the resources of great wealth, the advantages of privileged rank, and unceasing industry, for the discovery and practice of that which was for the good of mankind.</s>
<s id="1:50">His life was like a stream, which, issuing limpid from its native rock, moves on undefiled over various lands; and, clear and limpid still, unites itself with the ocean.</s>
<s id="1:51">In the midst of the pomps and pleasures of the world, he applied himself from his earliest youth to study and obey the precepts of religion; and this application produced in his heart its legitimate fruits.</s>
<s id="1:52">He took truth for the rule of his thoughts and actions.</s>
<s id="1:53">He was taught by it not to look upon this life as a burthen to the many, and a pleasure to the few; but as a scene of activity for all, and of which all must render their account; and the chief aim of his thoughts had ever been to render his life useful and holy.</s>
<s id="1:54">In 1580, he declared his resolution to devote himself to the ministry of the church, and he took the habit from the hands of his cousin Carlos, whom the public voice, even to the present day, has uniformly acknowledged as a saint.</s>
<s id="1:55">He entered a short time after into the college at Pavia, founded by that holy man, and which still bears the name of the family.</s>
<s id="1:56">There, whilst applying himself with assiduity to the occupations prescribed by its rules, he voluntarily imposed on himself, in addition, the task of instructing the poor and ignorant in the principles of the Christian religion, and of visiting, consoling, and aiding the sick.</s>
<s id="1:57">He made use of the authority which was conceded to him by all, to induce his companions to second him in these deeds of benevolence; he steadily refused all worldly advantages, and led a life of self-denial and devotion to the cause of religion and virtue.</s>
<s id="1:58">The complaints of his kindred, who thought the dignity of the house degraded by his plain and simple habits of life, were unavailing.</s>
<s id="1:59">He had another conflict to sustain with the ecclesiastical authorities, who wished to impel him forward to distinction, and make him appear as the prince of the place.</s>
<s id="1:60">From all this, however, he carefully withdrew himself, although at the time but a youth.</s>
<s id="1:61">It would not have been astonishing that, during the life of his cousin Carlos, Frederick should have imitated the example and followed the counsel of so good a man; but it was surprising, that after his death no one could perceive that Frederick, although only twenty years of age, had lost his guardian and guide.</s>
<s id="1:62">The increasing splendour of his talents, his piety, the support of many powerful cardinals, the authority of his family, the name itself, to which Carlos had caused to be associated an idea of sanctity and sacerdotal superiority, all concurred to point him out as a proper subject for ecclesiastical dignity.</s>
<s id="1:63">But he, persuaded in the depth of his soul of that which no true Christian can deny, that a man has no real superiority over others, but in devotion to their good, dreaded distinction, and sought to avoid it.</s>
<s id="1:64">He did not wish to escape from the obligation to serve his neighbour; his life was but one scene of such services; but he did not esteem himself worthy of so high and responsible an office.</s>
<s id="1:65">Governed by such feelings, in 1595, when Clement VIII. offered him the archbishopric of Milan, he refused it without hesitation, but was finally obliged to yield to the express command of the pope.</s>
<s id="1:66">Such demonstrations are neither difficult nor rare; it is no greater effort for hypocrisy to assume them, than for raillery to deride them.</s>
<s id="1:67">But are they not also the natural expression of wise and virtuous feeling?</s>
<s id="1:68">The life is the test of sincerity; and though all the hypocrites in the world had assumed the expression of virtuous sentiments, yet the sentiments themselves will always command our respect and veneration, when their genuineness is evinced by a life of disinterestedness and self-sacrifice.</s>
<s id="1:69">Frederick, as archbishop, was careful to reserve for himself only that which was barely necessary, of his time and his wealth: he said, as all the world says, that the ecclesiastical revenues are the patrimony of the poor; and we shall see how he put this maxim in practice.</s>
<s id="1:70">He caused an estimate to be made of the sum necessary for his expenses, and for those employed in his service: finding it to be 600 sequins, he ordered that amount to be taken from his patrimonial revenues for the supply of his table.</s>
<s id="1:71">He exercised such minute economy with regard to himself, that he did not relinquish any article of dress until it was entirely worn out; but he joined to these habits of extreme simplicity, an exquisite neatness, which was remarkable in this age of luxury and uncleanliness.</s>
<s id="1:72">He did more: in order that nothing should be lost from the fragments of his frugal table, he assigned them to a hospital for the poor, and a servant came every day to gather the remnants for that purpose.</s>
<s id="1:73">From the attention which he paid to such minutiæ, we might form a contracted idea of his mind, as being incapable of elevating itself to more extensive designs, were it not for the Ambrosian library, which remains a monument of his liberality and magnificence.</s>
<s id="1:74">To furnish it with books and manuscripts, besides those which he had already collected, he sent eight of the most skilful and learned men to make purchases of them in France, Spain, Germany, Italy, Flanders, Greece, Lebanon, and Jerusalem.</s>
<s id="1:75">He succeeded in collecting 30,000 printed volumes, and 14,000 manuscripts.</s>
<s id="1:76">He joined to the library a college of doctors: these doctors were nine in number, and supported by him as long as he lived; after his death, the ordinary revenues not being sufficient for the expense, they were reduced to two.</s>
<s id="1:77">Their duty consisted in the cultivation of the various branches of human knowledge, theology, history, belles lettres, ecclesiastical antiquities, and Oriental languages.</s>
<s id="1:78">Each one was obliged to publish some work on the subject to which he had particularly applied himself.</s>
<s id="1:79">He added to this a college, which he called Trilingue, for the study of the Greek, Latin, and Italian languages; and a college of pupils, who were instructed in these languages to become professors in their turn.</s>
<s id="1:80">He united to these also a printing establishment for the Oriental languages, for Hebrew, Chaldee, Arabic, Persian, and Armenian; a gallery of pictures, and another of statues; and a school for the three principal arts of design.</s>
<s id="1:81">For the latter, he was at no loss to find professors; but this was not the case with regard to the Eastern languages, which were at this time but little cultivated in Europe.</s>
<s id="1:82">In the orders which he left for the government and regulations of the library, we perceive a perpetual attention to utility, admirable in itself, and much in advance of the ordinary ideas of his time.</s>
<s id="1:83">He prescribed to the librarian the cultivation of a regular correspondence with the learned men of Europe, to keep himself acquainted with the state of science, and to procure every new and important work; he also charged him to point out to young students the books necessary for them, and, whether natives or foreigners, to afford them every possible facility in making use of those of the library.</s>
<s id="1:84">There is a history of the Ambrosian library by one Pierpaolo Bosca, who was librarian after the death of Frederick, in which all the excellent regulations are minutely detailed.</s>
<s id="1:85">Other libraries existed in Italy, but with little benefit to the studious: the books were carefully concealed from view in their cases, and inaccessible to all, except on rare occasions, and with the utmost difficulty.</s>
<s id="1:86">A book might then be seen, but not studied.</s>
<s id="1:87">It is useless to enquire what were the fruits of these establishments of Borromeo, but we must admire the generosity, judgment, and benevolence of the man who could undertake and execute such things, in the midst of the ignorance, inertness, and general indifference which surrounded him.</s>
<s id="1:88">And in attention to public, he was not unmindful of private benevolence; indeed, his whole life was a perpetual almsgiving; on the occasion of the famine of which our history has spoken, we may have to relate more than one instance of his wisdom and generosity.</s>
<s id="1:89">The inexhaustible charity of the man shone as much in his private charities, as in his splendid and magnificent public establishments already recorded.</s>
<s id="1:90">On one occasion he saved a young lady from being immured in a convent against her wish.</s>
<s id="1:91">Her selfish father pretended he could not marry her suitably without a portion of 4000 crowns. </s>
<s id="1:92">The bishop advanced the money.</s>
<s id="1:93">Easy of access, he made it a principle to receive the poor who applied to him, with kindness and affection.</s>
<s id="1:94">And on this point he was obliged to dispute with the nobility, who wished to keep him to their standard of action.</s>
<s id="1:95">One day, whilst visiting among the mountaineers, and instructing some poor children, Frederick bestowed caresses on them.</s>
<s id="1:96">A nobleman who was present, warned him to be careful, as the children were dirty and disgusting.</s>
<s id="1:97">The good bishop, not without indignation, replied, "These souls are committed to my care; these children may never see me again; and are you not willing that I should embrace them?"</s>
<s id="1:98">He, however, seldom felt indignation or anger: he was admired for a placability, a sweetness of manner nearly imperturbable; which, however, was not natural to him, but the effect of continual combat against a quick and hasty disposition.</s>
<s id="1:99">If ever he appeared harsh, it was to those subordinate pastors, whom he found guilty of avarice, or negligence, or any other vice opposed to the spirit of their high calling.</s>
<s id="1:100">With regard to his own interests or temporal glory, he exhibited no emotion, either of joy or regret; admirable indeed, if his spirit was in reality not affected by these emotions; but more admirable still, if viewed as the result of continued and unremitted effort to subdue them.</s>
<s id="1:101">And amidst all the important cares with which he was occupied, he did not neglect the cultivation of his mind; he devoted himself to literature with so much ardour, that he became one of the most learned men of his time.</s>
<s id="1:102">We must not, however, conceal that he adopted with firm persuasion, and maintained with constancy, certain opinions, which at this day would appear singular and ill-founded; these, however, were the errors of his time, and not his own.</s>
<s id="1:103">Our readers may perhaps enquire, if so learned and studious a man has left no monument of his labours and studies?</s>
<s id="1:104">His works, great and small, Latin and Italian, printed as well as manuscript, amount to more than a hundred; they are preserved with care in the library which he founded.</s>
<s id="1:105">They are composed of moral treatises, sermons, historical dissertations, sacred and profane antiquities, literature, the fine arts, &amp;c.</s>
<s id="1:106">And what is the reason that they are so little known, so little sought for?</s>
<s id="1:107">We cannot enter into the causes of this phenomenon, as our explanation might not be satisfactory to our readers.</s>
<s id="1:108">So that we had better resume the course of our history, in relating facts concerning this extraordinary man.</s>
</p>
</text>
