<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<text>
<p id="1">
<s id="1:1">The next morning, in the village of Lucy, and throughout all the territory of Lecco, nothing was talked of but herself, the Unknown, the archbishop, and another person, who, although generally desirous to be talked of, would willingly have been forgotten on this occasion,--we mean Don Roderick.</s>
<s id="1:2">Not that, previous to this period, the villagers had not conversed much of his actions, in secret, to those in whom they had perfect confidence; </s>
<s id="1:3">but now they could no longer contain themselves, nor surpress many enquiries on the marvellous events in which two persons so famous had played a part.</s>
<s id="1:4">In comparison of these two personages, Signor Don Roderick appeared rather insignificant,</s>
<s id="1:5">and all agreed in rejoicing over the ill success of his iniquitous designs; </s>
<s id="1:6">but these rejoicings were still, in some measure, moderated by fears of the bravoes by whom he was surrounded.</s>
<s id="1:7">A good portion of the public censure was bestowed on his friends and courtiers.</s>
<s id="1:8">It did not spare the Signor Podestà, always deaf and dumb and blind to the deeds of this tyrant, but these opinions were expressed in an under-tone, because the Podestà had his officers.</s>
<s id="1:9">Such regard was not paid to Doctor Azzecca Garbugli, who had only his tricks and his verbiage to employ for his defence; and as to the whole tribe of sycophants, resembling him, they were so pointed at, and eyed askance, that for some time they thought it most prudent to keep themselves within doors.</s>
<s id="1:10">Don Roderick, struck, as by a thunderbolt, with the unexpected intelligence, so different from that which he had been anticipating from day to day, kept himself shut up in his castle, alone with his bravoes, devouring his rage for the space of two days, and on the third set off for Milan.</s>
<s id="1:11">If there had only existed the murmurs of the people, notwithstanding things had gone so far, he would perhaps have remained expressly to brave them; but he felt himself compelled to quit the field of contest, by the certain information that the cardinal was coming to the village.</s>
<s id="1:12">The count, his uncle, who knew nothing of the story but what Attilio had told him, would certainly require him to be one of the first to visit the cardinal, in order to obtain in public the most distinguished reception from him.</s>
<s id="1:13">The count would require it, because it was an important opportunity for making known in what esteem the house was held by his powerful eminence.</s>
<s id="1:14">To escape such a dilemma, Don Roderick, having risen before the sun, threw himself into a carriage with Griso, and, followed by the rest of the bravoes, retired like a fugitive, like (if we may be permitted to elevate him by such a comparison), like Catiline from Rome, foaming with rage, and threatening a speedy return to accomplish his revenge.</s>
<s id="1:15">Meanwhile the cardinal approached, visiting every day one of the parishes situated in the territory of Lecco.</s>
<s id="1:16">On the day he was expected in the village, great preparations were made for his reception.</s>
<s id="1:17">At the entrance of the village, near the cottage of Agnes, a triumphal arch was erected, constructed of wood, covered with moss and straw, and ornamented with green boughs of birch and holly.</s>
<s id="1:18">The front of the church was adorned with tapestry; from every window of the houses were suspended quilts and sheets, intended for drapery; every thing, in short, whether in good taste or bad, was displayed in honour of this extraordinary occasion.</s>
<s id="1:19">At the hour of vespers (which was the hour Frederick usually selected to arrive at the churches which he visited), those who had not gone to church, the old men, women, and the youngest of the children, went forth, in procession, to meet their expected guest, headed by Don Abbondio.</s>
<s id="1:20">The poor curate was sad in the midst of the public joy; the tumult bewildered him; the movement of so many people, before and behind, disturbed him; and, moreover, he was tormented by the secret apprehension that the women had tattled, and that he should be obliged to render an account of his conduct to the cardinal.</s>
<s id="1:21">Frederick appeared at last, or rather the crowd appeared, in the midst of which was his litter, and the retinue surrounding it.</s>
<s id="1:22">The persons who followed Don Abbondio scattered and mingled themselves with the crowd, notwithstanding all his remonstrances; and he, poor man, finding himself deserted by them, went to the church, there to await the cardinal's approach.</s>
<s id="1:23">The cardinal advanced, bestowing benedictions with his hands, and receiving them in return from the mouths of the people, who were with difficulty kept back by his attendants.</s>
<s id="1:24">Being of the same village as Lucy, these peasants were desirous of rendering to the archbishop peculiar demonstrations of respect, but this was not practicable, inasmuch as, wherever he went, he was received with every possible honour.</s>
<s id="1:25">In the very commencement of his pontificate, at his first solemn entrance into the cathedral, the concourse had been so great that his life was in peril.</s>
<s id="1:26">Some gentlemen, who were near him, drew their swords to keep back and alarm the crowd.</s>
<s id="1:27">Such was the rude violence of the times, that even in the general disposition to do honour to their archbishop, they were on the point of crushing him: and this defence would not have been sufficient, if two priests, of great vigour and presence of mind, had not raised him in their arms, and carried him from the church door to the foot of the great altar.</s>
<s id="1:28">His very first entrance into the church, therefore, might be recorded amidst his pastoral labours and the dangers he had run.</s>
<s id="1:29">Entering the church, the cardinal advanced to the altar, and after having prayed some time, he addressed, as was his custom, some words to the people, on his love for them, on his desire for their salvation, and how they should dispose their minds for the duties of the morrow.</s>
<s id="1:30">He then withdrew to the house of the curate, and among other questions which he put to him, he interrogated him with regard to the character and conduct of Renzo.</s>
<s id="1:31">Don Abbondio replied that he was rather choleric and obstinate: but as the cardinal made more special and precise enquiries, he was obliged to confess that he was an honest peaceable youth, and even he himself could not comprehend how he had committed at Milan the conduct which had been imputed to him.</s>
<s id="1:32">"As to the young girl," continued the cardinal, "do you think she can return now with safety to her house?"</s>
<s id="1:33">"At present," replied Don Abbondio, "she can come and remain for a while.</s>
<s id="1:34">I say, at present, but," added he with a sigh, "your illustrious lordship should be always near at hand."</s>
<s id="1:35">"God is always present," said the cardinal.</s>
<s id="1:36">"But I will use my efforts to secure a place of safety for her."</s>
<s id="1:37">Before dismissing Don Abbondio, he ordered him to send a litter, on the following day, for Lucy and her mother.</s>
<s id="1:38">Don Abbondio went away quite pleased that the cardinal had talked to him of the young couple, without even alluding to his refusal to marry them.</s>
<s id="1:39">"He knows nothing of it," said he; "Agnes has kept silence! wonderful!</s>
<s id="1:40">She will see him again, 'tis true, but she shall have further instructions from me, so she shall."</s>
<s id="1:41">He little thought, poor man, that Frederick had only deferred the enquiry until he should have more leisure to learn the reasons of his conduct.</s>
<s id="1:42">But the solicitude of the good prelate for the disposal of Lucy had been rendered useless, by a circumstance which we will relate.</s>
<s id="1:43">The two females had as far as possible resumed, for the few days they had to pass under the hospitable roof of the tailor, their usual manner of life.</s>
<s id="1:44">As she had done at the monastery, Lucy, in a small chamber apart, employed herself in sewing; and Agnes, keeping much at home, remained for the most part with her daughter.</s>
<s id="1:45">Their conversations were affectionate and sorrowful; both were prepared for a separation, since the sheep could not dwell in the neighbourhood of the wolf.</s>
<s id="1:46">But how long was this separation to continue?</s>
<s id="1:47">The future was dark and inexplicable, </s>
<s id="1:48">but Agnes, notwithstanding, was full of agreeable anticipation.</s>
<s id="1:49">"After all," said she, "if no irreparable misfortune has befallen Renzo, we shall soon hear from him.</s>
<s id="1:50">If he has found employment, (and who can doubt it?) and if he keeps the faith he has sworn to you, why cannot we go and live with him?"</s>
<s id="1:51">Her daughter felt as much sorrow in listening to her hopes, as difficulty in replying to them.</s>
<s id="1:52">She still kept her secret in her heart; and although troubled at the idea of concealment with so good a mother, she was nevertheless restrained by a thousand fears from communicating it.</s>
<s id="1:53">Her plans were, indeed, very different from those of her mother, or rather, she had none, having committed the future into the hands of Providence; she therefore endeavoured to change the subject, saying in general terms that her only hope was to be permanently re-united to her mother.</s>
<s id="1:54">"Do you know why you feel thus?" said Agnes; "you have suffered so much, that it seems impossible to you that things can turn out happily.</s>
<s id="1:55">But let God work; and if-—</s>
<s id="1:56">Let a ray of hope come--a single ray, and then we shall see that you will think differently."</s>
<s id="1:57">Lucy and her mother entertained a lively friendship for their kind hosts, which was warmly reciprocated; and between whom can friendship exist more in its purity, than between the benefactor and the recipients of the benefit, when both have kind hearts!</s>
<s id="1:58">Agnes, especially, had long gossips with the mistress of the house, and the tailor afforded them much amusement by his tales and moral discourses; at dinner particularly he had always something to relate of the sword of Roland, or of the Fathers of the Thebaid.</s>
<s id="1:59">At some miles' distance from the village there dwelt a certain Don Ferrante, and Donna Prassede his wife; the latter was a woman of high birth, somewhat advanced in age, and exceedingly inclined to do good; which is surely the most praiseworthy employment one can be engaged on in this world; but which, indulged in without judgment, may be rendered hurtful, like all other good things.</s>
<s id="1:60">To do good, we must have correct ideas of good in itself considered, and this can be acquired only by control over our own hearts.</s>
<s id="1:61">Donna Prassede governed herself with her ideas, as some do with their friends; she had very few, but to these she was much attached.</s>
<s id="1:62">Among these few, were a number unfortunately a little narrow and unreasonable, and they were not those she loved the least.</s>
<s id="1:63">Thence it happened that she regarded things as good, which were not really so, and that she used means which were calculated to promote the very opposite of that which she intended; to this perversion of her intellect may also be attributed the fact, that she esteemed all measures to be lawful to her who was bent on the performance of duty.</s>
<s id="1:64">In short, with good intentions, her moral perceptions were in no small degree distorted.</s>
<s id="1:65">Hearing the wonderful story of Lucy, she was seized with a desire to know her, and immediately sent her carriage for the mother and daughter.</s>
<s id="1:66">Lucy, having no desire to go, requested the tailor to find some excuse for her; if they had been common people, who desired to make her acquaintance, the tailor would willingly have rendered her the service, but, under such circumstances, refusal appeared to him a species of insult.</s>
<s id="1:67">He uttered so many exclamations, such as, that it was not customary--that it was a high family--that it was out of the question to say No to such people--that it might make their fortune--and that, in addition to all this, Donna Prassede was a saint,--that Lucy was finally obliged to yield, especially as Agnes seconded the remonstrances and arguments of the tailor.</s>
<s id="1:68">The high-born dame received them with many congratulations; she questioned and advised them with an air of conscious superiority, which was, however, tempered by so many soft and humble expressions, and mingled with so much zeal and devotion, that Agnes and Lucy soon felt themselves relieved from the painful restraint her mere presence had at first imposed on them.</s>
<s id="1:69">In brief, Donna Prassede, learning that the cardinal wished to procure an asylum for Lucy, and impelled by the desire to second, and at the same time to anticipate, his good intention, offered to take the young girl to her house, where there would be no other service required of her than to direct the labours of the needle or the spindle.</s>
<s id="1:70">She added, that she herself would inform the cardinal of the arrangement.</s>
<s id="1:71">Besides the obvious and ordinary benefit conferred by her invitation, Donna Prassede proposed to herself another, which she deemed to be peculiarly important; this was to school impatience, and to place in the right path a young creature who had much need of guidance.</s>
<s id="1:72">The first time she heard Lucy spoken of, she was immediately persuaded that in one so young, who had betrothed herself to a robber, a criminal, a fugitive from justice such as Renzo, there must be some corruption, some concealed vice.</s>
<s id="1:73">"Tell me what company you keep, and I will tell you who you are."</s>
<s id="1:74">The visit of Lucy had confirmed her opinion;</s>
<s id="1:75">she appeared, indeed, to be an artless girl,</s>
<s id="1:76">but who could tell the cause of her downcast looks and timid replies?</s>
<s id="1:77">There was no great effort of mind necessary to perceive that the maiden had opinions of her own.</s>
<s id="1:78">Her blushes, sighs, and particularly her large and beautiful eyes, did not please Donna Prassede at all.</s>
<s id="1:79">She regarded it as certain as if she had been told it by having authority, that the misfortunes of Lucy were a punishment from Heaven for her connection with that villain, and a warning to withdraw herself from him entirely.</s>
<s id="1:80">That settled the determination to lend her co-operation to further so desirable a work; for as she frequently said to herself and others, "Was it not her constant study to second the will of Heaven?"</s>
<s id="1:81">But, alas! she often fell into the terrible mistake of taking for the will of Heaven, the vain imaginings of her own brain.</s>
<s id="1:82">However, she was on the present occasion very careful not to exhibit any of her proposed intentions.</s>
<s id="1:83">It was one of her maxims, that the first rule to be observed in accomplishing a good design, is to keep your motives to yourself.</s>
<s id="1:84">Excepting the painful necessity of separation the offer appeared to both mother and daughter very inviting, were it only on account of the short distance from the castle to their village.</s>
<s id="1:85">Reading in each other's countenance their mutual assent, they accepted with many thanks the kindness of Donna Prassede, who renewing her kind promises, said she would soon send them a letter to present to the cardinal.</s>
<s id="1:86">The two females having departed, she requested Don Ferrante to write a letter, who, being a literary and learned man, was employed as her secretary on occasions of importance.</s>
<s id="1:87">In an affair of this sort, Don Ferrante did his best, and he gave the original to his wife in order that she could copy it; he warmly recommended to her an attention to the orthography, as orthography was among the great number of things he had studied, and among the small number over which he had control in his family.</s>
<s id="1:88">The letter was forthwith copied and sent to the tailor's house.</s>
<s id="1:89">These events occurred a few days before the cardinal had despatched a litter to bring the mother and daughter to their abode.</s>
<s id="1:90">Upon their arrival they went to the parsonage;</s>
<s id="1:91">orders having been left for their immediate admittance to the presence of the cardinal.</s>
<s id="1:92">The chaplain, who conducted them thither, gave them many instructions with regard to the ceremony to be used with him, and the titles to be given him; it was a continual torment to the poor man to behold the little ceremony that reigned around the good archbishop in this respect.</s>
<s id="1:93">"This results," he was accustomed to say, "from the excessive goodness of this blessed man--from his great familiarity."</s>
<s id="1:94">And he added that he had "even heard people address him with Yes, sir, and No, sir!"</s>
<s id="1:95">At this moment, the cardinal was conversing with Don Abbondio on the affairs of his parish; so that the latter had no opportunity to repeat his instructions to the females; however, in passing by them as they entered, he gave them a glance, to make them comprehend that he was well satisfied with them, and that they should continue, like honest and worthy women, to keep silence.</s>
<s id="1:96">After the first reception, Agnes drew from her bosom the letter of Donna Prassede, and gave it to the cardinal, saying, "It is from the Signora Donna Prassede, who says that she knows your illustrious lordship well, my lord, as naturally is the case with great people.</s>
<s id="1:97">When you have read, you will see."</s>
<s id="1:98">"It is well," said Frederick, after having read the letter, and extracted its meaning from the trash of Don Ferrante's flowers of rhetoric.</s>
<s id="1:99">He knew the family well enough to be certain that Lucy had been invited into it with good intentions, and that she would be sheltered from the snares and violence of her persecutor.</s>
<s id="1:100">As to his opinion of Donna Prassede, we do not know it precisely; probably she was not a person he would have chosen for Lucy's protectress; but it was not his habit to undo things, apparently ordered by Providence, in order to do them better.</s>
<s id="1:101">"Submit, without regret, to this separation also, and to the suspense in which you are left," said he.</s>
<s id="1:102">"Hope for the best, and confide in God! and be persuaded, that all that He sends you, whether of joy or sorrow, will be for your permanent good."</s>
<s id="1:103">Having received the benediction which he bestowed on them, they took their leave.</s>
<s id="1:104">Hardly had they reached the street, when they were surrounded by a swarm of friends, who were expecting them, and who conducted them in triumph to their house.</s>
<s id="1:105">Their female acquaintances congratulated them, sympathised with them, and overwhelmed them with enquiries.</s>
<s id="1:106">Learning that Lucy was to depart on the following morning, they broke forth in exclamations of regret and disappointment.</s>
<s id="1:107">The men disputed with each other the privilege of offering their services; each wished to remain for the night to guard their cottage, which reminds us of a proverb; "If you would have people willing to confer favours on you, be sure not to need them."</s>
<s id="1:108">This warmth of reception served a little to withdraw Lucy from the painful recollections which crowded upon her mind, at the sight of her loved home.</s>
<s id="1:109">At the sound of the bell which announced the commencement of the ceremonies, all moved towards the church.</s>
<s id="1:110">The ceremonies over, Don Abbondio, who had hastened home to see every thing arranged for breakfast, was told that the cardinal wished to speak with him.</s>
<s id="1:111">He proceeded to the chamber of his illustrious guest, who accosted him as he entered, with "Signor Curate, why did you not unite in marriage, Lucy to her betrothed?"</s>
<s id="1:112">"They have emptied the sack this morning," thought Don Abbondio, and he stammered forth, "Your illustrious lordship has no doubt heard of all the difficulties of that business.</s>
<s id="1:113">It has been such an intricate affair, that it cannot even now be seen into clearly.</s>
<s id="1:114">Your illustrious lordship knows that the young girl is here, only by a miracle; and that no one can tell where the young man is."</s>
<s id="1:115">"I ask if it is true, that, before these unhappy events, you refused to celebrate the marriage on the day agreed upon? and why you did so?"</s>
<s id="1:116">"Truly--if your illustrious lordship knew--what terrible orders I received--" and he stopped, indicating by his manner, though respectfully, that it would be imprudent in the cardinal to enquire farther.</s>
<s id="1:117">"But," said Frederick, in a tone of much more gravity than he was accustomed to employ, "it is your bishop, who, from a sense of duty, and for your own justification, would learn from you, why you have not done that which, in the ordinary course of events, it was your strict duty to do?"</s>
<s id="1:118">"My lord," said Don Abbondio, "I do not mean to say,--but it appears to me, that as these things are now without remedy, it is useless to stir them up--</s>
<s id="1:119">However, however, I say, that I am sure your illustrious lordship would not betray a poor curate, because, you see, my lord, your illustrious lordship cannot be every where present, and I--I remain here, exposed--</s>
<s id="1:120">However, if you order me, I will tell all."</s>
<s id="1:121">"Speak; I ask for nothing but to find you free from blame."</s>
<s id="1:122">Don Abbondio then related his melancholy story, suppressing the name of the principal personage, and substituting in its place, "a great lord,"--thus giving to prudence the little that was left him in such an extremity.</s>
<s id="1:123">"And you had no other motive?" asked the cardinal, after having heard him through.</s>
<s id="1:124">"Perhaps I have not clearly explained myself.</s>
<s id="1:125">It was under pain of death that they ordered me not to perform the ceremony."</s>
<s id="1:126">"And this reason appeared sufficient to prevent the fulfilment of a rigorous duty?"</s>
<s id="1:127">"I know my obligation is to do my duty, even to my greatest detriment; but when life is at stake----"</s>
<s id="1:128">"And when you presented yourself to the church," said Frederick, with increased severity of manner, "to be admitted to the holy ministry, were there any such reservations made?</s>
<s id="1:129">Were you told that the duties imposed by the ministry were free from every obstacle, exempt from every peril?</s>
<s id="1:130">Were you told that personal safety was to be the guide and limit of your duty?</s>
<s id="1:131">Were you not told expressly the reverse of all this?</s>
<s id="1:132">Were you not warned that you were sent as a lamb among wolves?</s>
<s id="1:133">Did you not even then know that there were violent men in the world, who would oppose you in the performance of your duty?</s>
<s id="1:134">He, whose example should be our guide, in imitation of whom we call ourselves shepherds, when he came on earth to accomplish the designs of his benevolence, did he pay regard to his own safety?</s>
<s id="1:135">And if your object be to preserve your miserable existence, at the expense of charity and duty, there was no necessity for your receiving holy unction, and entering into the priesthood.</s>
<s id="1:136">The world imparts this virtue, teaches this doctrine.</s>
<s id="1:137">What do I say?</s>
<s id="1:138">O shame! the world itself rejects it.</s>
<s id="1:139">It has likewise its laws, which prescribe good, and prohibit evil; it has also its gospel, a gospel of pride and hatred, which will not admit the love of life to be offered as a plea for the transgression of its laws.</s>
<s id="1:140">It commands, and is obeyed; but we, we children and messengers of the promise! what would become of the church, if your language was held by all your brethren?</s>
<s id="1:141">Where would she now be, if she had originally come forth with such doctrines?"</s>
<s id="1:142">Don Abbondio hung down his head; he felt under the weight of these arguments as a chicken under the talons of a hawk, who holds him suspended in an unknown region, in an atmosphere he had never before breathed.</s>
<s id="1:143">Seeing that a reply was necessary, he said, more alarmed than convinced,-- "My lord, I have done wrong; since we should pay no regard to life, I have nothing more to say.</s>
<s id="1:144">But when one has to do with certain powerful people, who will not listen to reason, I do not see what is to be gained by carrying things with a high hand."</s>
<s id="1:145">"And know you not that our gain is to suffer for the sake of justice?</s>
<s id="1:146">If you are ignorant of this, what is it you preach?</s>
<s id="1:147">What do you teach? </s>
<s id="1:148">What is the good news which you proclaim to the poor?</s>
<s id="1:149">Who has required this at your hand, to overcome force by force?</s>
<s id="1:150">Certainly you will not be asked at the day of judgment, if you have vanquished the powerful, for you have neither had the commission nor the means to do so.</s>
<s id="1:151">But, you will be asked, if you have employed the means which have been placed in your power, to do that which was prescribed to you, even when man had the temerity to forbid it."</s>
<s id="1:152">"These saints are odd creatures," thought Don Abbondio; "extract the essence of this discourse, and it will be found that he has more at heart the love of two young people, than the life of a priest."</s>
<s id="1:153">He would have been delighted to have had the conversation terminate here, but he well perceived that such was not the intention of the cardinal, who appeared to be waiting a reply, or apology, or something of the kind.</s>
<s id="1:154">"I say, my lord," replied he, "that I have done wrong--</s>
<s id="1:155">We cannot give ourselves courage."</s>
<s id="1:156">"And why, then, I might say to you, have you undertaken a ministry which imposes on you the task of warring with the passions of the world?</s>
<s id="1:157">But, I will rather say, how is it that you have forgotten, that where courage is necessary to fulfil the obligations of this holy vocation, the Most High would assuredly impart it to you, were you earnestly to implore it?</s>
<s id="1:158">Do you think the millions of martyrs had courage naturally? that they had naturally a contempt for life, young Christians who had just begun to taste its charms, children, mothers!</s>
<s id="1:159">All had courage, simply because courage was necessary, and they trusted in God to impart it.</s>
<s id="1:160">Knowing your own weakness, have you ever thought of preparing yourself for the difficult situations in which you might be placed?</s>
<s id="1:161">Ah! if, during so many years of pastoral care, you had loved your flock, (and how could you refrain from loving them?) if you had reposed in them your affections, your dearest cares, your greatest delights, you would not have failed in courage: love is intrepid;</s>
<s id="1:162">if you had loved those who were committed to your spiritual guardianship, those whom you call children--if you had really loved them, when you beheld two of them threatened at the same time with yourself.</s>
<s id="1:163">Ah! certainly, charity would have made you tremble for them, as the weakness of the flesh made you tremble for yourself.</s>
<s id="1:164">You would have humbled yourself before God for the first risings of selfish terror; you would have considered it a temptation, and have implored strength to resist it.</s>
<s id="1:165">But, you would have eagerly listened to the holy and noble anxiety for the safety of others, for the safety of your children; you would have been unable to find a moment of repose; you would have been impelled, constrained to do all that you could to avert the evil that threatened them.</s>
<s id="1:166">With what then has this love, this anxiety, inspired you?</s>
<s id="1:167">What have you done for them?</s>
<s id="1:168">How have you been engaged in their service?"</s>
<s id="1:169">And he paused for a reply.</s>
</p>
</text>
