<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">As a pack of blood-hounds, after having in vain tracked the hare, return desponding towards their master, with their ears down, and tails hanging, so, in this night of confusion, returned the bravoes to the palace of Don Roderick, who was pacing, in the dark, the floor of an upper uninhabited chamber.</s>
    <s id="1:2">Full of impatience and uncertainty as to the issue of the expedition, and not without anxiety for the possible consequences, his ear was attentive to every sound, and his eye to every movement on the esplanade.</s>
    <s id="1:3">This was the most daring piece of villany he had ever undertaken; </s>
    <s id="1:4">but he felt that the precautions he had used would preserve him from suspicion.</s>
    <s id="1:5">"And who will dare to come here, and ask if she is not in this palace?</s>
    <s id="1:6">Should this young fellow do so, he will be well received, I promise him.</s>
    <s id="1:7">Let the friar come! yea, let him come.</s>
    <s id="1:8">If the old woman presumes so far, she shall be sent to Bergamo.</s>
    <s id="1:9">As for the law, I do fear it not; </s>
    <s id="1:10">the podestà is neither a boy nor a fool!</s>
    <s id="1:11">Pshaw! there's nothing to fear.</s>
    <s id="1:12">How will Attilio be surprised to-morrow morning; he will find I am not a mere boaster.</s>
    <s id="1:13">But if any difficulty should arise, he'll assist--the honour of all my relatives will be pledged."</s>
    <s id="1:14">But these anxious thoughts subsided as he reverted to Lucy.</s>
    <s id="1:15">– "She will be frightened to find herself alone, surrounded only by these rough visages: by Bacchus, the most human face here is my own, and she will be obliged to have recourse to me--to entreaty."</s>
    <s id="1:16">In the midst of these calculations he heard a trampling of feet, approached the window, and looking out exclaimed, "It is they!</s>
    <s id="1:17">But the litter! the devil! where is the litter?</s>
    <s id="1:18">Three, five, eight, they are all there; but where is the litter?</s>
    <s id="1:19">The devil!</s>
    <s id="1:20">Griso shall render me an account of this."</s>
    <s id="1:21">He then advanced to the head of the stairs to meet Griso.</s>
    <s id="1:22">"Well," cried he, "Signor Bully, Signor Captain, Signor 'Leave it to me!'"</s>
    <s id="1:23">"It is hard," said Griso,--"it is hard to meet with reproach, when one has hazarded one's life to perform his duty."</s>
    <s id="1:24">"How has it happened?</s>
    <s id="1:25">Let us hear, let us hear," said he, as he advanced towards the room, followed by Griso, who related, as clearly as he could, the occurrences of the night.</s>
    <s id="1:26">"Thou hast done well," said Don Roderick; "thou hast done all that thou couldst--but to think that this roof harbours a spy!</s>
    <s id="1:27">If I discover him I will settle matters for him; and I tell thee, Griso, I suspect the information was given the day of the dinner."</s>
    <s id="1:28">"I have had the same suspicion," said Griso; "and if my master discovers the scoundrel, he has only to trust him to me.</s>
    <s id="1:29">He has made me pass a troublesome night, and I wish to pay him for it.</s>
    <s id="1:30">But there must be, I think, some other cause, which we cannot at present fathom; to-morrow, Signor, to-morrow we will see clear water."</s>
    <s id="1:31">"Have you been recognised by any one?"</s>
    <s id="1:32">Griso thought not; and after having given him many orders for the morrow,</s>
    <s id="1:33">and wishing to make amends for the impetuosity with which he had at first greeted him, Don Roderick said,</s>
    <s id="1:34">Go to rest, poor Griso! you must indeed require it.</s>
    <s id="1:35">Labouring all day, and half the night, and then to be received in this manner!</s>
    <s id="1:36">Go to rest now; for we may yet be obliged to put your friendship to a severer test.</s>
    <s id="1:37">Good night."</s>
    <s id="1:38">The next morning Don Roderick sought the Count Attilio, who, receiving him with a laugh, said, "San Martin!"</s>
    <s id="1:39">"I will pay the wager," said Don Roderick.</s>
    <s id="1:40">"I thought indeed to have surprised you this morning, and therefore have kept from you some circumstances.</s>
    <s id="1:41">I will now tell you all."</s>
    <s id="1:42">"The friar's hand is in this business," said his cousin, after having heard him through: "this friar, with his playing at bo-peep, and giving advice; I know him for a busybody and a rascal!</s>
    <s id="1:43">And you did not confide in me, and tell me what brought him here the other day to trifle with you.</s>
    <s id="1:44">If I had been in your place he should not have gone out as he came in, of that be assured."</s>
    <s id="1:45">"What! would you wish me to incur the resentment of all the capuchins in Italy?"</s>
    <s id="1:46">"In such a moment," said the count, "I should have forgotten there was any other capuchin in the world than this daring rascal; but the means are not wanting, within the pale of prudence, to take satisfaction even of a capuchin.</s>
    <s id="1:47">It is well for him that he has escaped the punishment best suited to him; but I take him henceforth under my protection, and will teach him how to speak to his superiors."</s>
    <s id="1:48">"Do not make matters worse."</s>
    <s id="1:49">"Trust me for once; I will serve you as a relation and a friend."</s>
    <s id="1:50">"What do you mean to do?"</s>
    <s id="1:51">"I don't know yet; but I will certainly pay the friar.</s>
    <s id="1:52">Let me see--the count my uncle, who is one of the secret council, will do the service; dear uncle!</s>
    <s id="1:53">How pleased I am when I can make him work for me, a politician of his stamp!</s>
    <s id="1:54">The day after to-morrow I will be at Milan, and in some way or other the friar shall have his due."</s>
    <s id="1:55">Meanwhile breakfast was brought in, which however did not interrupt the important discussion.</s>
    <s id="1:56">Count Attilio interested himself in the cause from his friendship for his cousin, and the honour of the name, according to his notions of friendship and honour; yet he could hardly help laughing every now and then at the ridiculous issue of the adventure.</s>
    <s id="1:57">But Don Roderick, who had calculated upon making a master-stroke, was vexed at his signal failure, and agitated by various passions.</s>
    <s id="1:58">Fine stories will be circulated, said he, "of last night's affair, </s>
    <s id="1:59">but no matter;</s>
    <s id="1:60">as to justice, I defy it: it does not exist; and if it did, I should equally defy it.</s>
    <s id="1:61">Apropos, I have sent word this morning to the constable, to make no deposition respecting the affair, </s>
    <s id="1:62">and he will be sure to follow my advice; but tattling always annoys me, </s>
    <s id="1:63">– it is enough that you have it in your power to laugh at me."</s>
    <s id="1:64">"It is well you have given the constable his message," said the count; "this great empty-headed, obstinate proser of a podestà is however a man who knows his duty, and we must be careful not to place him in difficulty.</s>
    <s id="1:65">If a fellow of a constable makes a deposition, the podestà, however well intentioned, is obliged to----"</s>
    <s id="1:66">But you, interrupted Don Roderick, with a little warmth,--"you spoil my affairs, by contradicting him, and laughing at him on every occasion.</s>
    <s id="1:67">Why the devil can't you suffer a magistrate to be an obstinate beast, while in other things that suit our convenience he is an honest man?"</s>
    <s id="1:68">"Do you know, cousin," said the count, regarding him with an expression of affected surprise, "do you know that I begin to think you capable of fear?</s>
    <s id="1:69">You take the podestà and myself to be in earnest."</s>
    <s id="1:70">"Well, well, have not you yourself said that we should be careful?"</s>
    <s id="1:71">"Certainly; and when the question is serious, I will show you I am not a boy.</s>
    <s id="1:72">Shall I tell you what I will do for you?</s>
    <s id="1:73">I will go in person to make the podestà a visit; do you not think he will be pleased with the honour?</s>
    <s id="1:74">And I will let him talk by the half hour of the count duke, and the Spanish keeper of the castle, and then I will throw in some remarks about the signor count of the secret council, my uncle; you know what effect this will have.</s>
    <s id="1:75">Finally, he has more need of our protection, than you have of his condescension.</s>
    <s id="1:76">He knows this well enough, and I shall leave him better disposed than I find him, that you may depend upon."</s>
    <s id="1:77">So saying, he took his departure, leaving Don Roderick alone to wait the return of Griso, who had been, in obedience to his orders, reconnoitring the ground, and ascertaining the state of the public mind with regard to the events of the preceding night.</s>
    <s id="1:78">He came at last, at the hour of dinner, to give in his relation.</s>
    <s id="1:79">The tumult of this night had been so loud, and the disappearance of three persons from the village so mysterious, that strict and indefatigable search would naturally be made for them; and on the other hand, those who were possessed of partial information on the subject were too numerous to preserve an entire silence.</s>
    <s id="1:80">Perpetua was assailed every where to tell what had caused her master such a fright, and she, perceiving how she had been deceived by Agnes, and feeling exasperated at her perfidy, had need of a little self-restraint; not that she complained of the deception practised on herself, of that she did not breathe a syllable; but the injury done to her poor master could not pass in silence, and that such an injury should have been attempted by such worthy people!</s>
    <s id="1:81">Don Abbondio could command and entreat her to be silent, and she could reply that there was no necessity for inculcating a thing so obvious and proper, but certain it is that the secret remained in the heart of the poor woman as new wine in an old cask, which ferments and bubbles, and if it does not send the bung into the air, works out in foam between the staves, and drops here and there, so that one can drink it, and tell what sort of wine it is.</s>
    <s id="1:82">Jervase, who could scarcely believe that for once he knew a little more than others, and who felt himself a man, since he had been an accomplice in a criminal affair, was dying to communicate it.</s>
    <s id="1:83">And Tony, however alarmed at the thoughts of further enquiries and investigation, was bursting, in spite of all his prudence, till he had told the whole secret to his wife, who was not dumb.</s>
    <s id="1:84">The one who spoke least was Menico, because his parents, alarmed at his coming into collision with Don Roderick, had kept him in the house for several days; they themselves, however, without wishing to appear to know more than others, insinuated that the fugitives had taken refuge at Pescarenico.</s>
    <s id="1:85">This report, then, became current among the villagers.</s>
    <s id="1:86">But no one could account for the attack of the bravoes: all agreed in suspecting Don Roderick; but the rest was total obscurity.</s>
    <s id="1:87">The presence of the three bravoes at the inn was discussed,</s>
    <s id="1:88">and the landlord was interrogated; but his memory was, on this point, as defective as ever.</s>
    <s id="1:89">His inn, he concluded as usual, was just like a sea-port.</s>
    <s id="1:90">Who was this pilgrim, seen by Stefano and Carlandrea, and whom the robbers wished to murder, and had carried off?</s>
    <s id="1:91">For what purpose had he been at the cottage?</s>
    <s id="1:92">Some said it was a good spirit, come to the assistance of the inmates; others, that it was the spirit of a wicked pilgrim, who came at night to join such companions, and perform such deeds, as he had been accustomed to while living; others, again, went so far as to conjecture that it was one of these very robbers, clothed like a pilgrim; so that Griso, with all his experience, would have been at a loss to discover who it was, if he had expected to acquire this information from others.</s>
    <s id="1:93">But, as the reader knows, that which was perplexity to them, was perfect clearness to Griso.</s>
    <s id="1:94">He was enabled, therefore, from these various sources, to obtain a sufficiently distinct account for the ear of Don Roderick.</s>
    <s id="1:95">He related the attempt upon Don Abbondio, which accounted for the desertion of the cottage, without the necessity of imagining a spy in the palace: he told of their flight, which might be accounted for by the fear of the discovery of their trick upon Don Abbondio, or by the intelligence that their cottage had been broken into, and that they had probably gone together to Pescarenico.</s>
    <s id="1:96">"Fled together!" cried Don Roderick, hoarse with rage: "together! </s>
    <s id="1:97">and this rascal friar!</s>
    <s id="1:98">this friar shall answer it!</s>
    <s id="1:99">Griso, this night I must know where they are.</s>
    <s id="1:100">I shall have no peace; ascertain if they are at Pescarenico; quick; fly; four crowns immediately, and my protection for ever! this rascal! this friar!"</s>
    <s id="1:101">Griso was once more in the field; and on the evening of this very day reported to his worthy master the desired intelligence, and by the following means.</s>
    <s id="1:102">The good man by whom the little party had been conducted to Monza, returning with his carriage to Pescarenico at the hour of vespers, chanced to meet, before he reached his home, a particular friend, to whom he related, in great confidence, the good work he had accomplished; so that Griso could, two hours after, inform Don Roderick that Lucy and her mother had taken refuge in a convent of Monza, and that Renzo had proceeded on his way to Milan.</s>
    <s id="1:103">Don Roderick felt his hopes revive at this separation; and having, during great part of the night, revolved in his mind the measures for effecting his wicked purpose, he aroused Griso early in the morning, and gave him the orders he had premeditated.</s>
    <s id="1:104">"Signor?" said Griso, hesitating.</s>
    <s id="1:105">"Well, have I have not spoken clearly?"</s>
    <s id="1:106">"If you would send some other----"</s>
    <s id="1:107">"How?"</s>
    <s id="1:108">"Most illustrious signor, I am ready to sacrifice my life for my master, and it is my duty to do so; but you, you would not desire me to place it in peril?"</s>
    <s id="1:109">"Well?"</s>
    <s id="1:110">"Your illustrious lordship knows well these few murders that are laid to my account, and----</s>
    <s id="1:111">Here I am under the protection of your lordship, and in Milan the livery of your lordship is known, but in Monza I am known.</s>
    <s id="1:112">And, your lordship knows, I do not say it boastingly, he who should deliver me up to justice would be well rewarded, a hundred good crowns, and permission to liberate two banditti."</s>
    <s id="1:113">"What, the devil!" said Don Roderick, "you are like a vile cur, who has scarce courage to rush at the legs of such as pass by the door; and, not daring to leave the house, keeps himself within the protection of his master."</s>
    <s id="1:114">"I think I have given proof, signor," said Griso.</s>
    <s id="1:115">"Well?"</s>
    <s id="1:116">"Well," resumed Griso, boldly, thus put on his mettle, "your lordship must forget my hesitation; heart of a lion, legs of a hare, I am ready to go."</s>
    <s id="1:117">"But you shall not go alone; take with you two of the best; Cut-face and Aim-well, and go boldly, and show yourself to be still Griso.</s>
    <s id="1:118">The devil! people will be well content to let such faces as yours pass without molestation!</s>
    <s id="1:119">And as to the bailiffs of Monza, they must have become weary of life to place it in such danger, for the chance of a hundred crowns!</s>
    <s id="1:120">But I do not believe that I am so far unknown there, that the stamp of my service should pass for nothing."</s>
    <s id="1:121">Griso, having received ample and minute instructions, took his departure, accompanied by the two bravoes; cursing in his heart the whims of his master.</s>
    <s id="1:122">It now became the design of Don Roderick to contrive some way, by which Renzo, separated as he was from Lucy, should be prevented from attempting to return.</s>
    <s id="1:123">He thought that the most certain means would be to have him sent out of the state, but this required the sanction of the law; he could, for example, give a colouring to the attempt at the curate's house, and represent it as a seditious act, and through Doctor Azzecca Garbugli give the podestà to understand that it was his duty to apprehend Renzo.</s>
    <s id="1:124">But while he thought of the doctor as the man the most suitable for this service, Renzo himself put an end to much further deliberation on the subject by withdrawing himself.</s>
    <s id="1:125">Like the boy who drives his little Indian pigs to the fold, whose obstinacy impels them divers ways, and thus obliges him first to apply to one and then to another till he can succeed in penning them all,</s>
    <s id="1:126">so are we obliged to play the same game with the personages of our story.</s>
    <s id="1:127">Having secured Lucy, we ran to Don Roderick. </s>
    <s id="1:128">Him we now quit to give an account of Renzo.</s>
    <s id="1:129">After the mournful parting which we have related, he set out, discouraged and disheartened, on his way to Milan.</s>
    <s id="1:130">To bid farewell to his home and his country, and what was more, to Lucy! to find himself among strangers, not knowing where to rest his head, and all on account of this villain!</s>
    <s id="1:131">When these thoughts presented themselves to the mind of Renzo, he was, for the moment, absorbed by rage and the desire of revenge; but when he recollected the prayer that he had uttered with the good friar in the convent of Pescarenico, his better feelings prevailed, and he was enabled to acquire some degree of resignation to the chastisements of which he stood so much in need.</s>
    <s id="1:132">The road lay between two high banks; it was muddy, stony, and furrowed by deep wheel tracks, which, after a rain, became rivulets, overflowing the road, and rendering it nearly impassable. </s>
    <s id="1:133">In such places small raised footpaths indicated that others had found a way by the fields.</s>
    <s id="1:134">Renzo ascended one of these paths to the high ground, whence he beheld, as if rising from a desert, and not in the midst of a city, the noble structure of the cathedral, and he forgot all his misfortunes in contemplating, even at a distance, this eighth wonder of the world, of which he had heard so much from his infancy.</s>
    <s id="1:135">But looking back, he saw in the horizon the notched ridge of mountains, and distinctly perceiving, among them, his own Resegone, he gazed at it mournfully a while, and then with a beating heart went on his way; steeples, towers, cupolas, and roofs soon appeared: he descended into the road, and when he perceived that he was very near the city, he accosted a traveller, with the civility which was natural to him, "Will you be so good, sir----"</s>
    <s id="1:136">What do you want, my good young man?</s>
    <s id="1:137">"Will you be so good as to direct me by the shortest way to the convent of the capuchins, where Father Bonaventura resides?"</s>
    <s id="1:138">He replied, very affably, "My good lad, there is more than one convent; you must tell me more clearly what and whom you seek."</s>
    <s id="1:139">Renzo then took from his bosom the letter of Father Christopher, and presented it to the gentleman, who, after having read it, returned it, saying, "The eastern gate; you are fortunate, young man--the convent you seek is but a short distance from this.</s>
    <s id="1:140">Take this path to the left; it is a by-way, and in a little while you will find yourself by the side of a long and low building; that is the lazaretto; keep along the ditch that encircles it, and you will soon be at the eastern gate.</s>
    <s id="1:141">Enter, and a few steps further on you will see before you an open square with fine elm trees; the convent is there--you cannot mistake it.</s>
    <s id="1:142">God be with you!"</s>
    <s id="1:143">And accompanying his last words with a kind wave of his hand, he proceeded on his way.</s>
    <s id="1:144">Renzo was astonished at the good manners of the citizens to countrymen, not knowing that it was an extraordinary day, a day in which cloaks humbled themselves to doublets.</s>
    <s id="1:145">He followed the path which had been pointed out to him, and arrived at the eastern entrance,</s>
    <s id="1:146">which consisted of two pilasters, with a roofing above to secure the gates, and on one side was a small house for the toll-gatherer.</s>
    <s id="1:147">The openings of the rampart descended irregularly, and their surface was filled with rubbish.</s>
    <s id="1:148">The street of the suburb which led from this gate was not unlike the one which now opens from the Tosa gate.</s>
    <s id="1:149">A small ditch ran in the midst of it, until within a few steps of the gate, and divided it into two small crooked streets, covered with dust or mud, according to the season.</s>
    <s id="1:150">At the place where was, and is still, the collection of houses called the Borghetto, the ditch empties itself into a common sewer, and thence into another ditch which runs along the walls.</s>
    <s id="1:151">At this point was a column with a cross oh it, dedicated to San Dionigi; to the right and left were gardens enclosed by hedges, and at intervals, small houses inhabited for the most part by washerwomen.</s>
    <s id="1:152">Renzo passed through the gate, without being stopped by the toll-gatherer, which appeared to him very remarkable, as he had heard those few of his townsmen, who could boast of having been at Milan, relate wonderful stories of the strict search and close enquiries to which those were subjected who entered its gates.</s>
    <s id="1:153">The street was deserted, and if he had not heard the humming of a crowd at a distance, he might have thought he was entering a city which had been abandoned by its inhabitants.</s>
    <s id="1:154">As he advanced, he saw on the pavement something scattered here and there, which was as white as snow, but snow at this season it could not be; he touched it, and found that it was flour.</s>
    <s id="1:155"> "There must be a great plenty in Milan," said he, "if they thus throw away the gifts of God.</s>
    <s id="1:156">They give out that famine is every where; this they do to keep poor people abroad quiet."</s>
    <s id="1:157">But in a few moments he arrived in front of the column, and saw on the steps of the pedestal certain things scattered, which were not assuredly stones, and which, if they had been on a baker's counter, he would not have hesitated to call loaves of bread.</s>
    <s id="1:158">But Renzo dared not so easily trust his eyes, because truly this was not a place for bread.</s>
    <s id="1:159">Let us see what this is, said he, and approaching the column, he took one in his hand; it was, indeed, a very white loaf of bread, such as Renzo was accustomed to eat only on festival days.</s>
    <s id="1:160">It is really bread! said he, in wonder.</s>
    <s id="1:161">"Do they scatter it thus here?</s>
    <s id="1:162">And in a year like this?</s>
    <s id="1:163">And do they suffer it to lie here, and not take the trouble to gather it?</s>
    <s id="1:164">This must be a fine place to live in!" </s>
    <s id="1:165">After ten miles of travel, in the fresh air of the morning, the sight of the bread awaked his appetite. </s>
    <s id="1:166">"Shall I take it?" said he again.</s>
    <s id="1:167">"Poh! they have left it to the dogs; surely, a Christian may take advantage of it; </s>
    <s id="1:168">and if the owner should come, I can pay him at any rate."</s>
    <s id="1:169">So saying, he put in one pocket that which he had in his hand, took a second, and put it in the other, and a third, which he began to eat, and resumed his way, full of wonder at the strangeness of the incident.</s>
    <s id="1:170">As he moved on he saw people approaching from the interior of the city; and his attention was drawn to those who appeared first; a man, a woman, and a boy, each with a load which seemed beyond their strength, and exhibiting each a grotesque appearance.</s>
    <s id="1:171">Their clothes, or rather their rags, powdered with meal, their faces the same, and excessively heated; they walked, not only as if overcome by the weight, but as if their limbs had been beaten and bruised.</s>
    <s id="1:172">The man supported with difficulty a great bag of flour, which having holes here and there, scattered its contents at every unequal movement.</s>
    <s id="1:173">But the figure of the woman was still more remarkable:</s>
    <s id="1:174">she had her petticoat turned up, filled with as much flour as it could hold, and a little more; so that from time to time it flew over the pavement.</s>
    <s id="1:175">She was, indeed, a grotesque picture, with her arms stretched out to encompass her burden, and staggering under its weight, her bare legs were seen beneath it.</s>
    <s id="1:176">The boy held with both hands a basket full of bread on his head, but he was detained behind his parents to pick up the loaves which were constantly falling from it.</s>
    <s id="1:177">"If you let another fall, you ugly little dog----" said the mother, in a rage.</s>
    <s id="1:178">"I don't let them fall; they fall of themselves.</s>
    <s id="1:179">How can I help it?" replied he.</s>
    <s id="1:180">"Eh! it's well for thee that my hands are full," resumed the woman.</s>
    <s id="1:181"> "Come, come," said the man, "now that we have a little plenty, let us enjoy it in peace."</s>
    <s id="1:182">Meanwhile there had arrived a company of strangers, and one of them addressed the woman, "Where are we to go for bread?"--</s>
    <s id="1:183">"On, on," replied she, and added, muttering, "These rascal countrymen will sweep all the shops and warehouses, and leave none for us."</s>
    <s id="1:184">"There is a share for every one, chatterer," said her husband; "plenty, plenty."</s>
    <s id="1:185">From all that Renzo saw and heard, he gathered that there was an insurrection in the city, and that each one provided for himself, in proportion to his will and strength.</s>
    <s id="1:186">Although we would desire to make our poor mountaineer appear to the most advantage, historical truth obliges us to say that his first sentiment was that of complacency.</s>
    <s id="1:187">He had so little to rejoice at, in the ordinary course of affairs, that he congratulated himself on a change, of whatever nature it might be.</s>
    <s id="1:188">And for the rest, he, who was not a man superior to the age in which he lived, held the common opinion that the scarcity of bread had been caused by the speculators and bakers, and that any method would be justifiable, of wresting from them the aliment which they cruelly denied to the people.</s>
    <s id="1:189">However, he determined to keep away from the tumult, and congratulated himself on the good fortune of having for his friend a capuchin, who would afford him shelter and good advice.</s>
    <s id="1:190">Occupied with such reflections, and noticing from time to time as more people came up loaded with plunder, he proceeded to the convent.</s>
    <s id="1:191">The church and convent of the capuchins was situated in the centre of a small square, shaded by elm trees;</s>
    <s id="1:192">Renzo placed in his bosom his remaining half loaf, and with his letter in his hand, approached the gate and rung the bell.</s>
    <s id="1:193">At a small grated window appeared the face of a friar, porter to the convent, to ask "who was there?"</s>
    <s id="1:194">"One from the country, who brings a letter to Father Bonaventura, from Father Christopher."</s>
    <s id="1:195">"Give here," said the friar, thrusting his hand through the grate.</s>
    <s id="1:196">"No, no," said Renzo, "I must give it into his own hands."</s>
    <s id="1:197">"He is not in the convent."</s>
    <s id="1:198">"Suffer me to enter and wait for him," replied Renzo.</s>
    <s id="1:199">"You had best wait in the church," said the friar; "perhaps that may be of service to you.</s>
    <s id="1:200">Into the convent you do not enter at present."</s>
    <s id="1:201">So saying, he hastily closed the window, leaving Renzo to receive the repulse with the best grace he could.</s>
    <s id="1:202">He was about to follow the advice of the porter, when he was seized with the desire to give a glance at the tumult.</s>
    <s id="1:203">He crossed the square, and advanced towards the middle of the city, where the disturbance was greatest.</s>
    <s id="1:204">Whilst he is proceeding thither, we will relate, as briefly as possible, the causes of this commotion.</s>
  </p>
</text>
