<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<text>
<p id="1">
<s id="1:1">The discourse of the merchant had plunged our poor Renzo into inexpressible agitation and alarm;</s>
<s id="1:2">there was no doubt that his adventure was noised abroad--that people were in search of him?</s>
<s id="1:3">Who could tell how many bailiffs were in pursuit of him?</s>
<s id="1:4">Who could tell what orders had been given to watch at the villages, inns, and along the roads?</s>
<s id="1:5">True it was, that two only of the officers were acquainted with his person, and he didn't bear his name stamped on his forehead.</s>
<s id="1:6">Yet he had heard strange stories of fugitives being discovered by their suspicious air, or some unexpected mark; in short, he was alarmed at every shadow.</s>
<s id="1:7">Although at the moment he quitted Gorgonzola, the bells struck the Ave Maria, and the increasing darkness diminished his danger, he unwillingly took the high road, with the intention, however, of entering the first path which should appear to him to lead in the right direction.</s>
<s id="1:8">He met some travellers, but, his imagination filled with apprehensions, he dared not interrogate them.</s>
<s id="1:9">"The host called it six miles," said he; "if, in travelling through by-paths, I make it eight or ten, these good limbs will not fail me, I know.</s>
<s id="1:10">I am certainly not going towards Milan, and must therefore be approaching the Adda.</s>
<s id="1:11">If I keep on, sooner or later I must arrive there; the Adda has a voice sufficiently loud to be heard at some distance, and when I hear it, there will be no longer any need of direction.</s>
<s id="1:12">If there is a boat there, I shall cross immediately; if not, I will wait until morning in a field, upon the ground, like the sparrows, which will be far better than a prison."</s>
<s id="1:13">He saw a cross-road open to the left, and he pursued it:</s>
<s id="1:14">I play the devil! continued he, "I assassinate the lords!</s>
<s id="1:15">A packet of letters!</s>
<s id="1:16">My companions keeping watch!</s>
<s id="1:17">I would give something to meet this merchant face to face, on the other side of the Adda; (Oh! when shall I reach the beautiful stream?)</s>
<s id="1:18">I would ask him politely where he picked up that fine story.</s>
<s id="1:19">Know, my good sir, that, devil as I am, it was I who aided Ferrer, and like a good Christian saved your superintendent of provisions from a rough joke that those ruffians, my friends, were about to play on him.</s>
<s id="1:20">Ay, while you were keeping watch over your shop----</s>
<s id="1:21">and that enormous packet of letters--in the hands of the government.</s>
<s id="1:22">See, sir, here it is;</s>
<s id="1:23">a single letter, written by a worthy man, a monk; a hair of whose beard is worth-—</s>
<s id="1:24">but in future learn to speak with more charity of your neighbours."</s>
<s id="1:25">However, after a while, these thoughts of the poor traveller gave way to more urgent considerations of his present difficulties;</s>
<s id="1:26">he no longer feared pursuit or discovery; </s>
<s id="1:27">but darkness, solitude, and fatigue combined to distress him and retard his progress.</s>
<s id="1:28">A chill north wind penetrated his light clothing, his wedding suit; and, uncomfortable and disheartened, he wandered on, in hopes of finding some place where he might obtain concealment and repose for the night.</s>
<s id="1:29">He passed through villages, but did not dare ask shelter; </s>
<s id="1:30">the dogs howled at his approach, and induced him to quicken his steps.</s>
<s id="1:31">At single houses near the road-side his fatigue tempted him to knock for shelter; </s>
<s id="1:32">but the apprehension of being saluted with the cry of "Help, thieves! robbers!" banished the idea from his mind.</s>
<s id="1:33">Leaving the cultivated country, he found himself in a plain, covered with fern and broom; and thinking this a favourable symptom of the near vicinity of the river, he followed the path across it.</s>
<s id="1:34">When he had advanced a few steps, he listened, but in vain.</s>
<s id="1:35">The desolation of the place increased the depression of his spirits.</s>
<s id="1:36">Strange forms and apparitions, the birth of former tales and legends, began to haunt his imagination; and to drive them away he began to chant the prayers for the dead.</s>
<s id="1:37">He passed through a thicket of plum-trees and oaks, and found himself on the borders of a wood; he conquered his repugnance to enter it, but as he proceeded into its depths, every object excited his apprehensions.</s>
<s id="1:38">Strange forms appeared beneath the bushes; and the shade of the trees, trembling on his moon-lit path, with the crackling of the dead leaves between his footsteps, inspired him with dread.</s>
<s id="1:39">He would have hastened through the perilous passage, but his limbs refused their office; the wind blew cold and sharp, and penetrating his weakened frame, almost subdued its small remains of vigour.</s>
<s id="1:40">His senses, affected by undefined horrors, appeared to be leaving him; aroused to his danger, he made a violent effort to regain some degree of resolution, in order to return through the wood, and seek shelter in the last village he had passed through, even if it should be in an inn!</s>
<s id="1:41">As he stopped for a moment, before putting his design in execution, the wind brought a new sound to his ear--the murmur of running water.</s>
<s id="1:42">Intently listening, to ascertain if his senses did not deceive him, he cried out, "It is the Adda!"</s>
<s id="1:43">His fatigue vanished, his pulse returned, his blood flowed freely through his veins, his fears disappeared; and guided by the friendly sound, he went forward.</s>
<s id="1:44">He soon reached the extremity of the plain, and found himself on the edge of a steep precipice, whence looking downward, he discovered, through the bushes, the long-desired river, and, on the other side of it, villages scattered here and there, with hills in the distance; and on the summit of one of these a whitish spot, which in the dimness he took to be a city; Bergamo certainly!</s>
<s id="1:45">He descended the declivity, and throwing aside the bushes with his hands, looked beyond them, to spy if some friendly bark were moving on the flood, or if he could not, by listening, hear the sound of oars cleaving the water; but he saw, he heard nothing.</s>
<s id="1:46">If it had been any stream less than the Adda, he would have attempted to ford it, but this he well knew to be impracticable.</s>
<s id="1:47">He was uncertain what plan to pursue: to lie down on the grass for the next six hours, and wait until morning, exposed to the north wind and the damps of the night; or to continue walking to and fro, to protect himself from the cold, until the day should dawn: neither of these held out much prospect of comfort.</s>
<s id="1:48">He suddenly recollected to have seen, in a neighbouring part of the uncultivated heath, a cascinotto;--this was the name given by the peasants of the Milanese to cabins covered with straw, constructed with the trunks and branches of trees, and the crevices filled with mud, where they were in the habit of placing the crop, gathered during the day, until a more convenient opportunity for removing it; they were therefore abandoned except at such seasons.</s>
<s id="1:49">Renzo found his way thither, pushed open the door, and perceiving a bundle of straw on the ground, thought that sleep, even in such a place, would be very welcome.</s>
<s id="1:50">Before, however, throwing himself on the bed Providence had provided for him, he kneeled, and returned thanks for the blessing, and for all the assistance which had been this day afforded him,</s>
<s id="1:51">and then implored forgiveness for the errors of the previous day;</s>
<s id="1:52">then gathering the straw around him as some defence against the cold, he closed his eyes to sleep; but sleep was not so soon to visit our poor traveller.</s>
<s id="1:53">Confused images began to throng his fancy; the merchant, the notary, the bailiffs, the cutler, the host, Ferrer, the superintendent, the company at the inn, the crowds in the streets, assailed his imagination by turns; then came the thought of Don Abbondio, Roderick, Lucy, Agnes, and the good friar.</s>
<s id="1:54">He remembered the paternal counsels of the latter, and reflected with shame and remorse on his neglect of them; and what bitter retrospection did the image of Lucy produce! and Agnes! poor Agnes! how ill had she been repaid for her motherly solicitude on his behalf! an outcast from her home, solitary, uncertain of the future, reaping misery from what seemed to promise the happiness of her declining years!</s>
<s id="1:55">Poor Renzo!</s>
<s id="1:56">what a night didst thou pass!</s>
<s id="1:57">what an apartment!</s>
<s id="1:58">what a bed for a matrimonial couch!</s>
<s id="1:59">tormented, too, with apprehensions of the future!</s>
<s id="1:60">"I submit to the will of God," said he, speaking aloud, "to the will of God!</s>
<s id="1:61">He does only that which is right; I accept it all as a just chastisement for my sins.</s>
<s id="1:62">Lucy, however, is so good! the Lord will not long afflict her with suffering."</s>
<s id="1:63">In the mean time he despaired of obtaining any repose; the cold was insupportable; his teeth chattered; he ardently wished for day, and measured with impatience the slow progress of the hours; this he was enabled to do, as he heard, every half hour, in the deep silence, the heavy sound of some distant clock, probably that of Trezzo.</s>
<s id="1:64">When the time arrived which he had fixed on for his departure, half benumbed with exposure to the night air, he stretched his stiffened limbs, and opening the door of the cascinotto, looked out, to ascertain if any one were near, and finding all silent around, he resumed his journey along the path he had quitted.</s>
<s id="1:65">The sky announced a beautiful day; the setting moon shone pale in an immense field of azure, which, towards the east, mingled itself lightly with the rosy dawn.</s>
<s id="1:66">Near the horizon were scattered clouds of various hues and forms; it was, in fact, the sky of Lombardy, beautiful, brilliant, and calm.</s>
<s id="1:67">If Renzo had had a mind at ease, he would no doubt have stopped to contemplate this splendid ushering in of day, so different from that which he had been accustomed to witness amidst his mountains; but his thoughts were otherwise occupied.</s>
<s id="1:68">He reached the brow of the precipice where he had stood the preceding night, and looking below, perceived, through the bushes, a fisherman's bark, which was slowly stemming the current, near the shore.</s>
<s id="1:69">He descended the precipice, and standing on the bank, made a sign to the fisherman to approach. He intended to do this with a careless air, as if it were of little importance, but in spite of himself, his manner was half supplicatory.</s>
<s id="1:70">The fisherman, after having for a moment surveyed the course of the water, as if to ascertain the practicability of reaching the shore, directed the boat towards it; before it touched the bank, Renzo, who was standing on the water's edge, awaiting its approach, seized the prow, and jumped into it.</s>
<s id="1:71">"Do me a service, and I will pay you for it," said he; "I wish to cross to the other shore."</s>
<s id="1:72">The fisherman having divined his object, had already turned his boat in that direction.</s>
<s id="1:73">Renzo, perceiving another oar in the bottom of the bark, stooped to take it.</s>
<s id="1:74">"Softly, softly," said the fisherman.</s>
<s id="1:75">But seeing with what skill the young man managed the oar, "Ah! ah!" added he, "you know the trade."</s>
<s id="1:76">"A very little," replied Renzo, and he continued to row with a vigour and skill beyond that of a mere amateur in the art.</s>
<s id="1:77">With all his efforts, however, the bark moved slowly; the current, setting strong against it, drove it continually from the line of its direction, and impeded the rapidity of its course.</s>
<s id="1:78">New perplexities presented themselves to the mind of Renzo; now that the Adda was almost passed, he began to fear that it might not, at this place, serve for the boundary between the states, and that, this obstacle surmounted, there would yet be others remaining.</s>
<s id="1:79">He spoke to the fisherman, and pointing to the white spot he had noticed the night before, and which was now much more distinct, "Is that Bergamo?" said he.</s>
<s id="1:80">"The city of Bergamo," replied the fisherman.</s>
<s id="1:81">"And the other shore, does it belong to Bergamo?"</s>
<s id="1:82">"It is the territory of St. Mark."</s>
<s id="1:83">"Long live St. Mark!" cried Renzo.</s>
<s id="1:84">The fisherman made no reply.</s>
<s id="1:85">The boat reached the shore, at last; Renzo thanked God in his heart, as he stepped upon it; and turning to the fisherman took from his pocket a berlinga and gave it to him.</s>
<s id="1:86">The man took it in silence, and with a significant look, placed his forefinger on his lip; and saying, "A good journey to you," returned to his employment.</s>
<s id="1:87">In order to account for the prompt and discreet civility of this man towards a perfect stranger, we must inform the reader, that he was accustomed to render similar favours to smugglers and outlaws, not so much for the sake of the little gain which accrued to him thereby, as not to create enemies among these classes of people.</s>
<s id="1:88">He rendered these services, therefore, when he was sure of not being seen by the custom-house officers, bailiffs, or spies.</s>
<s id="1:89">Thus he endeavoured to act with an impartiality, which should give offence to neither party.</s>
<s id="1:90">Renzo stopped a moment to contemplate the shore he had quitted, and where he had suffered so much; "I am at last safely beyond it," was his first thought; then the remembrance of those he had left behind rushed over his mind, overwhelming it with regret and shame; for, with the calm and virtuous image of Lucy, came the recollection of his extravagances in Milan.</s>
<s id="1:91">He shook off, however, these oppressive thoughts, and went on, taking the direction of the whitish mass on the declivity of the mountain, until he should meet some one who could direct him on his way.</s>
<s id="1:92">And now with what a different and careless air he accosted travellers! he hesitated no more, he pronounced boldly the name of the place where his cousin lived, to ask the way to it; from the information given him by the first traveller he met, he found that he had still nine miles to travel.</s>
<s id="1:93">His journey was not agreeable.</s>
<s id="1:94">Without referring to his own causes of trouble, Renzo was affected every moment by the sight of painful and distressing objects; so that he foresaw, that he should find in this country the poverty he had left in his own.</s>
<s id="1:95">All along the way he was assailed by mendicants,--mendicants of necessity, not of choice,--peasants, mountaineers, tradesmen, whole families reduced to poverty, and to the necessity of begging their bread.</s>
<s id="1:96">This sight, besides the compassion it excited, made him naturally recur to his own prospects.</s>
<s id="1:97">"Who knows," thought he, mournfully, "if I shall find work to do? perhaps things are not as they were in preceding years.</s>
<s id="1:98">Bartolo wishes me well, I know; he is a good fellow; he has made money; he has invited me many times to come to him; I am sure he will not abandon me.</s>
<s id="1:99">And then Providence has aided me until now; and will continue to do so."</s>
<s id="1:100">Meanwhile, the walk had sharpened his appetite; he could indeed have well waited to the end of his journey, which was only two miles farther, but he did not like to make his first appearance before his cousin as a hungry beggar; he therefore drew all his wealth from his pocket, and counting it on the palm of his hand, found that he had more than sufficient to procure a slight repast; after paying for which, he would still have a few pence remaining.</s>
<s id="1:101">As he came out of the inn at which he had rested, to proceed on his journey, he saw, lying near the door, two women: the one was elderly, and the other more youthful, with an infant in her arms, which was in vain seeking sustenance from its exhausted mother; both were of the complexion of death: by them stood a man, whose countenance and limbs gave signs of former vigour; now lost from long inanition.</s>
<s id="1:102">All three stretched forth their hands, but spoke not--what prayer could be so moving as their appearance.</s>
<s id="1:103">Renzo sighed; "There is a Providence," said he, as he placed in the nearest hand the last remnant of his wealth.</s>
<s id="1:104">The slight repast he had made, and the good deed he had performed (for we are composed of body and soul), had equally tended to refresh and invigorate him.</s>
<s id="1:105">If, to afford relief to these unhappy persons, Providence had kept in reserve the last farthing of a fugitive stranger, would he leave the wants of that stranger unsupplied?</s>
<s id="1:106">He looked with renewed hope to the future; he pictured to himself the return of abundant harvests, and in the mean time he had his cousin Bartolo and his own industry to depend on, and moreover he had left at home a small sum of money, the fruit of his economy, which he could send for, if needed.</s>
<s id="1:107">"Then," said he, "plenty will eventually return, and trade will be profitable again; the Milanese workmen will be in demand, and can set a high price on their labour; I shall have more than enough to satisfy my wants, and can lay by money, and can furnish my nice house, and then write to Agnes and Lucy to come--and then--</s>
<s id="1:108">But why wait for this?</s>
<s id="1:109">We should have been obliged to live, had we remained at home; we should have been obliged to live during this winter, upon my little savings, and we can do the same here.</s>
<s id="1:110">There are curates every where, and they can come shortly.</s>
<s id="1:111">Oh! what joy will it be to walk together on this same road; to go to the borders of the Adda, where I will point out to them the place where I embarked, the woods through which I passed, the spot where I stood watching for a boat."</s>
<s id="1:112">He reached at last the village of his cousin; at its entrance, he saw a very high house, with numerous windows, and perceived it to be a silk manufactory; he entered, and amidst the noise of the water and machinery loudly demanded, "if Bartolo Castagneri was within?"</s>
<s id="1:113">"Signor Bartolo? there he is."</s>
<s id="1:114">"Signor! that's a good sign," thought Renzo.</s>
<s id="1:115">He perceived his cousin, and ran towards him, </s>
<s id="1:116">exclaiming, "I am come at last!"</s>
<s id="1:117">Bartolo made an exclamation of surprise, and embraced him; he then took him into another chamber, apart from the noise of the machinery and the notice of the inquisitive, and said, "I am glad to see you, but you are a droll fellow.</s>
<s id="1:118">I have invited you many times to come hither; you have always refused, and now choose a most unfavourable moment."</s>
<s id="1:119">"What shall I say to you?</s>
<s id="1:120">I have not now come of my own free will," said Renzo; </s>
<s id="1:121">and he briefly, and with much emotion, related the mournful story.</s>
<s id="1:122">"That's another affair truly," said Bartolo.</s>
<s id="1:123">"Poor Renzo! you have relied on me, and I will not abandon you.</s>
<s id="1:124">To say truth, workmen are not in much demand at present; and it is with difficulty that those already engaged are kept by their employers.</s>
<s id="1:125">But my master regards me, and he has money; </s>
<s id="1:126">and besides, without boasting, we are equally dependent on each other--he has the capital, and I the skill, such as it is!</s>
<s id="1:127">I am his first workman, his factotum!</s>
<s id="1:128">Poor Lucy Mondella!</s>
<s id="1:129">I remember her as if it was but yesterday that I last saw her!</s>
<s id="1:130">An excellent girl! always so modest at church; and if you passed by her cottage--</s>
<s id="1:131">I see it now, the little cottage beyond the village, with a large fig-tree against the wall----"</s>
<s id="1:132">No, no, said Renzo, "do not speak of it."</s>
<s id="1:133"> "I meant to say, that if you passed it, you always heard the noise of her reel.</s>
<s id="1:134">And Don Roderick! even before I left, showed symptoms of his character; but now, it seems, he plays the devil outright, until God shall put a bridle on his neck.</s>
<s id="1:135">Well, as I said, we suffer here also the consequences of scarce harvests.--</s>
<s id="1:136">But, apropos, are you not hungry?"</s>
<s id="1:137">"It is not long since I have eaten," said Renzo.</s>
<s id="1:138">"And how are you off for money?"</s>
<s id="1:139">Renzo extended the palm of his hand and shook his head.</s>
<s id="1:140">"No matter," said Bartolo: "I have plenty.</s>
<s id="1:141">Cheer up; things will change for the better soon, and then you can repay me."</s>
<s id="1:142">"I have a small sum at home, and I will send for it."</s>
<s id="1:143">"Well, in the mean while, depend on me.</s>
<s id="1:144">God has given me wealth to spend for others, and above all, for my relations and friends."</s>
<s id="1:145">"I knew that you would befriend me," said Renzo, affectionately pressing his cousin's hand.</s>
<s id="1:146">"Well, what a fuss they have made at Milan," continued Bartolo; "the people seem to me to be mad.</s>
<s id="1:147">The report has reached us, but I shall be glad to know the particulars from you.</s>
<s id="1:148">I think we shall have enough to talk about, shall we not?</s>
<s id="1:149">Here, however, things are conducted with more judgment.</s>
<s id="1:150">The city purchased two thousand loads of corn from a merchant of Venice; the corn comes from Turkey.</s>
<s id="1:151">Now, what do you think happened?</s>
<s id="1:152">The governors of Verona and Brescia forbade the transit of the corn.</s>
<s id="1:153">What did the people of Bergamo do then, do you think?</s>
<s id="1:154">They sent to Venice a man that knew how to talk, I can tell you: he went to the doge, and made a speech which they say deserves to be printed!</s>
<s id="1:155">Immediately an order was sent to let the corn pass: the governors were obliged to obey.</s>
<s id="1:156">The country, too, has been thought of.</s>
<s id="1:157">Another good man informed the senate that the people here were famishing, and the senate granted us four thousand bushels of millet, which makes very good bread.</s>
<s id="1:158">And then, if there is no bread, you and I can eat meat; God has given me wealth I tell you.</s>
<s id="1:159">Now I will conduct you to my patron.</s>
<s id="1:160">I have often spoken of you to him; he will make you welcome.</s>
<s id="1:161">He is a native of Bergamo, a man of an excellent disposition.</s>
<s id="1:162">'Tis true, he did not expect you at this time, but when he learns your story--</s>
<s id="1:163">And then he knows how to value skilful workmen, because scarcity lasts but a little while, and business must finally go on.--</s>
<s id="1:164">But I must hint to you one thing; do you know what name they give to us Milanese in this country?"</s>
<s id="1:165">"What name they give us?"</s>
<s id="1:166">"They call us simpletons."</s>
<s id="1:167">"That is certainly not a very agreeable name."</s>
<s id="1:168">"What matters it?</s>
<s id="1:169">Whoever is born in the territory of Milan, and would gain his living in that of Bergamo, must put up with it.</s>
<s id="1:170">As to the people here, they call a Milanese a simpleton as freely as they call a gentleman sir."</s>
<s id="1:171">"They say so, I suppose, to those who will suffer it."</s>
<s id="1:172">"My good fellow, if you are not disposed to submit to be called simpleton, till it becomes familiar to your taste, you must not expect to live in Bergamo.</s>
<s id="1:173">You would always be obliged to carry your knife in hand; and when you had killed three or four, you might be killed yourself, and have to appear before the bar of God with three or four murders to answer for?" </s>
<s id="1:174">And a Milanese who understands his trade?</s>
<s id="1:175">"It is all the same; he would still be a simpleton.</s>
<s id="1:176">Do you know how my master expresses himself when he talks of me to his friends?</s>
<s id="1:177">Heaven has sent me this simpleton to carry on my business.</s>
<s id="1:178">If it were not for this simpleton I should never get on.</s>
<s id="1:179">It is the custom."</s>
<s id="1:180">"It is a silly custom, to say the least of it; </s>
<s id="1:181">and especially as it is we who have brought the art hither, and who carry it on.</s>
<s id="1:182">Is it possible that there is no remedy?"</s>
<s id="1:183">"None.</s>
<s id="1:184">Time may accomplish it.</s>
<s id="1:185">The next generation may be different, but at present we must submit.</s>
<s id="1:186">And after all, what is it?"</s>
<s id="1:187">Why, if there is no other evil---- </s>
<s id="1:188">"Ah! now that you are convinced, all will be well.</s>
<s id="1:189">Let us go to my master.</s>
<s id="1:190">Be of good courage." </s>
<s id="1:191">In fact, the promises of Bartolo were realised, and all was well.</s>
<s id="1:192">It was truly a kind Providence; for we shall see how little dependence Renzo could place on the treasure he had left at home,--the savings of his labour.</s>
</p>
</text>
