<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">"CARNEADES.</s>
    <s id="1:2">Who was he?"</s>
    <s id="1:3">Don Abbondio was pondering, as, with a book opened up before him, he sat in his great chair in a room of the upper floor, when Perpetua entered on her embassy.</s>
    <s id="1:4">"Carneades.</s>
    <s id="1:5">I seem to have read or heard of that name somewhere.</s>
    <s id="1:6">He must have been some scholar, a blue-stocking of antiquity——his name hath the ring of it.</s>
    <s id="1:7">But who the foul fiend was he?"——</s>
    <s id="1:8">So far was he from foreseeing the storm which was gathering about his head.</s>
    <s id="1:9">The reader should know that Don Abbondio diverted himself with reading a little each day, and a neighboring pastor who possessed a small library used to lend him one book after another——the first that came to hand.</s>
    <s id="1:10">The one over which Don Abbondio was then poring (during his convalescence from the fever which his fear had precipitated and from which——I mean the fever, not the fear——he was more nearly recovered than he would admit) was a panegyric on St. Charles, which had been pronounced with as much energy as it had been received with admiration two years before in the cathedral of Milan.</s>
    <s id="1:11">The saint was therein compared, for love of study, to Archimedes; and thus far Don Abbondio was not greatly embarrassed, because Archimedes' achievements are of such a curious order and of such common notoriety that it requires no vast erudition to know something of them.</s>
    <s id="1:12">But, after Archimedes, the orator went on to institute a parallel with Carneades; and here the reader was hopelessly marooned.</s>
    <s id="1:13">It was at this moment that Perpetua entered to announce Tonio's visit.</s>
    <s id="1:14">"At such an hour?" quoth Don Abbondio also, as was natural enough.</s>
    <s id="1:15">"What is there to do?</s>
    <s id="1:16">They lack all sense of propriety; but a bird in the hand————"</s>
    <s id="1:17">"To be sure.</s>
    <s id="1:18">Unless I take it now, Heaven knows when I shall get it.——</s>
    <s id="1:19">Hold! are you positive it is really he?"</s>
    <s id="1:20">"Pish!" replied Perpetua, starting off.</s>
    <s id="1:21">"Where are you?" she asked, as she opened the door.</s>
    <s id="1:22">Tonio came forward, and at the same time Agnese appeared, bidding Perpetua a good-even by name.</s>
    <s id="1:23">"Good-evening, Agnese.</s>
    <s id="1:24">And whence are you bound at such an hour?"</s>
    <s id="1:25">"I'm coming from ————" naming a near-by hamlet.</s>
    <s id="1:26">"And if you only knew——" she continued.</s>
    <s id="1:27">"Tis for your sake, moreover, that I stopped."</s>
    <s id="1:28">"Oh.</s>
    <s id="1:29">Why?" asked Perpetua; and, turning to the brothers, "Go in," she said, "and I'll be in after you."</s>
    <s id="1:30">"Because," Agnese responded, "one of those would-be oracles that get hold of the wrong end of everything would have it (just fancy!) that the reason you did not marry Beppe Suolavecchia or Anselmo Lunghigna was that they refused to have you.</s>
    <s id="1:31">I claimed that it was you who had refused them, both of them————"</s>
    <s id="1:32">"Certainly I did.</s>
    <s id="1:33">Oh, the false hussy, the lying vixen! </s>
    <s id="1:34">Who was it?"</s>
    <s id="1:35">"Nay, ask me not.</s>
    <s id="1:36">I do not wish to make bad blood."</s>
    <s id="1:37">"You shall tell me, you must tell me.</s>
    <s id="1:38">Oh, the detractor!" </s>
    <s id="1:39">"Prithee.</s>
    <s id="1:40">But you cannot imagine how vexed I was at not having the whole story, that I might have put her down."</s>
    <s id="1:41">"How can folks ever invent such stories!" exclaimed Perpetua anew; but she resumed immediately: "As for Beppe, it was plain to be seen, and everyone knows—— </s>
    <s id="1:42">Ho! there, Tonio, draw the door to, and go upstairs.</s>
    <s id="1:43">I am coming."</s>
    <s id="1:44">Tonio acquiesced from within, and Perpetua continued her impassioned narrative.</s>
    <s id="1:45">Opposite Don Abbondio's doorway stood two small tumble-down houses, and between them a lane opened into the fields beyond.</s>
    <s id="1:46">Agnese bent her steps in this direction, as if withdrawing somewhat for greater freedom, and Perpetua followed.</s>
    <s id="1:47">When they had turned a corner and were in a position whence it was impossible to see what took place in front of Don Abbondio's, Agnese gave a loud cough.</s>
    <s id="1:48">It was the signal.</s>
    <s id="1:49">Renzo heard it, and, pressing Lucia's arm to reassure her, he and she stole ahead, walking on tiptoe and grazing against the wall.</s>
    <s id="1:50">On arriving at the entrance, they pushed open the door noiselessly, and, crouching down, crept silently into the passage-way, where the two brothers awaited them.</s>
    <s id="1:51">Renzo closed the door again without making the faintest sound, and together they mounted the stairs, but so lightly that it might have been one instead of four.</s>
    <s id="1:52">Once at the top, the brothers approached the door, which opened to one side of the landing.</s>
    <s id="1:53">The two lovers huddled close to the wall.</s>
    <s id="1:54">"Deo gratias," said Tonio in a good clear voice.</s>
    <s id="1:55">"Tonio, eh?</s>
    <s id="1:56">Come in," replied a voice inside.</s>
    <s id="1:57">Thus invited, Tonio opened the door, but barely wide enough for himself and Gervaso to pass one at a time.</s>
    <s id="1:58">The light, suddenly flooding through this opening and forming a bright pathway across the dark landing, caused Lucia to start as if she had been discovered.</s>
    <s id="1:59">Tonio drew the door after him, and the lovers remained motionless, with ears strained and bated breath, in the shadow.</s>
    <s id="1:60">The loudest noise was made by the beating of poor Lucia's heart.</s>
    <s id="1:61">Don Abbondio was seated, as we have said, in an old armchair, with a shabby cloak gathered about him and on his head a well-worn skull-cap, which by the indistinct light of a small lamp gave his face the appearance of being in a frame.</s>
    <s id="1:62">Two shaggy locks escaped from under his cap, and the general effect of their hoary whiteness against the swart, wrinkled visage, with its shaggy eyebrows, shaggy mustaches and chin-tuft, all silvered alike by age, was somewhat like those snow-covered clumps of bushes that one may see hanging against the face of a cliff in the moonlight.</s>
    <s id="1:63">"Huh!" was the salutation with which he greeted them, as he took off his glasses and put them into his book.</s>
    <s id="1:64">"Your reverence will say that I came late," said Tonio with a bow, whose awkwardness was exaggerated in Gervaso's imitation of it.</s>
    <s id="1:65">"Indeed, it is late——late in every sense of the word.</s>
    <s id="1:66">Knew you not that I am ill?"</s>
    <s id="1:67">"Oh.</s>
    <s id="1:68">I am sorry, in good sooth."</s>
    <s id="1:69">"You must needs have heard some rumors of it.</s>
    <s id="1:70">I am ill and know not when I can see people—— </s>
    <s id="1:71">But why are you lugging that——that lad there after you?"</s>
    <s id="1:72">"For company, your reverence." </s>
    <s id="1:73">"Well, well; let us not waste time."</s>
    <s id="1:74">"Here be the twenty-five fire-new berlinghe——you know——with St. Ambrose on horseback," said Tonio, drawing a purse from his pocket.</s>
    <s id="1:75">"Let us see," responded Don Abbondio, taking the purse into his hands.</s>
    <s id="1:76">Then, resuming his glasses, he undid the string and took out the coins, which, after counting and turning over and over again, he found to be quite unexceptionable.</s>
    <s id="1:77">"Now your reverence will give me back Tecla's necklace." </s>
    <s id="1:78">"Right enough," replied Don Abbondio.</s>
    <s id="1:79">Then, going to a cabinet and looking round him as he drew the key from his pocket, as if bidding onlookers to keep their distance, he partially opened one of the doors, thrusting his body into the aperture, and poked his head into the interior to look for the necklace.</s>
    <s id="1:80">He then reached in for it, and having closed the cabinet, gave Tonio his property, saying: "Is everything all right?"</s>
    <s id="1:81">"Now," said Tonio, "if you will be good enough to put it down in black and white."</s>
    <s id="1:82">"That too!" said Don Abbondio.</s>
    <s id="1:83">"'Tis a knowing swain.</s>
    <s id="1:84">Faugh! how suspicious the world is becoming.</s>
    <s id="1:85">Don't you trust me?"</s>
    <s id="1:86">"Not trust your reverence?</s>
    <s id="1:87">You do me wrong.</s>
    <s id="1:88">But since my name is already on the wrong side of your books—— </s>
    <s id="1:89">That is, since you have not found it irksome to write it out once, perhaps—— </s>
    <s id="1:90">We're here today and in our graves tomorrow, you know."</s>
    <s id="1:91">"Very well, very well," interrupted Don Abbondio, and grumblingly pulled out a drawer of his desk from which he brought forth pen, ink and paper, and started to write, repeating each word aloud as he formed it with his pen.</s>
    <s id="1:92">Meanwhile, Tonio and, at a gesture from him, Gervaso, took their stand in front of the desk in such a manner as to obstruct the writer's view of the doorway and set to scraping the floor with his feet, idly it would appear, but in reality to give the couple outside a signal to enter, and, at the same time, to cover up the noise of their footfalls.</s>
    <s id="1:93">Don Abbondio, absorbed in his writing, had no attention left for aught else.</s>
    <s id="1:94">At the sound of the scraping Renzo took Lucia's arm, giving it another reassuring squeeze, and started in, drawing her along with him.</s>
    <s id="1:95">She trembled so that of herself she would never have been able to budge.</s>
    <s id="1:96">They glided in on tiptoe, not even breathing as they went, and hid behind the brothers.</s>
    <s id="1:97">Don Abbondio had finished writing in the meantime, and without raising his eyes from the paper, started to read it over.</s>
    <s id="1:98">He then folded it double, saying: "Now are you satisfied?"</s>
    <s id="1:99">And, taking off his glasses with one hand and handing the receipt to Tonio with the other, he looked up.</s>
    <s id="1:100">Tonio, at the same time that he reached out for the document, stepped to one side, Gervaso, at a direction from him, stepped to the other, and in the middle, as if a stage-setting had suddenly opened up, stood Renzo and Lucia.</s>
    <s id="1:101">Don Abbondio at first saw the proceeding as if in a dream.</s>
    <s id="1:102">Then fear, dismay and rage followed one another in quick succession.</s>
    <s id="1:103">Finally, collecting his wits, he hit on a plan of action——all this in the time it took Renzo to say: "Your reverence, in the presence of these witnesses, this is my wife."</s>
    <s id="1:104">Hardly had the words left his lips, when Don Abbondio, dropping the receipt from his fingers and seizing the lamp with his left hand, grabbed off the desk-cover with his right, scattering book, paper, ink and blotting-sand all over the floor in his mad haste, and made a bound between the desk and the armchair towards Lucia.</s>
    <s id="1:105">The poor maid, in accents mild as always, but now trembling besides, was just beginning: "And this——" when Don Abbondio unceremoniously clapped the desk-cover over her head and face so as to hinder her from completing the formula.</s>
    <s id="1:106">Another instant, and, having dropped the lamp, the left hand was assisting in the operation of making a muffler out of the desk-cover, with the result that she was well-nigh stifled.</s>
    <s id="1:107">In the meantime he never ceased screaming at the pitch of his voice: "Perpetua.</s>
    <s id="1:108">Perpetua.</s>
    <s id="1:109">Treason.</s>
    <s id="1:110">Help!" </s>
    <s id="1:111">The wick, which was flickering out its last on the floor, cast a pale wavering light on Lucia, who stood in a daze, not even making a move to disengage herself——not unlike a sculptor's clay model over which he has thrown a dampened cloth.</s>
    <s id="1:112">When the last glimmer had expired, Don Abbondio left the distraught maiden to herself and felt his way to the door of an adjoining chamber, in which he locked himself, screaming without intermission: "Perpetua.</s>
    <s id="1:113">Treason.</s>
    <s id="1:114">Help.</s>
    <s id="1:115">Out of my house! out of my house!"</s>
    <s id="1:116">In the first room all was confusion.</s>
    <s id="1:117">Renzo was seeking to intercept the priest, and, groping about as if he were playing at blindman's-buff, he at last found the door, and, rapping on it, cried: "Open up! open up.</s>
    <s id="1:118">Cease your outcry!"</s>
    <s id="1:119">Lucia was adjuring Renzo in a voice husky with terror to come away by all that was holy.</s>
    <s id="1:120">Tonio was down on all fours, scouring the floor for the lost receipt.</s>
    <s id="1:121">Gervaso, frightened out of his wits, danced about, screaming like one possessed and searching for the stair-door to flee for safety.</s>
    <s id="1:122">In the midst of all this hurly-burly we cannot forbear pausing an instant to make a reflection.</s>
    <s id="1:123">Renzo, who has raised all this nocturnal racket in the house of another, who gained an entrance surreptitiously and is now besieging the master of the house himself in one of his rooms, has all the appearance of an aggressor; still, in the last analysis, he is the oppressed.</s>
    <s id="1:124">Don Abbondio, waylaid and put to flight in terror while he was peaceably minding his own business, seems to be the victim; still, in reality, it is he who was guilty of oppression.</s>
    <s id="1:125">This is often the way things go in the world——I mean to say, the way they went in the seventeenth century.</s>
    <s id="1:126">The beleaguered, seeing that the enemy gave no sign of raising the siege, opened the window giving on the church-square and set up a yelling for help.</s>
    <s id="1:127">The moon shone brightly.</s>
    <s id="1:128">The shadow of the church, and farther on, the long, pointed shadow of the steeple, stood out dark and clear-cut against the glistening lawn of the square.</s>
    <s id="1:129">One could distinguish every object almost as clearly as by day.</s>
    <s id="1:130">But as far as the eye could reach there was no sign of a living person.</s>
    <s id="1:131">Under the wall of the church, however, on that side which faced the parochial residence, stood a small abode hardly larger than a kennel, where the sacristan slept.</s>
    <s id="1:132">He was aroused by the unconscionable screaming, and, leaping from his bed, he thrust his head out of the window with his eyes still glued together and asked the cause of the pother.</s>
    <s id="1:133">"Come quick, Ambrogio.</s>
    <s id="1:134">Help.</s>
    <s id="1:135">People in the house!"</s>
    <s id="1:136">Don Abbondio hallooed across to him.</s>
    <s id="1:137">"At once," he replied, and, drawing in his head, closed the window.</s>
    <s id="1:138">Though half-asleep and something more than half-scared, he bethought himself on the spur of the moment of an expedient to give more help than was desired without involving himself in the fray, whatever might be its nature.</s>
    <s id="1:139">Grabbing up his breeches, which lay upon the bed, and tucking them under his arm as one might a dress-hat, he tore down the narrow stairs and made for the belfry, where he seized the rope of the larger of a pair of bells and started pealing out an alarm.</s>
    <s id="1:140">Dong! dong! dong! dong.</s>
    <s id="1:141">Up spring the peasants in their beds.</s>
    <s id="1:142">The younger men in their lofts strain their ears and jump to their feet.</s>
    <s id="1:143">"What is it?</s>
    <s id="1:144">What is it?</s>
    <s id="1:145">The alarm bell?</s>
    <s id="1:146">Fire?——thieves?——bandits?——which?"</s>
    <s id="1:147">Wives entreat their husbands to stay in bed and let the others do the gadding.</s>
    <s id="1:148">As for the men, some rise and go to the window; the cowardly to come back and get between the sheets, as if in answer to their wives' entreaties; the more courageous or the more curious to go below and, arming themselves with pitchforks or muskets, to hurry off to the summons.</s>
    <s id="1:149">Some simply wait for developments.</s>
    <s id="1:150">But before this volunteer host was in motion, indeed before they were well awake, the noise had reached the ears of other persons not far away who were on their feet and dressed——the bravos in one quarter, and Agnese and Perpetua in another.</s>
    <s id="1:151">Let us describe briefly the doings of the former from the moment when we left them, some in the abandoned dwelling, some at the inn.</s>
    <s id="1:152">The three latter, when they saw the doors all closed and the street deserted, hurried off as if they had only just adverted to the lateness of the hour, saying that they must be going home.</s>
    <s id="1:153">They took a turn through the village to ascertain whether all had retired.</s>
    <s id="1:154">Not a living soul was to be met with; not the faintest noise reached their ears.</s>
    <s id="1:155">With furtive steps they passed by Agnese's poor cottage: it was the quietest of all, being empty.</s>
    <s id="1:156">Then straight to the abandoned dwelling, where they made their report to Griso.</s>
    <s id="1:157">This gentleman immediately arrayed himself in a palmer's cloak of waxed cloth strewn with cockle-shells, took a pilgrim's staff in his hand, placed on his head an unsightly old hat, and saying, "Come, lads, let us to it bravely——no talking and look to your commands," he led off the expedition.</s>
    <s id="1:158">Within a few moments they were at the cottage, having followed a direction opposite to that which our little party took in starting forth on their own expedition.</s>
    <s id="1:159">Griso halted his band some paces off and went forward alone to reconnoitre.</s>
    <s id="1:160">Finding all still and deserted without, he summoned two of his ruffians and ordered them to scale the garden-wall noiselessly and hide in a corner behind a thick-leafed fig-tree on which his eye had lighted that morning.</s>
    <s id="1:161">This done, he gave a subdued rap at the gate, intending to say that he was a pilgrim who had lost his way and to ask shelter till morning.</s>
    <s id="1:162">On receiving no answer, he knocked again a little louder.</s>
    <s id="1:163">Not a sound comes from within.</s>
    <s id="1:164">Thereupon he goes after a third member of his rascally crew and makes him scale the wall in the same manner as the other two, with orders to unscrew the latch gently, so as to leave a free passage in and out; all of which is carried out with the utmost caution and the most gratifying success.</s>
    <s id="1:165">Then, summoning the rest, he takes them along in and sends them off to hide with the first, afterwards stealthily closing the gate and posting two sentinels on the inside.</s>
    <s id="1:166">He now goes straight to the housedoor and knocks once more.</s>
    <s id="1:167">Again he waits——as well he may.</s>
    <s id="1:168">This door, in turn, is noiselessly taken off its hinges, and still not a word of challenge nor a sign of life from within.</s>
    <s id="1:169">What more could be wished for?</s>
    <s id="1:170">On, on, then, Griso; there is not a minute to lose.</s>
    <s id="1:171">"Hist!" he calls to those under the fig-tree, and with them enters the room on the ground floor, where he had that morning fraudulently begged an alms of bread.</s>
    <s id="1:172">Then, producing flint, steel, tinder and sulphur splints, he lights a small lantern and looks about an adjoining room to make sure that no one is there.</s>
    <s id="1:173">It is empty.</s>
    <s id="1:174">He next goes to the stair-door and peers up, straining his ear for the faintest sound.</s>
    <s id="1:175">The solitude and silence are unbroken.</s>
    <s id="1:176">Leaving two more sentinels below, he chooses for his immediate partner a bravo named Grignapoco from the state of Bergamo, who was to make all threats, do all the coaxing, issue all commands——who, in fact, was to be sole spokesman, to the end that Agnese might be induced to believe that the expedition came from those parts.</s>
    <s id="1:177">With him at his shoulder and the others in his wake, Griso creeps slowly up the stairs, cursing in his heart every step that creaks and every noise that one of the cutthroats behind him makes with his feet.</s>
    <s id="1:178">At length the top is reached.</s>
    <s id="1:179">Here, at last, lies the quarry.</s>
    <s id="1:180">Gently he tries the door leading into the first room——it gives.</s>
    <s id="1:181">He looks in through the crack, but everything is dark; he applies his ear to listen for some sound or snoring or breathing or some rustling of the bed, but all within is silent as the tomb.</s>
    <s id="1:182">On, then, Griso; it is but one step more.</s>
    <s id="1:183">Holding the lantern up before his face, so as to see without being seen in turn, he throws the door wide open and rushes towards the bed.</s>
    <s id="1:184">It is untouched.</s>
    <s id="1:185">The coverlet is still unruffled, with the end folded back neatly over the bolster.</s>
    <s id="1:186">With a shrug of the shoulders he turns towards his crew and indicates by a gesture that he is going to look in the other room and that they are to follow without making any noise.</s>
    <s id="1:187">There, he goes through the same routine and finds the same state of affairs.</s>
    <s id="1:188">"What the foul fiend is the meaning of this?" he says.</s>
    <s id="1:189">"Has some dog of a traitor turned informer?"</s>
    <s id="1:190">Thereupon, with caution much abated, they all set themselves to ransacking the whole house, ferreting in every nook and corner and turning the place topsy-turvy.</s>
    <s id="1:191">While this part of the band were thus occupied, the pair who were on guard at the street gate heard the sudden patter of childish footsteps hastening towards them.</s>
    <s id="1:192">Fancying that whoever it was would pass by, they kept perfectly still and, for caution's sake, keenly on the alert.</s>
    <s id="1:193">They were justified in the event, for the steps stopped just at the gate.</s>
    <s id="1:194">It was Menico running back home from Father Cristoforo with a solemn adjuration to Lucia and her mother to flee their home without delay and take refuge in the monastery for the reason——for the reason which the reader already knows.</s>
    <s id="1:195">He took hold of the latch-pin to use it in lieu of a knocker and felt the bolt dangle idly in his hand.</s>
    <s id="1:196">"What is this?" he thought, fearfully pushing the gate, which opened to his touch.</s>
    <s id="1:197">He stepped inside with great misgivings.</s>
    <s id="1:198">On the instant he felt himself seized by the shoulders and heard a menacing voice at either side of him say in subdued tones: "Silence, or you die."</s>
    <s id="1:199">By way of compliance he let out a vociferous yell.</s>
    <s id="1:200">One of the ruffians clapped a hand over his mouth, while the other drew a murderous-looking knife to terrify him.</s>
    <s id="1:201">The lad trembled like an aspen-leaf and did not even make an effort to raise his voice again.</s>
    <s id="1:202">But all at once a far more ominous sound than Menico's piping tones arose on the air, as that first awful stroke of the church-bell boomed out, and in its wake a whole ordnance of them in quick succession.</s>
    <s id="1:203">Evil-doers are evil-dreaders, as the Milanese proverb says.</s>
    <s id="1:204">To each of the two marauders it seemed that the brazen notes of the alarm-bell were spelling out his own name, surname and sobriquet.</s>
    <s id="1:205">They released Menico's arms and stood looking at each other, with gaping mouths and fear-benumbed hands, and the next instant dashed into the house to rejoin the main body of the party.</s>
    <s id="1:206">Off scampered Menico down the road in the direction of the belfry, where at all events someone would be found.</s>
    <s id="1:207">The rest of the scoundrels, who were at that moment ransacking the house from top to bottom, were affected by the terrible clap in the same way as the first two.</s>
    <s id="1:208">Panic-stricken, they jostled one against another helter-skelter in a general rush for the exit.</s>
    <s id="1:209">Still, not one of them but was a tried man, accustomed to face the enemy; but such an ill-defined danger, bursting on them suddenly like a bolt from the blue, was more than they could stand.</s>
    <s id="1:210">It needed all of Griso's ascendancy to hold them together and save their retreat from becoming a rout.</s>
    <s id="1:211">If the reader has ever seen a dog accompanying a herd of swine and watched him as he runs hither and thither after the vagabonds, nosing this one into line, snapping at that one by the ear and barking at a third which starts at the same instant to leave the path, he can easily form a picture of Griso in palmer's attire laying about him, cuffing back one bravo who had already reached the threshold, stopping the flight of a second and a third with his staff, calling after the others who ran back and forth without knowing which way to turn, until finally he had them all corralled in the middle of the courtyard.</s>
    <s id="1:212">"Be quick, now," said he.</s>
    <s id="1:213">"Pistols in your hands, knives within reach, and all together, so; and then away.</s>
    <s id="1:214">Who will ever raise a hand against you if you stand together, you dolts?</s>
    <s id="1:215">But if you let yourselves be set upon one by one, even these louts of peasants will lay you by the heels.</s>
    <s id="1:216">Follow me, you poltroons, and keep together."</s>
    <s id="1:217">After this brief harangue he placed himself at their head and led them off.</s>
    <s id="1:218">The house stood, as we have said, on the edge of the village.</s>
    <s id="1:219">Griso took the road leading out into the country, and the others followed after in good order.</s>
    <s id="1:220">Leaving them to pursue their way, let us now return to Agnese and Perpetua, whom we last saw strolling down a certain lane.</s>
    <s id="1:221">Agnese had bent her efforts towards drawing the other as far away as possible from Don Abbondio's, and up to a certain point all had gone well.</s>
    <s id="1:222">But suddenly the housekeeper bethought herself of the open door, and would fain turn back.</s>
    <s id="1:223">To remonstrate was impossible.</s>
    <s id="1:224">There was nothing for it but for Agnese to turn back also, so as not to excite suspicion; so, lagging along behind her conductor, she sought to detain her each time that she saw her wax warm on the subject of the frustrated marriages.</s>
    <s id="1:225">She made a show of listening spellbound to the narrative and every once in a while, under pretext of interest or to steer the conversation into other channels, she would say: "Why, to be sure, now I understand.</s>
    <s id="1:226">Just so.</s>
    <s id="1:227">It's clear as daylight.</s>
    <s id="1:228">And now as to him?</s>
    <s id="1:229">And you?"</s>
    <s id="1:230">But all the while she held quite other colloquy with herself: "Are they out yet, or still in the house?</s>
    <s id="1:231">What a trio of blockheads we are not to have concerted some signal, to let me know when it is over. '</s>
    <s id="1:232">Twas badly botched; but now the milk is spilled, and there is no help for it but to hold off this magpie as long as possible.</s>
    <s id="1:233">At the worst, 'twill be only so much lost time."</s>
    <s id="1:234">Thus, walking by fits and starts, they had arrived within a short distance of the house, which, however, could not be seen on account of the bend in the road of which mention has been made.</s>
    <s id="1:235">Perpetua had reached an important point in her narrative and allowed her progress to be checked without demur, and indeed, without adverting to it, when all at once Don Abbondio's first stentorian call for help pierced the unbroken stillness of the slumbering night air.</s>
    <s id="1:236">"God 'a' mercy.</s>
    <s id="1:237">What has happened?" cried Perpetua, starting to run.</s>
    <s id="1:238">"What's the matter?" said Agnese, holding her by the skirts.</s>
    <s id="1:239">"God 'a' mercy.</s>
    <s id="1:240">Did you not hear?" replied the other, struggling to release herself.</s>
    <s id="1:241">"What is it? what is it?" repeated Agnese, clutching her by the arm.</s>
    <s id="1:242">"Pest of a woman!" exclaimed Perpetua, pushing her aside and setting herself at liberty.</s>
    <s id="1:243">She turned to fly, and at the same instant Menico's screams rang out, farther off but shriller and more startled.</s>
    <s id="1:244">"God 'a' mercy on us!" now exclaimed Agnese, darting off after the other.</s>
    <s id="1:245">Her heels were barely off the ground when the church-bell crashed out——once, twice, thrice, and many more.</s>
    <s id="1:246">They would have been spurs to her flight had any been needed.</s>
    <s id="1:247">Perpetua arrived a moment before her companion.</s>
    <s id="1:248">As she was on the point of shoving the door, it was thrown open from within, and on the threshold appeared Tonio, Gervaso, Renzo and Lucia, who had come leaping down the stairway once it was found, and, hearing the peal of that terrible bell, were making off in furious haste to reach a place of safety.</s>
    <s id="1:249">"What is it? what is it?"</s>
    <s id="1:250">Perpetua breathlessly asked of the two brothers, who pushed her nearly off her feet for reply and scuttled away.</s>
    <s id="1:251">"And you! you! what are you doing here?" she then asked of the other pair when she had made them out.</s>
    <s id="1:252">But they, too, made their exit without answering.</s>
    <s id="1:253">Perpetua, to be on hand where the need was paramount, asked no more questions but hurried into the hall and, making the best of her way through the darkness, ran for the stairs.</s>
    <s id="1:254">The betrothed lovers found themselves facing Agnese, still only betrothed.</s>
    <s id="1:255">"Oh, you are here," she said, panting so that she could hardly speak.</s>
    <s id="1:256">"How did it thrive?</s>
    <s id="1:257">What means this ringing?</s>
    <s id="1:258">Methinks I heard————"</s>
    <s id="1:259">"Get we home, get we home," said Renzo, "before the people come."</s>
    <s id="1:260">They were on the point of starting, when Menico dashed up.</s>
    <s id="1:261">He recognized them, and, still trembling all over, stayed their flight, saying hoarsely: "Whither would you go?</s>
    <s id="1:262">Turn back, turn back.</s>
    <s id="1:263">To the monastery.</s>
    <s id="1:264">This way."</s>
    <s id="1:265">"Was it you——?"</s>
    <s id="1:266">Agnese was beginning.</s>
    <s id="1:267">"What else is amiss?" asked Renzo. </s>
    <s id="1:268">Lucia trembled and held her peace in unabated dismay.</s>
    <s id="1:269">"All Bedlam is loose in the house," replied Menico, gasping for breath. </s>
    <s id="1:270">"I saw them with my own eyes.</s>
    <s id="1:271">They would have murdered me—— </s>
    <s id="1:272">Father Cristoforo said——for you too, Renzo——that you should come at once—— </s>
    <s id="1:273">I saw them, so I did.</s>
    <s id="1:274">What a mercy I found you all here.</s>
    <s id="1:275">I'll tell you the rest when we are out of this."</s>
    <s id="1:276">Renzo, whose head was the clearest of all, was of opinion that it behooved them to make off in one direction or another before the crowd gathered, and that the safest course was to do what Menico advised, nay commanded, with all the insistence of terror.</s>
    <s id="1:277">The boy could then be made to explain more coherently when they were on their way and well out of danger.</s>
    <s id="1:278">"Walk ahead," he said to him; "and let us accompany him," he said to the two women.</s>
    <s id="1:279">Turning their steps towards the church, they hastened across the square, where, providentially, no one was yet to be seen; then down the lane that separated the church from Don Abbondio's house and off through the first gap in the hedge into the fields.</s>
    <s id="1:280">They had advanced not fifty paces, perhaps, when a stream of people began to flow into the church-square, and each moment swelled its volume.</s>
    <s id="1:281">They looked into one another's face, each with a question on his lips, none with a reply.</s>
    <s id="1:282">The first to arrive rushed to the church-door——it was locked.</s>
    <s id="1:283">They then ran to the belfry.</s>
    <s id="1:284">One of them, putting his mouth up to a small window, or rather, a kind of embrasure in the wall, roared through, demanding by all the powers of darkness to know what was wrong.</s>
    <s id="1:285">When Ambrogio heard a familiar voice, he let go the bell-rope, and, assured by the murmur outside of a great concourse of people, he replied that he would open the door.</s>
    <s id="1:286">Pulling on the gear which he had borne off under his arm, he came through the interior to the portal of the church and opened to the throng.</s>
    <s id="1:287">"What means all this hue-and-cry?</s>
    <s id="1:288">What's wrong?</s>
    <s id="1:289">Where are we to go?</s>
    <s id="1:290">Who is it?"</s>
    <s id="1:291">"What.</s>
    <s id="1:292">Who is it?" said Ambrogio, with one hand holding the door open and with the other taking a hitch in the garment which he had donned so hastily.</s>
    <s id="1:293">"What.</s>
    <s id="1:294">Know you not that there are marauders in the pastor's house?</s>
    <s id="1:295">Blithely, my lads; to the rescue!"</s>
    <s id="1:296">They turned about at that and swarmed towards the house.</s>
    <s id="1:297">They looked up at it, listening for some sound from within; but all was quiet.</s>
    <s id="1:298">Some ran around to the front door; it was closed and bore no traces of having been touched.</s>
    <s id="1:299">These also looked up at the second story; not a window was open and all was silent as the tomb.</s>
    <s id="1:300">"Halloo! halloo.</s>
    <s id="1:301">Who is there?</s>
    <s id="1:302">Don Abbondio.</s>
    <s id="1:303">Don Abbondio!"</s>
    <s id="1:304">Don Abbondio, who was no sooner assured of the invaders' flight than he drew in his head and closed the window, and was at that instant engaged in a subdued altercation with Perpetua for having left him alone in such an ordeal, had no choice, on hearing the populace clamor for him, but to go to the window once again.</s>
    <s id="1:305">When he saw the number who had come to his relief, he repented of summoning them.</s>
    <s id="1:306">"What hath happened?</s>
    <s id="1:307">What have they done?</s>
    <s id="1:308">Who were they?</s>
    <s id="1:309">Where did they go?" were the questions that were put to him by fifty voices at once.</s>
    <s id="1:310">"There is nobody now.</s>
    <s id="1:311">I am much beholden to you.</s>
    <s id="1:312">Now return to your homes again."</s>
    <s id="1:313">"But who was it?</s>
    <s id="1:314">Where have they gone?</s>
    <s id="1:315">What befell?" </s>
    <s id="1:316">"People who meant no good——fly-by-nights; but they have decamped.</s>
    <s id="1:317">Return to your homes; the danger is over for this time, my sons.</s>
    <s id="1:318">Gramercy for your goodness of heart."</s>
    <s id="1:319">So saying, he drew in his head and closed the window.</s>
    <s id="1:320">Hereupon some set to grumbling and others to jesting, some gave vent to profanity and still others, shrugging their shoulders, were starting away, when a newcomer arrived, so exhausted that it was with difficulty he could frame his speech coherently. </s>
    <s id="1:321">He was a man whose house stood almost opposite to Agnese's, and who from his window, whither he had gone at the sound of the alarm, had seen the confusion of the bravos in the courtyard that Griso was at such pains to control.</s>
    <s id="1:322">His first care, on recovering his breath, was to cry out: "What are you doing here, my lads?</s>
    <s id="1:323">It's down the street that Old Nick is loose, not here——down at Agnese Mondella's——men armed to the teeth——and inside the house.</s>
    <s id="1:324">They seem to be murdering a palmer.</s>
    <s id="1:325">The Lord only knoweth what's amiss." </s>
    <s id="1:326">"What? what? what? what?"</s>
    <s id="1:327">A stormy consultation ensued.</s>
    <s id="1:328">"Let us go," said one.</s>
    <s id="1:329">"Let us look into it," said another.</s>
    <s id="1:330">"What do they number?" asked one.</s>
    <s id="1:331">"What do we number ourselves?" queried a second.</s>
    <s id="1:332">"Who are they?" contributed a third.</s>
    <s id="1:333">Then, by acclamation, they demanded: "The consul! the consul!"</s>
    <s id="1:334">"I am here," replied the consul from the midst of the crowd; "I am here, but I must have your aid and obedience.</s>
    <s id="1:335">Quick.</s>
    <s id="1:336">Where is the sacristan?</s>
    <s id="1:337">Toll the bell, toll the bell.</s>
    <s id="1:338">Quick.</s>
    <s id="1:339">A man to run to Lecco for reenforcements.</s>
    <s id="1:340">This way, all ....."</s>
    <s id="1:341">Some pressed forward, others were squeezing a way out to take themselves off.</s>
    <s id="1:342">The confusion was prodigious, when a man who had seen Griso's band beating such a hasty retreat came upon the scene and screamed: "Come quick, lads.</s>
    <s id="1:343">Thieves or bandits, who are carrying off a palmer.</s>
    <s id="1:344">They are already outside the village.</s>
    <s id="1:345">After them.</s>
    <s id="1:346">After them!"</s>
    <s id="1:347">At this announcement the mob started off without awaiting any word of command from their captain and rushed down the street pell-mell, some of those at the vanguard gradually dropping back as the army advanced and choking up the ranks of the main body, while those in the rear simultaneously closed in.</s>
    <s id="1:348">At length they reached the place designated, a confused and motley throng.</s>
    <s id="1:349">The traces of the invasion were fresh and unequivocal, the gate gaping open and its fastenings torn off; but the invaders had disappeared.</s>
    <s id="1:350">They entered the courtyard and approached the house entrance; this door also was unhinged and wide open.  "Agnese.</s>
    <s id="1:351">Lucia! palmer!" they cried out.</s>
    <s id="1:352">"Where's the palmer?</s>
    <s id="1:353">Stefano must have been dreaming." </s>
    <s id="1:354">"No, no; Carlandrea saw him, too." </s>
    <s id="1:355">"Halloo! palmer.</s>
    <s id="1:356">Agnese.</s>
    <s id="1:357">Lucia!" </s>
    <s id="1:358">No reply. </s>
    <s id="1:359">"They have been kidnapped," they then told one another.</s>
    <s id="1:360">Some among them thereupon spoke up, proposing to go in pursuit of the kidnappers.</s>
    <s id="1:361">It was outrageous, they said, and their village would suffer grave scorn if every rogue in the realm could thus come and carry off their towns-women from under their eyes, as a kite might chicks from an empty threshing-floor.</s>
    <s id="1:362">A new and stormier consultation then began; when some one (and it was never well known who) launched the rumor that Agnese and Lucia had taken refuge with some neighbor.</s>
    <s id="1:363">The rumor flew rapidly from mouth to mouth and was accepted as the truth.</s>
    <s id="1:364">From that on there was no further talk of giving chase to the fugitives; the band dispersed and each wended his way back home.</s>
    <s id="1:365">The murmur of voices lingered for a while on the air, and the sound of tramping filled the streets, to be succeeded by a rapping at doors and a hoisting of windows.</s>
    <s id="1:366">Women's heads were thrust out inquiringly and men's voices answered from beneath.</s>
    <s id="1:367">Lights twinkled, hinges creaked and silence reigned once more in the deserted street.</s>
    <s id="1:368">The conversation eddied along within doors for some time still, until it finally died away in yawning.</s>
    <s id="1:369">The next morning saw tongues wagging again, but there was no further incident——except that the consul, while standing in his field with his elbow leaning on the handle of his spade and his foot resting on the blade driven half-way into the clod, and speculating upon the respective merits of the course which his duty prescribed and of that which caution suggested, was approached by two men of burly mien, grisly as the early race of Frankish kings and further remarkable for the striking resemblance they presented to the pair who had accosted Don Abbondio five days previously——if, in fact, they were not the identical pair.</s>
    <s id="1:370">With still less ceremony on this occasion they enjoined the consul that he should carefully refrain from making any deposition on the occurrence before the podestà, that he should dissimulate the truth in case that he happened to be called upon to testify, and that he should neither prattle himself nor encourage the prattling of the villagers, if he laid any store by dying in his bed.</s>
    <s id="1:371">Our fugitives proceeded some distance at a good round pace, looking back by turns to see if any one followed.</s>
    <s id="1:372">It was a silent journey.</s>
    <s id="1:373">They were all of them overwrought, as well from the stress of their flight and the excitement and suspense to which they had been subjected as from the bitterness of their frustrated hopes and the vague apprehensions raised by this new and dimly defined danger. </s>
    <s id="1:374">The inexorable tolling of the church-bell, growing fainter and hollower as they proceeded, but taking on at the same time a strangely ominous and sinister character, contributed no little to their agitation of mind.</s>
    <s id="1:375">The ringing finally ceased.</s>
    <s id="1:376">The fugitives happening just then to be in an empty field and hearing not a stir about them, slackened their pace.</s>
    <s id="1:377">It was Agnese who first broke the silence.</s>
    <s id="1:378">As soon as she had recovered her breath she inquired of Renzo how his affairs had thrived and of Menico what was the nature of the disturbance he had seen in the house.</s>
    <s id="1:379">Renzo briefly related his sad tale; whereupon all three turned to the boy.</s>
    <s id="1:380">He delivered the monk's admonition in greater detail than before and related the scene he had witnessed and the danger he had run——all of which served to invest the admonition with additional authority and to convey to the listeners a meaning of which the informant himself was innocent.</s>
    <s id="1:381">They shuddered at the disclosure, and looking from one to another, they were all three rooted to the spot by a common impulse of horror.</s>
    <s id="1:382">Then with one accord they began to shower endearments on Menico, one patting him on the head, another on the shoulders, to express their silent thanks for his having been their guardian-angel, to testify the compassion which they felt for the anguish he had experienced and the perils he had encountered in their defence, and almost to apologize to him for their having been the occasion of his jeopardy.</s>
    <s id="1:383">"And now return home," said Agnese, "that your parents may be disquieted about you no longer"; and remembering her promise of the two parpagliole, she put her hand into her pocket and drew out double the number, adding as she gave them to him: "Enough said.</s>
    <s id="1:384">Pray God we may soon meet again; and then——"</s>
    <s id="1:385">Renzo gave him a bright new berlinga and warmly recommended reticence in regard to the friar's commission.</s>
    <s id="1:386">Lucia embraced him once more and said good-bye in heart-broken accents.</s>
    <s id="1:387">The lad bade them all farewell, much moved by the demonstrations, and turned back home.</s>
    <s id="1:388">They continued on their way, communing sadly with their thoughts, the women going on before and Renzo following behind like a bodyguard.</s>
    <s id="1:389">Lucia clung close to her mother and gently but adroitly eluded the arm which the youth proffered her over the rougher parts of their cross-country progress, her modesty beginning to be alarmed, even in the perturbed state of her thoughts, at having been alone with him so long and on such familiar terms in the expectation of shortly becoming his wife.</s>
    <s id="1:390">Now that that dream had been so cruelly dissipated, she repented of the lengths to which she had gone, and amid so many other causes for trembling, she trembled also with shame——a shame that arises not from the melancholy knowledge of evil, but springs it knows not whence, like the fears of a child who trembles in the dark without knowing why.</s>
    <s id="1:391">"And what of the house?" of a sudden asked Agnese.</s>
    <s id="1:392">No one replied, important though the question was, because no one could think of a satisfactory reply to make.</s>
    <s id="1:393">They continued silently upon their way and in a little while came out upon the square that lay in front of the monastery-church.</s>
    <s id="1:394">Renzo mounted the steps and pushed gently against the door.</s>
    <s id="1:395">It yielded, and the moonlight streamed in upon the pallid countenance and silvery beard of Father Cristoforo, who was standing there waiting.</s>
    <s id="1:396">Upon seeing that no one was missing, "God be praised!" he said, and made them a sign to enter.</s>
    <s id="1:397">At his side stood a second Capuchin, the lay brother-sacristan, whom he had prevailed upon by dint of entreaty and argument to leave the door ajar and stand watch to receive the poor refugees; and it had called for all of the friar's ascendancy of character and fame of sanctity to obtain from the brother a compliance at once so irksome, so risky and so irregular.</s>
    <s id="1:398">Once they were inside and Father Cristoforo had softly closed the door behind them, the sacristan could stand it no longer.</s>
    <s id="1:399">Calling the old priest to one side, he poured a stream of whispered remonstrances into his ear, shaking his head the while: "But father, father.</s>
    <s id="1:400">At night——in the church——with women——and the doors closed—— </s>
    <s id="1:401">But, father! our rule——" </s>
    <s id="1:402">"See now," thought Father Cristoforo as the other was stammering out these objections, "if it were some roisterer making good his escape, Fra Fazio would find no difficulty in the world; and the sight of innocence fleeing from the fangs of the wolf does not——" </s>
    <s id="1:403">"Omnia munda mundis," he then said, turning suddenly to Fra Fazio and forgetting that the latter did not understand Latin.</s>
    <s id="1:404">But this oversight was precisely what gave effect to his words.</s>
    <s id="1:405">If the father had tried to gain his point by arguing, Fra Fazio would have been sure to oppose reason to reason, and Heaven knows when and how the matter would have ended.</s>
    <s id="1:406">But at the sound of words fraught with such mysterious significance and uttered in a tone of such authority, he acquiesced, deeming that they must contain the solution of all his doubts.</s>
    <s id="1:407">"'Tis well," he said; "thou knowest better than I."</s>
    <s id="1:408">"Let your heart be at rest," replied Father Cristoforo, and made towards the refugees by the uncertain glimmer of the sanctuary lamp.</s>
    <s id="1:409">"Thank God, my children," he said to them, who had remained waiting in suspense all this time, "for having delivered you from grave danger.</s>
    <s id="1:410">Belike at this very instant——"</s>
    <s id="1:411">And here he proceeded to explain that which he had only intimated by the little messenger, for he suspected not that they knew more than he of the story he had to tell them, presuming that Menico had found them quietly at home before the marauders had appeared.</s>
    <s id="1:412">No one disabused him, not even Lucia, who nevertheless felt a secret remorse for such duplicity with a man like Padre Cristoforo.</s>
    <s id="1:413">But it was a night of confusion and subterfuge.</s>
    <s id="1:414">"After what hath happened," he continued, "you see plainly that the village is no longer safe for you.</s>
    <s id="1:415">It is your home and the place of your birth; you have done no man harm; still God wills it so.</s>
    <s id="1:416">It is a trial, my children.</s>
    <s id="1:417">Bear it with patience, with trustfulness, with forbearance, and rest assured that the time will come when your hearts will be glad of what now betides.</s>
    <s id="1:418">I have taken thought for your shelter during these first days, and soon, I hope, you can return in safety to your homes.</s>
    <s id="1:419">At all events God will manage all for your behoof, and I, on my part, shall endeavor not to be found wanting to the grace He hath shown me in selecting me for His agent to minister to your needs in tribulation.</s>
    <s id="1:420">You," he went on, addressing himself to the women, "can bide at ————.</s>
    <s id="1:421">There you will be far enough from danger and at the same time not too far from home.</s>
    <s id="1:422">Look for our monastery, call the father-guardian and give him this letter.</s>
    <s id="1:423">He will be another Padre Cristoforo to you.</s>
    <s id="1:424">And thou, too, my dear Renzo, must for the present seek a place where thou wilt be safe from the rage of others as well as from thy own. </s>
    <s id="1:425">Bear this letter to Father Bonaventura of Lodi at  our monastery hard by the East Gate of Milan.</s>
    <s id="1:426">He will be to thee at once a father and guide, and will find thee some employment against the time when thou canst return here and live in peace.</s>
    <s id="1:427">Go now, and on the lake shore, nigh the mouth of the Bioni" (a mountain stream some few paces from Pescarenico) "ye shall see a bark standing.</s>
    <s id="1:428">Call out: 'A boat!' 'For whom?' ye shall be asked.</s>
    <s id="1:429">Reply, 'Saint Francis.'</s>
    <s id="1:430">The bark will take you aboard and carry you across to the other shore, where you will find a conveyance to take you straight to ————"</s>
    <s id="1:431">If any one ask how Father Cristoforo had such prompt means of transportation by land and water at his disposal, he will show how little he knows of the power of a Capuchin with a reputation for sanctity.</s>
    <s id="1:432">The houses still remained to be thought of.</s>
    <s id="1:433">Father Cristoforo took over the keys, engaging to consign them to the persons whom Renzo and Agnese designated.</s>
    <s id="1:434">The latter heaved a great sigh as she drew hers from her pocket, reflecting that the house even then stood open and that it was a question, after the invasion it had suffered, if there was aught left to guard.</s>
    <s id="1:435">"Ere you depart," said the monk, "let us pray God all together to be with you in this journey and always, and above all, for the gift of His strength and His grace to will what He hath willed."</s>
    <s id="1:436">So saying, he knelt down in the middle of the church, as likewise did the others.</s>
    <s id="1:437">After some moments of silent prayer the priest, in subdued but clear-sounding accents, uttered the following words: "We pray likewise for the poor unfortunate who hath reduced us to such a plight.</s>
    <s id="1:438">We would be unworthy of Thy mercy, did we not ask it also for him, who hath so much need of it, from our hearts.</s>
    <s id="1:439">We have this solace in our tribulation, that our feet are treading the path of Thy appointment.</s>
    <s id="1:440">We can offer Thee our crosses and count them again.</s>
    <s id="1:441">But he—— he is Thy enemy, miserable man——he would strive against Thee.</s>
    <s id="1:442">Have pity on him, O Lord; touch his heart, receive him back into Thy friendship and grant him all the blessings that we could wish for ourselves." </s>
    <s id="1:443">Then, arising with a hurried movement, he said: "Come, my children, there is no time to lose.</s>
    <s id="1:444">May God have you in His keeping and His angel accompany you on your way.</s>
    <s id="1:445">Farewell."</s>
    <s id="1:446">As they were starting off, agitated by emotions that baffle speech but have an eloquence of their own, the friar subjoined in broken tones: "My heart tells me we shall soon meet again."</s>
    <s id="1:447">It is certain that the heart has something to say about what is to be, to him who listens.</s>
    <s id="1:448">But what does it know?</s>
    <s id="1:449">Scarcely a tithe of what has already happened.</s>
    <s id="1:450">Without pausing for a reply Fra Cristoforo turned towards the sacristy.</s>
    <s id="1:451">The travelers went out of the church and Fra Fazio locked the door, after having bid them farewell in a voice that was also broken by feeling.</s>
    <s id="1:452">They then bent their steps in silence towards the beach that had been indicated to them.</s>
    <s id="1:453">They saw the boat waiting, and, after the pass-words had been exchanged, they went aboard.</s>
    <s id="1:454">The boatman punted the bark off into deep water with one oar, then, seizing the other, he rowed with both hands towards the opposite strand.</s>
    <s id="1:455">There was not a breath of wind blowing.</s>
    <s id="1:456">The lake lay shimmering tranquilly under a moon which then hung in the meridian of the heavens and which betrayed by its undulating reflections on the mirror-like expanse of waters the sole indication that they were not absolutely at rest.</s>
    <s id="1:457">The silence was unbroken, save for the lazy, monotonous rippling of the wave along the pebbly shore, farther off the gurgling made by the current as it swirled past the piers of the bridge, and the regular plash of the oars as their blades clove the azure surface of the lake or rose dripping for the coming stroke.</s>
    <s id="1:458">Their ever-lengthening path was marked by a dimpled furrow which streamed from under their keel towards the shore.</s>
    <s id="1:459">The passengers sat silent, with their faces turned back gazing at the mountains and the checkered lights and shadows of the landlandscape.</s>
    <s id="1:460">Hamlets, dwellings and cotes stood out to the view.</s>
    <s id="1:461">Don Rodrigo's castle with its flat donjon towered above the miserable huts clustered about the promontory like some blood-thirsty savage standing in the dark over a band of sleeping men and meditating, as he keeps watch, on the crime he means to perpetrate. </s>
    <s id="1:462">Lucia shuddered as she beheld it.</s>
    <s id="1:463">Then her eye roved down the slope of the mountain until it rested on her native hamlet.</s>
    <s id="1:464">Focussing her glance on the edge of the settlement, she made out her cottage home, the thick foliage of the fig-tree rising over the garden-wall, even the window of her chamber; and, seated as she was on the bottom of the bark, she leaned her arm against the side and, burying her head as if to sleep, wept silent tears.</s>
    <s id="1:465">Farewell! ye mountains rising out of the azure flood beneath into azure skies above.</s>
    <s id="1:466">Farewell! ye rugged peaks, whose image is engraved as clear and deep on the memory of him who was raised among you as that of his own nearest and dearest! ye mountain torrents, who babble to him, each with your own well-known accents; ye scattered hamlets, who loom up like pale flocks of sheep grazing on the moon-lit down; farewell.</s>
    <s id="1:467">How sad the path that leads one away from such scenes of his childhood.</s>
    <s id="1:468">Even when one parts from them voluntarily to seek elsewhere his fortune, he feels his soul disenchanted for the moment of its dreams of wealth.</s>
    <s id="1:469">He wonders how he could ever have committed himself to such a resolution, and he would retrace his steps without delay, did he not hope to return again some day to live in riches.</s>
    <s id="1:470">His eye shrinks back, with each step that he advances into the plain, in weariness and disgust from the unending monotony of the scene, and his lungs seem oppressed by the vapid air.</s>
    <s id="1:471">He advances without interest or pleasure into the city's turmoil, and feels himself cramped by its huddled heaps of houses and its bewildering maze of streets.</s>
    <s id="1:472">He stands before buildings that are the cynosure of foreign eyes, and thinks with impatient longing of the cosy cottage with its modest acre in his native village which he has long marked for his own and which he will buy when he returns wealthy to his mountain home. </s>
    <s id="1:473">But what of one who had never cast one fugitive longing glance beyond its pale, who had centered there all her plans for the future, and who is then whisked far away by a perverse fortune! </s>
    <s id="1:474">What of one who leaves these mountains, with the dearest of ties sundered and the fondest hopes shattered, to seek out strangers she has no wish to know, and who cannot even conjecture when she will come back! </s>
    <s id="1:475">Farewell, native cottage, where secret dreams took shape as she sat listening with mysterious apprehension for one step that she learned to  distinguish from all others.</s>
    <s id="1:476">Farewell, yet unvisited roof-tree, the object of so many stolen glances in passing and the occasion of as many maidenly blushes, where fancy had painted a quiet, perennial life of conjugal bliss.</s>
    <s id="1:477">Farewell, beloved church, where the soul so often forgot its troubles in singing the praises of the Lord; where she owned the promise of a rite that had already been prepared; where the secret longings of the heart were to meet a solemn benediction and love would become a commandment and deserve the name of holy; farewell.</s>
    <s id="1:478">He Who is the Author your delights is everywhere, and He does not mar the joy of His children except to prepare them for bliss that is greater and surer.</s>
    <s id="1:479">Of such a character, if not precisely such, were the thoughts of Lucia, and with but slight variations, the thoughts of the other two pilgrims, as the bark sped on towards the right bank of the Adda.</s>
  </p>
</text>
