<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">CARNEADES! </s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Now who was he?-</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">Don Abbondio was pondering to himself as he sat in his big arm-chair in an upstairs room, with a little book open in front of him, when Perpetua came in to give him the message.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">-Carneades!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">I seem to've read or heard that name somewhere; he must be some scholar or man of letters of antiquity; it's one of those names; but who the devil was he?-</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">So far was the poor man from foreseeing the storm about to burst over his head!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">Don Abbondio, it should be known, enjoyed doing a little reading every day; and the priest of a nearby parish, who had a small library, used to lend him one book after the other-the first that came to hand.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">The one over which Don Abbondio was then poring (he was now convalescent from his fever and fears, in fact more recovered, as far as the fever was concerned, than he wanted people to think) was a panegyric in honour of San Carlo, which two years earlier, in Milan Cathedral, had been delivered with as much emphasis as it had been heard with admiration.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">In it the saint was compared to Archimedes for his love of study; and thus far Don Abbondio had not found himself in any difficulties, as Archimedes did so many strange things, and got himself so talked about, that no very vast erudition was required to know something about him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">But after Archimedes the orator had compared him to Carneades; and here the reader had got stuck.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">It was at this moment that Perpetua came in to announce Tonio's visit.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">'What, at this time of night?' said Don Abbondio also, naturally enough.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">'What's one to expect?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">They've got no consideration; but if you don't catch him on the wing...'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">'Quite; if I don't catch him now, who knows when I will catch him!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">Let him in....</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">Hey! hey!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">You're quite sure it's really him?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">'Of course,' replied Perpetua, and went down, opened the door and said: 'Where are you?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">Tonio came forward, and at the same moment Agnese appeared and greeted Perpetua by name.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">'Good evening, Agnese,' said Perpetua. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">'Where've you come from at this hour?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">'I've come from ***,' and she named a nearby village. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">'As a matter of fact,' she went on, 'I was kept there late all on your account.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">'Oh, why?' asked Perpetua; and, turning to the two brothers, 'Go in,' she said.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">'I'm coming, too.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">'Because,' answered Agnese, 'one of those women who likes a gossip and doesn't know things kept on saying-would you believe it?-that the reason you never married Beppe Suolavecchia or Anselmo Lunghighna was because they wouldn't have you.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">I maintained that it was you who'd refused them, both of them....'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="29">
    <s id="29:1">'Of course.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="30">
    <s id="30:1">The liar!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="31">
    <s id="31:1">The big liar!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="32">
    <s id="32:1">Who is she?' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="33">
    <s id="33:1">'Don't ask me that; I don't want to make mischief.' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="34">
    <s id="34:1">'You shall tell me; you must tell me.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="35">
    <s id="35:1">Oh, the liar!' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="36">
    <s id="36:1">'Anyway... but you can't think how sorry I was not to know the whole story, so's to put her in her place.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="37">
    <s id="37:1">'The things people make up!' exclaimed Perpetua again, then went on quickly: 'As for Beppe, everyone knows, and could see ...</s>
  </p>
  <p id="38">
    <s id="38:1">Hey, Tonio!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="39">
    <s id="39:1">Leave the door to, and go on up; I'm just coming.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="40">
    <s id="40:1">A track opened out between two shacks opposite Don Abbondio's door, and turned past them into the fields.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="41">
    <s id="41:1">Agnese went towards this as if she wanted to get somewhere apart, so as to talk more freely; and Perpetua followed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="42">
    <s id="42:1">When they had turned a corner and got to a spot from which it was impossible to see what happened in front of Don Abbondio's house, Agnese gave a loud cough.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="43">
    <s id="43:1">This was the signal.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="44">
    <s id="44:1">Renzo heard it, and gave Lucia an encouraging squeeze of the arm; and then they both went forward very quietly on tiptoe, creeping along close to the wall; they reached the door, gave it a gentle push, and went into the passage, where the two brothers were waiting for them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="45">
    <s id="45:1">Renzo quietly closed the door again; and all four went up the stairs, without making as much noise even as a single person.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="46">
    <s id="46:1">On reaching the landing, the two brothers went to the door of the room, which was by the stairs, while bride and bridegroom flattened themselves against the wall. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="47">
    <s id="47:1">'Deo gratias,' said Tonio, in a clear voice.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="48">
    <s id="48:1">'Tonio, eh?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="49">
    <s id="49:1">Come on in,' answered the voice from inside.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="50">
    <s id="50:1">Thus called, Tonio opened the door just wide enough to let him and his brother through one at a time.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="51">
    <s id="51:1">The ray of light suddenly coming through this opening and spreading over the dark floor of the landing made Lucia start as if she had been discovered.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="52">
    <s id="52:1">The two brothers went in, and Tonio drew the door to behind him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="53">
    <s id="53:1">The bride and groom stood motionless in the darkness, with ears straining, holding their breath; the loudest noise was the hammering of Lucia's poor heart.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="54">
    <s id="54:1">Don Abbondio was sitting, as we have said, in an old arm-chair, wrapped in an old dressing-gown, with an old night-cap on his head which framed his face, in the dim light of a little lamp.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="55">
    <s id="55:1">The two thick curls of hair escaping from his night-cap, the two thick eyebrows, the two thick mustachios, and a thick beard, grizzled and scattered all over his lined, brown face, looked very much like clumps of bushes covered with snow, jutting from a rock in moonlight.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="56">
    <s id="56:1">'Ah! ah!' was his greeting, as he took off his spectacles and them on to his book.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="57">
    <s id="57:1">'Your reverence'll be saying we've come late,' said Tonio, bowing, as also did Gervaso, rather more awkwardly.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="58">
    <s id="58:1">'Of course it's late; late in every way.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="59">
    <s id="59:1">D'you realize I'm ill?' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="60">
    <s id="60:1">'Oh, I'm sorry.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="61">
    <s id="61:1">'You must have heard; I'm ill, and don't know when I can appear in public....</s>
  </p>
  <p id="62">
    <s id="62:1">But why have you brought this... this lad along with you?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="63">
    <s id="63:1">'Just for company, your reverence.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="64">
    <s id="64:1">'All right; now, let's see....'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="65">
    <s id="65:1">'They're twenty-five new berlinghe, the ones with St Ambrose on horseback,' said Tonio, drawing a little parcel from his pocket.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="66">
    <s id="66:1">'Let's have a look at them,' replied Don Abbondio; and, taking the packet, he put on his spectacles again, opened it, took out the coins, counted them, turned them over, turned them over again, and found no flaws in them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="67">
    <s id="67:1">'Now, father, you can give me back my Tecla's necklace.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="68">
    <s id="68:1">'Fair enough,' replied Don Abbondio; then he went to a cupboard, took a key from his pocket, and, looking around as if to keep spectators at a distance, partly opened the cupboard, filled the aperture with his person, put his head inside to see and an arm to take the necklace, found it, and, closing the cupboard door, handed it over to Tonio, saying: 'Is that all right?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="69">
    <s id="69:1">'Now,' said Tonio, 'perhaps you wouldn't mind putting something in black and white.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="70">
    <s id="70:1">'D'you want that, too!' said Don Abbondio.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="71">
    <s id="71:1">'Everyone's so wise to these things nowadays.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="72">
    <s id="72:1">Eh!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="73">
    <s id="73:1">How suspicious the world's become!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="74">
    <s id="74:1">Don't you trust me?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="75">
    <s id="75:1">'What, not trust your reverence!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="76">
    <s id="76:1">You wrong me. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="77">
    <s id="77:1">But as my name's down in that book of yours on the debit side... so, as you've given yourself the trouble of writing it out once, well... from life to death...'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="78">
    <s id="78:1">'All right, all right,' interrupted Don Abbondio, and with many a grumble drew a box on the table towards him, took out pen, ink, and paper, and began to write, repeating the words out loud as they came off his pen.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="79">
    <s id="79:1">Meanwhile Tonio and, at a sign from him, Gervaso had taken their stand right in front of the table, so as to prevent the writer from seeing the door, and begun scraping their feet on the floor out of apparent idleness, as a signal for the couple outside to come in, and at the same time as a cover for the sound of their footsteps.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="80">
    <s id="80:1">Don Abbondio, deep in his writing, was not attending to anything.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="81">
    <s id="81:1">At the sound of the scraping feet Renzo took Lucia's arm, gave it another encouraging squeeze, and moved forward, drawing with him the trembling girl, who could never have moved on her own.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="82">
    <s id="82:1">They came tiptoeing in very quietly, holding their breath, and hid behind the two brothers.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="83">
    <s id="83:1">Meanwhile Don Abbondio had finished what he was writing and was carefully re-reading it without raising his eyes from the paper; then he folded it in four, and said: 'Are you satisfied now?' took his spectacles off his nose with one hand, held the paper up to Tonio with the other, and looked up.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="84">
    <s id="84:1">Tonio, holding out a hand to take the paper, stepped back to one side; Gervaso, at a sign from him, stepped back on the other; and between them, as at a curtain opening at a play, appeared Renzo and Lucia.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="85">
    <s id="85:1">Don Abbondio saw them vaguely, then saw them clearly, was first alarmed, then amazed, then enraged, collected his wits, and made a decision-all this in the time it took Renzo to utter the words, 'Your reverence, in the presence of these witnesses, this is my wife.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="86">
    <s id="86:1">His lips had hardly closed before Don Abbondio had dropped the paper, seized and lifted the lamp with his left hand, snatched the table-cover with his right, and pulled it hard towards him, flinging book, papers, ink-pot, and sand-box on to the floor; then, springing between the table and the arm-chair, he made for Lucia.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="87">
    <s id="87:1">The poor girl had scarcely been able, in that soft and now trembling voice of hers, to bring out, 'And this . . .' when Don Abbondio rudely flung the table-cover over her head and face to stop her saying the complete formula.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="88">
    <s id="88:1">Then, quickly dropping the lamp, which he held in his other hand, he used that, too, to wrap her up in the table-cloth, so that she was almost suffocated; mean- while he was shouting at the top of his voice, 'Perpetua! Perpetua!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="89">
    <s id="89:1">Treachery!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="90">
    <s id="90:1">Help!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="91">
    <s id="91:1">The wick dying on the floor threw a dim flickering light over Lucia, who, completely dazed, was not even making any effort to disentangle herself, and looked like a clay-model over which the sculptor has thrown a damp cloth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="92">
    <s id="92:1">When the last glimmer of light had gone, Don Abbondio let the poor girl go, and began feeling his way towards the door of an inner room; he found it, went through, and locked himself in, still shouting, 'Perpetua!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="93">
    <s id="93:1">Treachery!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="94">
    <s id="94:1">Help!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="95">
    <s id="95:1">Out of this house!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="96">
    <s id="96:1">Out of this house!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="97">
    <s id="97:1">In the first room all was confusion; Renzo, groping about with his hands, trying to stop the priest, as if he was playing at blind-man's bluff, had found the door, and was knocking on it, shouting, 'Open up!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="98">
    <s id="98:1">Open up!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="99">
    <s id="99:1">Don't make such a row!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="100">
    <s id="100:1">Lucia was calling Renzo in a feeble voice, and begging, 'Let's go; let's go!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="101">
    <s id="101:1">For the love of God.' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="102">
    <s id="102:1">Tonio was crawling about on all fours, scouring the floor with his hands, to try and find his receipt.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="103">
    <s id="103:1">Gervaso was screaming and jumping about like one possessed, looking for the door on to the stairs to get out to safety.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="104">
    <s id="104:1">We cannot forbear pausing a moment to make a reflection in the midst of all this uproar.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="105">
    <s id="105:1">Renzo, who had raised all this noise in someone else's house, who had got in by a trick, and was now keeping the master of the house himself besieged in a room, has all the appearance of being the aggressor; and yet, if one thinks it out, he was the injured party.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="106">
    <s id="106:1">Don Abbondio, surprised, terrified, and put to flight while peacefully attending to his own affairs, might seem the victim; and yet, in reality, it was he who was doing the wrong.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="107">
    <s id="107:1">Such is often the way the world goes... I mean, that's the way it went in the seventeenth century.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="108">
    <s id="108:1">The besieged man, seeing the enemy showed no sign of withdrawing, opened a window looking over the church square, and began to shout, 'Help! help!' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="109">
    <s id="109:1">It was a clear, moonlit night; the shadow of the church, and beyond it the long, pointed shadow of the steeple, stood out dark and sharp on the glistening grass of the square; every object could be distinguished almost as clear as day.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="110">
    <s id="110:1">But as far as the eye could reach there was no sign of a living soul.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="111">
    <s id="111:1">Under the wall of the church--the one facing the priest's house--was a little room, a poky hole, where the sacristan slept.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="112">
    <s id="112:1">The latter was suddenly woken by the confused shouting, sat up, sprang hastily out of bed, opened the lattice of his little window, thrust out his head with half-glued eyes, and said, 'What's up?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="113">
    <s id="113:1">'Quick, Ambrogio!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="114">
    <s id="114:1">Help!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="115">
    <s id="115:1">People in the house!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="116">
    <s id="116:1">Don Abbondio called across to him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="117">
    <s id="117:1">'Coming right away,' the man answered, pulled in his head, and shut his lattice.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="118">
    <s id="118:1">Though half asleep and more than half scared, he thought of an expedient on the spur of the moment to give even more help than he was asked, without getting himself involved in the fray, whatever it might be.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="119">
    <s id="119:1">Grabbing the breeches on the bed and tucking them under one arm, as if they were a dress hat, he went jumping down the wooden ladder, and rushed to the belfry, where he seized the rope of the bigger of the two bells and began ringing out an alarm.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="120">
    <s id="120:1">Ton, ton, ton, ton.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="121">
    <s id="121:1">The peasants started up in bed; the youngsters in the hay-lofts pricked up their ears, listened, and jumped to their feet.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="122">
    <s id="122:1">'What is it?' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="123">
    <s id="123:1">'What is it?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="124">
    <s id="124:1">'The alarm bell!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="125">
    <s id="125:1">Fire?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="126">
    <s id="126:1">Thieves?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="127">
    <s id="127:1">Bandits?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="128">
    <s id="128:1">Many of the women advised, begged their husbands not to stir, but to let the others do the running about; some of the men got up and went to the window; the more cowardly went back under the bed-clothes as if yielding to their wives' entreaties; the braver and the more inquisitive went down to get their pitchforks and muskets, and hurried off towards the noise.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="129">
    <s id="129:1">Others stayed to wait and see.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="130">
    <s id="130:1">But before they were ready, even before they were well awake, the sound had reached the ears of the other persons who, not far away, were already up and dressed: the bravoes in one place, Agnese and Perpetua in another.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="131">
    <s id="131:1">We will first give a brief account of what the former group had been doing from the moment when we left them, part at the ruined house and part at the inn. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="132">
    <s id="132:1">The latter three, when they saw all the doors closed and the road deserted, hurried out as if they had just noticed how late it was, saying that they had to get home at once. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="133">
    <s id="133:1">They made a turn round the village to make sure that everyone had gone indoors, met not a living soul, heard not the slightest noise. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="134">
    <s id="134:1">They also slipped furtively past our poor cottage, which was the quietest of all, as there was no longer anyone in it.</s>
    <s id="134:2">Then they went straight on to the hut and made their report to Griso.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="135">
    <s id="135:1">The latter at once put a wide hat on his head and a palmer's cloak of waxed cloth covered with shells over his shoulders, took a pilgrim's staff, and said, 'Come along, now, be careful; quiet, and mind your orders, then led off first, with the others behind.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="136">
    <s id="136:1">In a moment or two thes were at the cottage, having taken a different path from the one our little group had used when they went off on their own expedition.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="137">
    <s id="137:1">Griso stopped his men a few yards away from it and went ahead alone to reconnoitre; then, seeing everything still and deserted outside, he beckoned two of his ruffians forward, and ordered them to climb carefully over the wall bounding the little yard, and, once inside, hide behind a thick fig-tree that had caught his eye that morning.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="138">
    <s id="138:1">This done, he gives a gentle knock intending to say that he was a pilgrim who had lost his way, and ask for shelter until daybreak. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="139">
    <s id="139:1">There is no reply; he knocks again a little louder; not a sound.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="140">
    <s id="140:1">Then he goes to fetch a third ruffian and gets him to climb into the yard like the other two, to undo the bolt gently, so that they can get in and out easily.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="141">
    <s id="141:1">All this goes off with the utmost caution, and with gratifying success.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="142">
    <s id="142:1">He goes and calls the others, brings them in with him and sends them to hide with the rest; then stealthily closes the gate and posts two sentinels inside; thence he goes to the garden door.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="143">
    <s id="143:1">He knocks at this, too, and waits;-as well he may.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="144">
    <s id="144:1">Very quietly he undoes this bolt too; no one calls.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="145">
    <s id="145:1">'Who's there?' from inside; there is no one to be heard; things couldn't be going better.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="146">
    <s id="146:1">Forward, then: 'Sst,' he calls to those under the fig-tree, and with them enters the ground-floor room, where, the same morning, he had so treacherously begged that piece of bread.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="147">
    <s id="147:1">He pulls out steel, flint, tinder, and sulphur, lights his lantern, and goes into the inner room to see if there is anyone there: no one.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="148">
    <s id="148:1">He turns back, goes to the bottom of the stairs, looks, listens: all is solitude and silence.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="149">
    <s id="149:1">He leaves two other sentinels on the ground floor, and takes with him a bravo from Bergamo called Scratchihead, who is to do all the threatening, coaxing, and giving of orders-all the talking, in fact, so that his dialect may make Agnese believe that the expedition has come from those parts.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="150">
    <s id="150:1">With this man beside him, and the others behind, Griso goes stealthily up the stairs cursing in his heart every creaking stair and every noisy step which his rascals make.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="151">
    <s id="151:1">Finally the top is reached.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="152">
    <s id="152:1">Here's where the rabbit is.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="153">
    <s id="153:1">Gently he tries the door leading into the first room; it gives, and opens a crack; he looks through it: all is dark; he puts his ear against it, to listen for anyone snoring, breathing, or moving inside; nothing.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="154">
    <s id="154:1">Forward, then.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="155">
    <s id="155:1">Holding the lantern before his face, so as to see without being seen, he flings the door wide, sees a bed, and rushes towards it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="156">
    <s id="156:1">It is smooth and made up, with the coverlet turned neatly down over the pillow.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="157">
    <s id="157:1">With a shrug of the shoulders, he turns to his companions and signs to them that he is going to look in the next room, and that they are to come quietly in behind him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="158">
    <s id="158:1">He enters it, goes through the same routine, and finds the same thing.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="159">
    <s id="159:1">'What the devil's this mean?' he says then; 'has some swine of a traitor been spying on us?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="160">
    <s id="160:1">Then they all begin looking about much less cautiously, poking into every corner, and turning the place upside down.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="161">
    <s id="161:1">While that part of the band are busy doing this, the two keeping guard at the street door hear a patter of little footsteps hurrying towards them; then, thinking that whoever it is will pass straight by, they keep quite still and on the alert, just in case.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="162">
    <s id="162:1">In fact, the clatter stops right at the door.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="163">
    <s id="163:1">It was Menico running back with a message from Fra Cristoforo warning the two women to escape from home as soon as possible, for the love of heaven, and take refuge in the monastery, because... the reader knows because of what.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="164">
    <s id="164:1">He takes the bolt-handle to knock with, and feels it dangling loose and undone in his hand.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="165">
    <s id="165:1">-What's this-he thinks, and pushes the door with trepidation; it opens.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="166">
    <s id="166:1">Menico sets a foot inside, in deep suspicion, and suddenly finds himself seized by both arms, with two low voices, to left and right of him, saying menacingly, 'Quiet! or you're a dead 'un.' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="167">
    <s id="167:1">Instead of which he lets out a yell.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="168">
    <s id="168:1">One of the ruffians claps a hand over his mouth; the other pulls out a great knife to frighten him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="169">
    <s id="169:1">The poor boy trembles like a leaf, and does not try to cry out again.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="170">
    <s id="170:1">But all of a sudden there is heard a very different sound to his voice, as that first clap of the church bell booms out, followed by a whole storm of peals in succession.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="171">
    <s id="171:1">There's nothing so suspicious as the guilty, says a Milanese proverb.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="172">
    <s id="172:1">Both those rogues seem to hear their Christian name, surname, and nickname being spelt out in those sounds.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="173">
    <s id="173:1">They let go of Menico's arms, hastily pull theirs back, look at each other with open hands and gaping mouths, and rush into the house to the main body.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="174">
    <s id="174:1">Off runs Menico down the road as fast as his legs can take him towards the belfry, where there is bound to be someone.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="175">
    <s id="175:1">The terrible peals have the same effect on the other rascals ransacking the house from top to toe.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="176">
    <s id="176:1">They jostle against each other in panic-stricken disorder, each looking for the quickest way out.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="177">
    <s id="177:1">Tried men as they all are, and used to risking their necks, they cannot stand up to an indefinite danger, which they had not spied some way off before it came down on them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="178">
    <s id="178:1">It needs all Griso's authority to keep them together, to save their retreat from becoming a flight.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="179">
    <s id="179:1">As a dog shepherding a herd of swine rushes about here and there after the strays, taking one by the ears and dragging it back into the herd, nosing in another, and barking at a third which is simultaneously getting out of line, so the pilgrim seizes and pulls in one man who is already on the threshold, shoves back with his staff one or two others making off in the same direction, and shouts at others who were rushing about without knowing where they were going; until he finally succeeded in collecting them all together in the middle of the yard.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="180">
    <s id="180:1">'Quick! quick!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="181">
    <s id="181:1">Pistols in your hands, daggers at the ready, all together; and then we'll be off; that's the way to go.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="182">
    <s id="182:1">D'you think anyone'll dare touch us if we all keep together, yer fools?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="183">
    <s id="183:1">But if we let ourselves be set on one by one, even the villagers'll have a go at us.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="184">
    <s id="184:1">Shame on you!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="185">
    <s id="185:1">Follow me, and keep together.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="186">
    <s id="186:1">After which brief harangue he put himself at their head, and led the way out.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="187">
    <s id="187:1">The cottage was at the end of the village, as we have said; Griso took the road leading away from it, and the others all followed behind him in good order.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="188">
    <s id="188:1">Leaving them on their way, let us go back a step to Agnese and Perpetua, whom we have left in that little lane.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="189">
    <s id="189:1">Agnese had been trying to get the other as far from Don Abbondio's house as possible; and it had all gone well up to a certain point.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="190">
    <s id="190:1">But suddenly the serving-woman had remembered the door which she had left open, and wanted to turn back.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="191">
    <s id="191:1">There was nothing to be done; Agnese had to turn back with her so as not to arouse her suspicions, and follow behind her; still trying to detain her, however, every time she saw that she was getting really warmed up on the subject of one of those abortive marriages of hers.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="192">
    <s id="192:1">She pretended to be paying close attention, and every now and again, to show that she was listening, and to keep the flow going, would say, 'Why, now I understand; that's all right; it's quite clear now: and what happened next?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="193">
    <s id="193:1">And what about him?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="194">
    <s id="194:1">What about you?' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="195">
    <s id="195:1">But meanwhile she was carrying on another conversation with herself. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="196">
    <s id="196:1">-Will they be out by now?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="197">
    <s id="197:1">Or will they still be inside?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="198">
    <s id="198:1">What fools all three of us were not to have arranged some signal, so's I could know when it's over.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="199">
    <s id="199:1">A really silly mistake!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="200">
    <s id="200:1">But it can't be helped; the only thing to do is to keep this woman away as long as I can.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="201">
    <s id="201:1">It's only time wasted, at the worst.-</s>
  </p>
  <p id="202">
    <s id="202:1">So, by little spurts and stops, they had got back quite close to the house, which, however, could not be seen because of the bend in the path.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="203">
    <s id="203:1">Perpetua had just reached an important part of her story and allowed herself to be stopped without making any fuss, and indeed without noticing the fact that she had, when, all of a sudden, echoing above through the still air and the deep silence of the night, she heard that first wild cry of Don Abbondio's, 'Help! help!' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="204">
    <s id="204:1">'Mercy!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="205">
    <s id="205:1">What's happened?' cried Perpetua, and tried to run.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="206">
    <s id="206:1">'What's up?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="207">
    <s id="207:1">What's up?' said Agnese, holding her by the skirt.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="208">
    <s id="208:1">'Mercy!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="209">
    <s id="209:1">Didn't you hear?' replied the other, struggling to free herself.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="210">
    <s id="210:1">'What's up?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="211">
    <s id="211:1">What's up?' repeated Agnese, clutching her by an arm.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="212">
    <s id="212:1">'Devil take the woman!' exclaimed Perpetua, pushing her aside to free herself, and began to run.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="213">
    <s id="213:1">Just then, farther away, shriller, sharper, rang out Menico's scream.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="214">
    <s id="214:1">'Mercy!' cried Agnese in her turn; and began running along behind the other.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="215">
    <s id="215:1">They had scarcely got their heels off the ground before out boomed the church bell; one stroke, then two, then three, then many more. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="216">
    <s id="216:1">These would have spurred them on if they had any need of it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="217">
    <s id="217:1">Perpetua arrived a moment before the other.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="218">
    <s id="218:1">As she was about to push open the door, it was flung open from inside, and on the threshold appeared Tonio, Gervaso, Renzo, Lucia, who had just found the stairs and come leaping down them; and, hearing those terrible peals, were rushing to safety.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="219">
    <s id="219:1">'What's up?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="220">
    <s id="220:1">What's up?' Perpetua breathlessly asked the brothers, whose only answer was to shove her aside and rush away.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="221">
    <s id="221:1">'And you two?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="222">
    <s id="222:1">What?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="223">
    <s id="223:1">What're you doing here?' she then asked the other pair, when she had recognized them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="224">
    <s id="224:1">But they also came out without answering her.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="225">
    <s id="225:1">Perpetua in her haste to get off where she was most needed asked no more questions, but quickly entered the passage, and ran, as best she could in the dark, for the stairs.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="226">
    <s id="226:1">The two lovers, still only promised lovers, now came face to face with Agnese, who was just panting up.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="227">
    <s id="227:1">'Ah, there you are!' she gasped out. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="228">
    <s id="228:1">'How did it go?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="229">
    <s id="229:1">What's the bell mean?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="230">
    <s id="230:1">I thought I heard...'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="231">
    <s id="231:1">'Home, home,' said Renzo, 'before people come.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="232">
    <s id="232:1">They were just setting off when Menico came dashing up, recognized them, stopped them, and still trembling all over, said in a hoarse voice: 'Where're you going?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="233">
    <s id="233:1">Back, back!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="234">
    <s id="234:1">This way, to the monastery.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="235">
    <s id="235:1">'Was it you who...' Agnese was beginning.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="236">
    <s id="236:1">'Now what's happened?' asked Renzo.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="237">
    <s id="237:1">Lucia stood trembling in silence, completely overwhelmed. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="238">
    <s id="238:1">'You've got devils in your house,' gasped out Menico.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="239">
    <s id="239:1">'I've seen them myself-they tried to kill me-Fra Cristoforo said so-and that you were to come, too, Renzo, at once-and I saw them myself-what luck I found you all here!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="240">
    <s id="240:1">I'll tell you more about it when we're outside.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="241">
    <s id="241:1">Renzo, who was the most self-possessed of the party, thought that it would be best to make off immediately, one way or another, before people began arriving; and that the safest course was to do what Menico was advising, or rather ordering, with all the energy of one terrified out of his wits.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="242">
    <s id="242:1">Once they were on their way, and out of danger, the boy could be made to give a clearer explanation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="243">
    <s id="243:1">'You walk ahead,' he said to him, and 'Let's go with him,' he told the women.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="244">
    <s id="244:1">They turned and hastened towards the church and across the square, where, providentially, there was no living soul yet, down the lane between the church and Don Abbondio's house, through the first gap which they saw in the hedge, and away across the fields.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="245">
    <s id="245:1">They were about fifty yards from it, when a stream of people began running into the square, swelling in volume every moment.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="246">
    <s id="246:1">They looked into each other's faces; everyone had a question to ask, no one had an answer to give.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="247">
    <s id="247:1">The first arrivals ran to the church door-it was locked.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="248">
    <s id="248:1">Then they ran to the outside of the belfry; one of them put his mouth to a window, or rather a slit, and shouted in, 'What the devil is it?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="249">
    <s id="249:1">On hearing a familiar voice, Ambrogio let go the rope and, assured by the buzz that there was a big crowd, answered, 'Just coming to open up.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="250">
    <s id="250:1">He hastily slipped on the garment which he was carrying under his arm, went inside to the church door and opened it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="251">
    <s id="251:1">'What's all the row about?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="252">
    <s id="252:1">-What is it?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="253">
    <s id="253:1">-Where is it?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="254">
    <s id="254:1">-Who is it?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="255">
    <s id="255:1">'What d'you mean, who is it?' said Ambrogio, holding one of the doors with one hand and with the other grasping the top of the garment which he had hurriedly slipped on.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="256">
    <s id="256:1">'What, don't you know?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="257">
    <s id="257:1">People in the priest's!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="258">
    <s id="258:1">Up, lads, to the rescue!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="259">
    <s id="259:1">They all turned and swarmed below the house, looking up and listening dead silence.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="260">
    <s id="260:1">Others ran round to the door; it was shut, and showed no traces of having been touched.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="261">
    <s id="261:1">They looked up; there was not a window open, not a sound to be heard.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="262">
    <s id="262:1">'Who's inside there?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="263">
    <s id="263:1">-Hey, hey!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="264">
    <s id="264:1">-Y'r reverence!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="265">
    <s id="265:1">Y'r reverence!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="266">
    <s id="266:1">Don Abbondio, who had left the window and shut it as soon as he realized that the invaders had fled, and was at that moment busy rebuking Perpetua for leaving him alone in his ordeal, was forced to come to the window again on hearing himself called by the crowd; and when he saw the amount of help, began regretting having asked for it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="267">
    <s id="267:1">'What's happened?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="268">
    <s id="268:1">-What've they done to you?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="269">
    <s id="269:1">-Who are they?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="270">
    <s id="270:1">-Where are they?' fifty voices were simultaneously shouting at him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="271">
    <s id="271:1">'There's no one here any more-thank you-you can go back home now.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="272">
    <s id="272:1">'But who was it?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="273">
    <s id="273:1">-Where've they gone to?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="274">
    <s id="274:1">-What's happened?'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="275">
    <s id="275:1">'People up to no good, people who go round by night-but they've fled go back home-it's all over-another time, my children-thank you once again for your kindness.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="276">
    <s id="276:1">And so saying he drew his head in again and shut the window.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="277">
    <s id="277:1">At which some of the crowd began to grumble, others to jeer, others to curse; and others were shrugging their shoulders and going off, when suddenly someone arrived so completely breathless that he could only just get his words out.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="278">
    <s id="278:1">This was a man who lived almost opposite our two women, who had gone to his window on hearing the noise, and seen the scattering bravoes as Griso was trying to round them up.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="279">
    <s id="279:1">As soon as he had recovered his breath, he shouted: 'What're you doing here, lads?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="280">
    <s id="280:1">The devils aren't here, they're down the road, at Agnese Mondella's.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="281">
    <s id="281:1">Armed men; they're inside it; they seemed to be murdering a pilgrim; the devil only knows what it's all about!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="282">
    <s id="282:1">'What?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="283">
    <s id="283:1">-What?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="284">
    <s id="284:1">-What?' and tumultuous consultations began.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="285">
    <s id="285:1">'We must go.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="286">
    <s id="286:1">-We must see.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="287">
    <s id="287:1">-How many are there?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="288">
    <s id="288:1">-How many are we?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="289">
    <s id="289:1">Who are they?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="290">
    <s id="290:1">-The beadle!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="291">
    <s id="291:1">The beadle!' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="292">
    <s id="292:1">'Here I am,' answered the parish beadle, from the middle of the crowd; 'here I am.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="293">
    <s id="293:1">But you've got to help me, you've got to do what I say.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="294">
    <s id="294:1">Quick; where's the sacristan?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="295">
    <s id="295:1">To the belfry, to the belfry!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="296">
    <s id="296:1">Quick; one of you run to Lecco for help.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="297">
    <s id="297:1">Now come along, all of you.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="298">
    <s id="298:1">Some pressed forward, some slipped away through the crowd and made off; the confusion was tremendous, when another man arrived who had seen the band beating their hasty retreat, and shouted: 'Hurry, lads; thieves or bandits carrying off a pilgrim.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="299">
    <s id="299:1">They're out of the village already.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="300">
    <s id="300:1">After them!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="301">
    <s id="301:1">After them!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="302">
    <s id="302:1">At this news they all moved off pell-mell down the road, without waiting for their leader's orders.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="303">
    <s id="303:1">Some of those in the vanguard dropped back as the army advanced, let others overtake them, and slipped into the main battle group; those in the rear pushed forward; finally the confused swarm reached the place indicated.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="304">
    <s id="304:1">The traces of the invasion were fresh and obvious: the door hanging open, the bolts undone; but the invaders had disappeared.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="305">
    <s id="305:1">They entered the yard and went up to the garden door; that too was open and unhinged.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="306">
    <s id="306:1">They called: 'Agnese!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="307">
    <s id="307:1">Lucia!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="308">
    <s id="308:1">The pilgrim!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="309">
    <s id="309:1">Where's the pilgrim?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="310">
    <s id="310:1">Stefano must've dreamt that pilgrim.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="311">
    <s id="311:1">-No, no; Carlandrea saw him, too.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="312">
    <s id="312:1">Hey, pilgrim!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="313">
    <s id="313:1">- Agnese!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="314">
    <s id="314:1">Lucia!' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="315">
    <s id="315:1">No answer.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="316">
    <s id="316:1">'They've been kidnapped!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="317">
    <s id="317:1">They've been kidnapped!' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="318">
    <s id="318:1">At which some began shouting that they ought to follow the kidnappers, and that it was a scandal, a disgrace to the village if any rascal could come and kidnap women with impunity, like a kite snatching fledglings from an unguarded nest.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="319">
    <s id="319:1">More tumultuous confabulations followed this; then someone in the crowd (no one ever really knew who it was) started a rumour that Agnese and Lucia had taken refuge in a house.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="320">
    <s id="320:1">The rumour rapidly grew, and was believed; no one said any more about chasing the fugitives; and the crowd dispersed, everyone going back to his own home.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="321">
    <s id="321:1">There was a general buzzing of voices, a tramping and knocking and opening of doors, an appearing and disappearing of lights, an asking of questions by the women at the windows and an answering back from the road.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="322">
    <s id="322:1">When this had become silent and deserted, the discussions continued indoors, until they ended in yawns, only to begin in the morning once again.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="323">
    <s id="323:1">There were no more incidents, however; except that that same morning, when the beadle was standing in his field, with his chin in his hand and an elbow leaning on a spade half-stuck into the ground, with one foot propped on its edge-standing, in fact turning over in his mind the strange happenings of the previous night, and wondering whether his duty should have called him to do more than his caution suggested-he was approached by two burly-looking men with quiffs like those of the early French kings, very like the pair who had accosted Don Abbondio five days before, if indeed they were not the same ones.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="324">
    <s id="324:1">These men warned the beadle even more brusquely to be very careful not to make a report to the mayor about what had happened, not to tell the truth if he was questioned about it, not to talk about it, and not to encourage the villagers to talk about it, if he valued his chances of dying in bed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="325">
    <s id="325:1">Our fugitives walked on in silence at a good pace for some time, each looking round in turn to see if anyone was following them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="326">
    <s id="326:1">They were all overwrought by the stress of the flight, the excitement and suspense through which they had gone, the disappointment of their failure, and a confused apprehension of this new and unknown danger.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="327">
    <s id="327:1">But the continual tolling of those bells, which seemed, as distance weakened and muffled them, to take on something more and more gloomy and sinister, made them feel more overwrought than ever.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="328">
    <s id="328:1">Finally they ceased.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="329">
    <s id="329:1">Then the fugitives, who were just passing through a deserted field, not hearing a sound around them, finally slowed down.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="330">
    <s id="330:1">Agnese was the first to get back her breath and break the silence by asking Renzo how it had gone, and asking Menico what all the row at home had been.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="331">
    <s id="331:1">Renzo briefly told his sad story; and all three then turned to the boy, who passed on the friar's warning in more detail, and described what he himself had seen and the risk he had run, which was only too definite a confirmation of the warning.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="332">
    <s id="332:1">His listeners understood more than Menico could tell them; they shuddered at the discovery, and then suddenly stopped, and with one accord all three of them put out a hand to pat the boy's head and shoulders, as if to thank him tacitly for having been a guardian angel to them, and to show him how sorry they were for the agony which he had endured and the danger which he had run for their sakes; and almost to apologize to him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="333">
    <s id="333:1">'Now go back home, as your family can't be allowed to worry about you any more,' said Agnese to him; and remembering the two parpagliole she had promised him, she took four from her pocket and gave them to him, saying: 'There; pray God we'll meet again soon,' and then Renzo gave him a new berlinga, and made him promise not to say a word about the message which the friar had given him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="334">
    <s id="334:1">Lucia embraced him again and said good-bye in a sad voice.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="335">
    <s id="335:1">The boy, deeply moved, bade all of them a tender farewell and turned back.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="336">
    <s id="336:1">They went on their way again, deep in thought, the women ahead and Renzo behind, acting as guard.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="337">
    <s id="337:1">Lucia clung close to her mother's arm, gently but adroitly avoiding the help which the young man offered her in the difficult parts of that cross-country journey, feeling ashamed, even in this trouble, of having been alone with him so long and on such familiar terms when she had expected to become his wife a few moments afterwards.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="338">
    <s id="338:1">Now that the dream had been so cruelly dispelled she regretted having gone so far, and faced as she was with many reasons for trembling, trembled, too, with that modesty which does not spring from the painful knowledge of evil-that modesty which is ignorant of its own existence, like the fears of a child trembling in the dark without knowing why.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="339">
    <s id="339:1">'And what about the house?' said Agnese suddenly.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="340">
    <s id="340:1">But, important as the question was, no one answered her, because no one could think of a satisfactory answer.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="341">
    <s id="341:1">They continued their way in silence, and shortly afterwards finally came out on the square in front of the monastery church.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="342">
    <s id="342:1">Renzo went up to the door and gave it a strong push.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="343">
    <s id="343:1">It opened at once; and the moon streamed through the aperture upon the pale face and silvery beard of Fra Cristoforo, who had been standing there waiting for them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="344">
    <s id="344:1">'Thanks be to God!' said he when he saw there was no one missing, and beckoned them to enter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="345">
    <s id="345:1">At his side was another Capuchin; this was the sacristan lay-brother, whom by entreaty and argument he had persuaded to wait up with him, to leave the door ajar, and stand watch to welcome the poor refugees; and all the friar's authority and prestige as a saint had been needed to get the lay-brother to do him so irksome, risky, and irregular a favour.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="346">
    <s id="346:1">Once they were inside, Fra Cristoforo softly closed the door again.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="347">
    <s id="347:1">Then the sacristan could contain himself no longer, and calling the friar to one side began muttering in his ear: 'But, father, father!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="348">
    <s id="348:1">At night-in church-with women-shut-the rules-but, father!'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="349">
    <s id="349:1">And he shook his head. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="350">
    <s id="350:1">-Just consider!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="351">
    <s id="351:1">-Fra Cristoforo thought as the lay-brother was stammering out these words-if it was some rascal making his escape, Fra Fazio wouldn't make any difficulties at all; and yet a poor, innocent girl, who's escaping from a wolf's clutches.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="352">
    <s id="352:1">'Omnia munda mundis,' he said then, suddenly turning to Fra Fazio, and forgetting that the latter knew no Latin.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="353">
    <s id="353:1">But it was this very oversight that gave the words the right effect.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="354">
    <s id="354:1">If Fra Cristoforo had begun to argue and produce reasons, Fra Fazio would have been at no loss to find other reasons to oppose against his; and heaven knows how and when it would have ended.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="355">
    <s id="355:1">But at the sound of words so pregnant with mysterious meaning, and uttered with such an air of decision, he felt that they must contain the solution to all his doubts.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="356">
    <s id="356:1">He calmed down, and said: 'Ah, well!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="357">
    <s id="357:1">You know better than I do.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="358">
    <s id="358:1">'You can trust me,' answered Fra Cristoforo; then by the flickering light of the sanctuary lamp in front of the altar he went towards the fugitives as they waited there in suspense, and said to them: 'Give thanks to the Lord, my children, who has delivered you from so great a danger.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="359">
    <s id="359:1">Perhaps at this very moment...!' </s>
  </p>
  <p id="360">
    <s id="360:1">And here he began to explain what he had told the young messenger, little suspecting that they knew more than he did, and presuming that Menico had found them sitting quietly at home before the bravoes had arrived.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="361">
    <s id="361:1">No one disabused him, not even Lucia, who did, however, feel a secret twinge of remorse at deceiving such a man; but it was a night of trickery and subterfuge.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="362">
    <s id="362:1">'After this,' he went on, 'you must realize, my children, that this village isn't safe for you any longer.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="363">
    <s id="363:1">It's your village; you were born in it, you have done no one any harm; but such is God's will.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="364">
    <s id="364:1">It is a trial, my children; bear it with patience and faith and without rancour, and you can be quite sure that the day will come when you will find that you are glad of what is happening now. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="365">
    <s id="365:1">I have thought of a refuge for you for the present.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="366">
    <s id="366:1">Soon, I hope, you will be able to go safely back home; in any case, the Lord will do what is best for you; and I will certainly do my utmost not to fail in the trust He has put in me by choosing me as His instrument in the service of you His poor, afflicted creatures!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="367">
    <s id="367:1">You,' he went on, turning to the two women, can stay at ***.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="368">
    <s id="368:1">You will be far enough away from any danger there, and at the same time not too far from your own home.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="369">
    <s id="369:1">Go to our monastery, ask for the Father Superior, and give him this letter; he'll be another Fra Cristoforo to you.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="370">
    <s id="370:1">And you, too, Renzo, my boy-you, too, must find a place where you're safe from the fury of others and from your own.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="371">
    <s id="371:1">Take this letter to Fra Bonaventura of Lodi, of our monastery at the Porta Orientale in Milan.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="372">
    <s id="372:1">He will be a father to you, he will advise you and find you work, until you can come back and live here in peace.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="373">
    <s id="373:1">Now go down to the shore of the lake, near the mouth of the Bione' (this is a torrent near Pescaranico); 'there you'll find a boat.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="374">
    <s id="374:1">Call out: "Boat ahoy!" </s>
  </p>
  <p id="375">
    <s id="375:1">"Who for?" you'll be asked.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="376">
    <s id="376:1">Reply, "For Saint Francis." </s>
  </p>
  <p id="377">
    <s id="377:1">The boat will take you aboard and carry you over to the other shore, where you will find a cart that will take you straight to ***.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="378">
    <s id="378:1">Anyone asking how Fra Cristoforo had managed to get such means of transport by sea and land put at his disposal so promptly would show how little he realizes the power which a Capuchin can wield when he has the reputation of a saint.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="379">
    <s id="379:1">There was still the custody of the houses to be thought of.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="380">
    <s id="380:1">The friar took the keys, and arranged to hand them over to whomsoever Renzo and Agnese named.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="381">
    <s id="381:1">The latter heaved a great sigh as she took the key out of her pocket, reflecting that her home was open at that very moment, that it had been broken into, and who knew what there was still left to take care of.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="382">
    <s id="382:1">'Before you leave,' said the friar, 'let us all pray to the Lord that He may be with you in this journey and for ever; and, above all, that He may give you strength and love, so that you yourselves may desire what He has desired for you.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="383">
    <s id="383:1">So saying, he knelt down in the middle of the church, and all knelt with him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="384">
    <s id="384:1">After praying for some minutes in silence, the friar uttered these words in a low but clear voice: 'We pray to Thee also for the poor wretch who has brought us to this pass. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="385">
    <s id="385:1">We should be unworthy of Thy mercy if we did not implore it for him from the bottom of our hearts; his need of it is so great!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="386">
    <s id="386:1">We, in our tribulations, have the solace of being on the road on which Thou hast set us; we can offer up our troubles to Thee.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="387">
    <s id="387:1">But he!... he is Thine enemy.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="388">
    <s id="388:1">Oh, wretch that he is!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="389">
    <s id="389:1">He struggles against Thee!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="390">
    <s id="390:1">Take pity on him, O Lord; touch his heart, reconcile him to Thee, grant him all the blessings we could wish for ourselves.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="391">
    <s id="391:1">Then he arose, as if in haste, and said: 'Come, my children; there's no time to lose.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="392">
    <s id="392:1">May God guard you and His angel accompany you; go.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="393">
    <s id="393:1">And, as they were setting off, filled with that emotion which has no words to express it and shows itself without them, the friar added in a deeply moved tone: 'My heart tells me we shall meet again soon.'</s>
  </p>
  <p id="394">
    <s id="394:1">Certainly the heart has always something to tell about the future to those who listen to it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="395">
    <s id="395:1">But what does the heart know?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="396">
    <s id="396:1">Scarce a little of what has already happened.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="397">
    <s id="397:1">Without waiting for a reply, Fra Cristoforo went towards the sacristy; the travellers left the church; and Fra Fazio shut the door, after saying good-bye in a voice that was also deeply moved.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="398">
    <s id="398:1">Very quietly they made their way to the spot on the lakeside to which they had been directed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="399">
    <s id="399:1">They found the boat ready, exchanged the password, and went aboard.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="400">
    <s id="400:1">The boatman punted the boat away from the bank with one oar, then took up the other opposite shore.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="401">
    <s id="401:1">There was not a breath of wind; the lake lay flat and smooth, and would have seemed quite motionless but for the gentle, tremulous swaying of the moon, reflected from high up in the sky.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="402">
    <s id="402:1">The only sounds were the slow, sluggish lapping of the waves on the pebbly shore, farther away the gurgle of water swishing around the piles of the bridge, and then the measured splash of those two oars as they cut the blue surface of the lake, suddenly came out dripping, and then plunged in once again.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="403">
    <s id="403:1">The wash of the boat, joining up behind the stern, left a rippling furrow which drew farther and farther away from the shore.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="404">
    <s id="404:1">The passengers sat silent, with their heads turned back, gazing at the mountains, and at the moonlit countryside, dappled here and there by great shadows.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="405">
    <s id="405:1">The villages and houses, even the sheds, could be made out; Don Rodrigo's mansion, with its squat tower, rising above the cottages huddled at the foot of the headland, seemed like a wild beast standing there in the dark amidst a group of sleepers, waiting and meditating some evil deed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="406">
    <s id="406:1">Lucia saw it and shuddered; she followed the slope down with her eye, on down to her own village, gazed fixedly at the end of it, and found her own cottage, found the thick top of the fig-tree rising above the yard wall, found the window of her own room; and as she sat in the bottom of the boat she leant her arm against its side and her head against her arm, as if to sleep, and secretly wept.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="407">
    <s id="407:1">Farewell, mountains springing from the waters and rising to the sky; rugged peaks, familiar to any man who has grown up in your midst, and impressed upon his mind as clearly as the features of his nearest and dearest; torrents whose varying tones he can pick out as easily as the voices of his family; villages scattered white over the slopes, like herds of grazing sheep; farewell!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="408">
    <s id="408:1">How sadly steps he who was reared among you, as he draws away!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="409">
    <s id="409:1">At that moment, in the mind even of him who leaves you of his own accord, lured by the hope of finding fortune elsewhere, the dreams of riches lose their charm; he finds himself wondering how he could ever have resolved to leave you, and would turn back even then, but for the hope of one day returning rich.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="410">
    <s id="410:1">The more he advances into the plain, the more his eye flinches away in weariness and disgust from its vast uniformity; the air seems lifeless and heavy; gloomily and listlessly he enters the bustling cities; the houses heaped on houses, the streets leading to more streets, seem to prevent him breathing there; and as he stands before the buildings which foreigners admire, he thinks with restless longing of a little acre in his own village, of a cottage which he has long marked for his own and will buy when he returns wealthy to his native mountains.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="411">
    <s id="411:1">But what of one who has never even cast a passing wish beyond those mountains, who had set all the plans of her future among them, and is then driven far away from them by a perverse power!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="412">
    <s id="412:1">What of one who, suddenly torn from her dearest habits and thwarted in her dearest hopes, leaves those mountains to go and seek out strangers whom she has never wished to know, and can look forward to no definite time for her return!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="413">
    <s id="413:1">Farewell, home, where, sitting among her secret thoughts, she had learned to pick out from all others the sound of a footstep awaited with a mysterious awe.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="414">
    <s id="414:1">Farewell, house that was still not hers; house at which she had so often glanced hastily in passing, not without a blush; house in which the imagination had pictured a perpetual calm, unending life of married bliss.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="415">
    <s id="415:1">Farewell, church, wherein her soul had so often found serenity in singing the praises of the Lord; where a ritual had already been prepared by a promise; where the secret longing of her heart was to be solemnly blessed, and love ordained and called holy: farewell!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="416">
    <s id="416:1">He who gave you so much happiness is everywhere, and never disturbs the joy of His children, unless to prepare for them one greater and more certain.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="417">
    <s id="417:1">Such-or more or less such-were Lucia's thoughts, and scarcely different were those of the other two pilgrims, as the boat drew nearer the right bank of the Adda.</s>
  </p>
</text>
