<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">CARNEADES!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Who was he?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">Don Abbondio was ruminating with himself in his great arm chair, in a chamber in the upper story, with a small book open before him, when Perpetua entered with the embassy.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Carneades!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">I think I have heard or read of this name; he must have been a man of study, some learned man of the old days; its one of their names; but who the devil was he?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">So far was the poor man from foreseeing what sort of a storm was going to burst over his head!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">The reader must know that Don Abbondio was fond of reading a few lines every day, and a neighboring curate, who had a sort of library, lent him one book after another, the first that came to his hand.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">The book upon which Don Abbondio was meditating at that moment —— being now convalescent of his terror fever, indeed, as far as fever was concerned, more completely cured than he was willing to acknowledge —— was a panegyric in honor of Saint Charles, delivered with great emphasis, and heard with much admiration in the Dome of Milan, two years before.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">The saint was compared, on account of his love of study, to Archimedes, and thus far Don Abbondio, had not been puzzled, because Archimedes has done such great things, and has caused himself to be so much talked of, that without possessing vast erudition, a man may know some little matter about him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">But having done with Archimedes, the orator institutes a comparison with Carneades, and here Don Abbondio was completely run ashore.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Just at this time, Perpetua announced the visit of Tonio.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">“At this hour?” cried he, likewise, as was very natural.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">“What will you do?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">They have no discretion, but if you don't take them when they are flying ————”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">“If I don't catch him, who knows when I shall catch him?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">Let him come ——</s>
    <s id="16:2">Eh! eh! are you quite sure it's him, Tonio?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">“Why, the dickens!” answered Perpetua, and going down stairs, opened the door, saying “where are you?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">Tonio came forward, and then Agnes appeared and saluted Perpetua by name.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">“Good evening, Agnes,” said Perpetua, “where do you come from at this hour?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">“I came from ———” naming a small place in the neighborhood,“ and if you only knew,” she continued, “I staid rather too long only on your own account.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">“Ay, wherefore,” inquired Perpetua; and turning to the two brothers, “enter,” she said, “I'll go with you.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">“Why,” resumed Agnes, “it was because one of those women that know nothing, and still will talk ——— would you believe it? insisted that you was not married to Beppo Suolavecchia, nor to Anselmno Lunghigna, because they would'nt have you.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">I insisted upon it that you had refused them, both one and t'other ———”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">“Certainly.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">Oh the lying slut! the lying minx!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">Who is she!” </s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">“Don't ask me.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">I don't like to brew ill ———”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="29">
    <s id="29:1">“You shall tell ine; I will know it; the impudent lying slut.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="30">
    <s id="30:1">“Enough —— but you cannot believe how vexed I was not to know the whole story just to confound her.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="31">
    <s id="31:1">“She is a good for nothing, infamous lying devil!” said Perpetua.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="32">
    <s id="32:1">“As to Beppo, every body knew and could see —— eh! Tonio, shut the door gently and go up stairs, I'll follow you.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="33">
    <s id="33:1">Tonio answered from within that he would do so, and Perpetua went on with her story in the most impassioned manner.—— </s>
  </p>
  <p id="34">
    <s id="34:1">Fronting the door of Don Abbondio, there was a lane that separated two small houses, and when it had reached their extreme length, turned short round into the fields.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="35">
    <s id="35:1">Agnes went there, as though she wanted to get to a by place to talk more freely, and Perpetua followed her.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="36">
    <s id="36:1">As soon as they had turned the corner, and were in a place whence nothing could be seen which was passing at Don Abbondio's door, Agnes coughed loudly.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="37">
    <s id="37:1">This was the signal, Renzo understood it, pressed the arm of Lucia to encourage her, and both of them on the tips of their toes, turned also their corner, creeping closely to the wall, reached the door, and opened it gently; first one, and then the other silently stooping down, glided into the hall, where the two brothers were waiting for them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="38">
    <s id="38:1">Renzo replaced, without making the slightest noise, the latch of the door, and all four went up the stairs, making not more noise than would be made by two.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="39">
    <s id="39:1">Being arrived upon the landing, the two brothers went to the door of the room which was on the side of the staircase, and the lovers kept close to the wall.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="40">
    <s id="40:1">“Deo gratias,” said Tonio, with a clear voice.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="41">
    <s id="41:1">“Tonio, eh! enter,” answered a voice from within.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="42">
    <s id="42:1">Tonio opened the door just enough to let himself and his brother in, one at a time.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="43">
    <s id="43:1">The ray of light that burst at once through the opening, and fell upon the dark floor of the landing, made Lucia tremble as if she was discovered.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="44">
    <s id="44:1">The brothers having entered, Tonio closed the door behind him, the lovers remaining immoveable in the dark, their ears stretched out, and holding their breath: the loudest noise that was heard was the continual beating of the poor heart of Lucia.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="45">
    <s id="45:1">Don Abbondio, as we have said, was seated in an old arm chair, by the faint light of a small lamp, wrapped up in a worn symar or gown, with the upper part of his head buried in an old cap, in which his face was set as in a frame.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="46">
    <s id="46:1">Two of his grizzly locks had escaped from his cap, and his thick eyebrows, mustachios, and a grey tuft on his chin, were hoarily stuck in his embrowned and wrinkled visage, and somewhat resembled those snowy looking tufts of bushes, which are seen growing on the side of a steep by the pale light of the moon. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="47">
    <s id="47:1">“Ah, ah,” was his salutation, whilst he took off his spectacles and placed them in the leaves of the book.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="48">
    <s id="48:1">“Your worship will say I am come late,” said Tonio, bowing, as did also Gervaso in a clumsy way.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="49">
    <s id="49:1">“Certainly, it is late: late in every sense.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="50">
    <s id="50:1">Do you know that I am sick?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="51">
    <s id="51:1">“I am sorry to hear it.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="52">
    <s id="52:1">“You must have heard that I am sick, and I don't know when I shall be able to go out.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="53">
    <s id="53:1">But why have you brought that —— that —— young fellow —— with you?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="54">
    <s id="54:1">“Only for company, your worship.” </s>
  </p>
  <p id="55">
    <s id="55:1">“Well, well, let us see.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="56">
    <s id="56:1">“Here are five and twenty new pieces, those with Saint Ambrose on horseback,” said Tonio, taking a purse tied in a knot from his pocket.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="57">
    <s id="57:1">“Let us see,” replied Don Abbondio, and taking the purse, he put his spectacles on, untied it, took out the money, turned it, returned it, counted it, and found it all right.” </s>
  </p>
  <p id="58">
    <s id="58:1">“Now, your worship will please to give me the necklace of my Tecla.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="59">
    <s id="59:1">“That is correct,” replied Don Abbondio, and going to a closet took out a key, and looking round as if to see no lookers on were near him, opened another closet, filling the entrance of it with his person, putting his head in to look, and reaching with his arm to take out the pledge.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="60">
    <s id="60:1">Having got it, he locked the door, opened the paper, and saying, “It is all right,” folded it up again, and delivered it to Tonio.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="61">
    <s id="61:1">“Now,” said Tonio, “have ——— the goodness to put a little black upon the white.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="62">
    <s id="62:1">“This, too,” said Don Abbondio, “they understand every thing.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="63">
    <s id="63:1">Eh, how suspicious the world has got to be!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="64">
    <s id="64:1">Don't you trust me?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="65">
    <s id="65:1">“How your worship?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="66">
    <s id="66:1">Don't I trust you?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="67">
    <s id="67:1">You do me injustice.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="68">
    <s id="68:1">But as my name is in the book, on the debtor's side —— as your worship has had the trouble to write once, so life and death are ———”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="69">
    <s id="69:1">“Very well, very well,” interrupted Don Abbondio, and grumbling, he drew towards him a small case that was on the table, took some paper, pen and ink, and began to write, repeating over all the words, as they came from his pen.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="70">
    <s id="70:1">In the meantime, Tonio made a sign to Gervaso, and both of them placed themselves before the table, so as to hide the door from the curate whilst he was writing.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="71">
    <s id="71:1">And as if from pure idleness, they began to scrape and rub the floor with their feet, as a sign to the lovers to enter, and to conceal the noise of their feet when they should enter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="72">
    <s id="72:1">Don Abbondio was so taken up with his writing that he paid no attention to any thing else.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="73">
    <s id="73:1">At the scraping of their feet, Renzo took the arm of Lucia, pressed it to give her courage, and moved, drawing her, all trembling, behind him, and incapable of moving alone.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="74">
    <s id="74:1">Softly they entered the room, on the tips of their feet, keeping in their breath, and placed themselves behind the two brothers.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="75">
    <s id="75:1">In the meantime, Don Abbondio, having finished the receipt, read it over again attentively, without raising his eyes from the paper, and folding it up, said, “Will you be satisfied now?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="76">
    <s id="76:1">And taking his spectacles from his nose with one hand, and reaching out the paper with the other, he lifted up his face.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="77">
    <s id="77:1">Tonio, extending his right hand to take it, drew on one side, and Gervaso at a sign from him drew to another, so that, like the scenes which sometimes occur on the theatre, Renzo and Lucia appeared in the centre.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="78">
    <s id="78:1">Don Abbondio looked, and was astounded; he became aware of the trap he had fallen into, was enraged, but in a moment came to a resolution.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="79">
    <s id="79:1">All this took place whilst Renzo was saying, “Signor curate, this is my wife in the presence of these witnesses.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="80">
    <s id="80:1">His lips were not yet closed, ere Don Abbondio let fall the receipt, laid hold of the lamp with his left hand, lifted it up, seized with his right the cloth that covered the table, and drew it off in a ferocious manner, throwing to the ground, book, paper, inkstand, sandbox and every thing else, and rushing from his chair and the table, got near to Lucia.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="81">
    <s id="81:1">The poor young creature, all trepidation, had scarce with her gentle voice, got out, “And this ——” when Don Abbondio most uncourteously flung the cloth over her head and face, to prevent her from pronouncing the whole formula: then letting the lamp fall from his left hand, he used that also to wrap the cloth so tightly over her face that he almost suffocated her; screaming out in the meantime, like a wounded bull, “Perpetua, Perpetua, treason, help!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="82">
    <s id="82:1">The dying lamp sent from the floor a faint and flickering glare upon Lucia, who altogether terrified, did not even attempt to disengage herself, and who might be thought to resemble a statue modelled from chalk, over which the sculptor had thrown a wet cloth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="83">
    <s id="83:1">The light having expired, Don Abbondio left the poor girl, and groping about for a door that led to another room, found it and fastened himself in, screaming all the time, “Perpetua, treason, help; out of this house, out of this house.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="84">
    <s id="84:1">In the first room every thing was confusion.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="85">
    <s id="85:1">Renzo, groping about with his hands to get hold of the curate, as if he was playing at blindman's buff, reached the door, and thumped at it, calling out, “Open, open, don't make such a screaming.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="86">
    <s id="86:1">Lucia called Renzo with a faint voice, and said in a supplicating manner to him, “Let us go, let us go, for the love of God.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="87">
    <s id="87:1">Tonio, on the floor, all fours, was scraping about, hoping to lay his paws on the receipt, whilst Gervaso, terrified, was jumping about and screaming, seeking for the door that opened upon the landing in order to save himself.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="88">
    <s id="88:1">In the midst of this confusion, we cannot forbear stopping an instant to make a reflection.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="89">
    <s id="89:1">Renzo, whom we find kicking up a prodigious noise, in the night time, in another man's house, into which he had introduced himself in an underhanded way, and who kept the master of the house besieged in a room, has all the appearance of an oppressor; yet at the end of the story he turns out to be the oppressed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="90">
    <s id="90:1">Don Abbondio, surprised, put in flight, terrified, whilst he was occupied with his own affairs, would seem to be a persecuted man, yet in reality it was he who inflicted the injury.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="91">
    <s id="91:1">That is the way things often go in the world —— I mean to say, it is the way they used to go in the seventeenth century.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="92">
    <s id="92:1">The besieged, perceiving that the enemy gave no signs of decamping, opened a window that looked towards the sacristy or vestry room, and began to scream out, “assistance, help, help.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="93">
    <s id="93:1">The moon shone in the most beautiful manner, the shadow of the church, and at a greater distance the long and acute figure of the steeple, was extended, dark, immoveable and distinct, upon the grassy and shining lawn of the sacristy, every object, could be discerned as clear as by daylight.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="94">
    <s id="94:1">But as far as the sight could extend, there was no indication of a living soul.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="95">
    <s id="95:1">Contiguous, however, to the side wall of the church, and exactly on that side which looked towards the parsonage, was a small habitation, a hole of a place where the sacristan slept.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="96">
    <s id="96:1">This man being awakened by this unusual alarm, started in his bed, got up, opened a sort of glazed paper window, put his head out, and with his eye-lids yet glued together, called out, “What's the matter?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="97">
    <s id="97:1">“Run, Ambrosio, help, people in the house,” Don Abbondio, kept screaming towards him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="98">
    <s id="98:1">“I'll come directly,” replied he, drawing in his head and closing the window; and although half asleep, and more than half frightened, he hit upon an expedient, at once to give more help than he was asked for, without running his own head into Don Abbondio's troubles, of whatever nature they might be.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="99">
    <s id="99:1">Seizing his breeches which were upon the bed, and shoving them under his arm like a dress hat, he scrambled quickly down his wooden ladder, ran to the steeple, seized hold of the rope of the largest of two bells hung there, and began to pull away.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="100">
    <s id="100:1">Tong, tong, tong, tong, in an instant all the country people were sitting upright in bed, and all the lads that were stretched out on the hay, hung out their ears and sprung out upon their feet.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="101">
    <s id="101:1">“What's the matter, what's the matter?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="102">
    <s id="102:1">The steeple bell?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="103">
    <s id="103:1">Fire?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="104">
    <s id="104:1">Thieves?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="105">
    <s id="105:1">Banditti ?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="106">
    <s id="106:1">Then some of the women began to pray their husbands not to stir, to let the others go; some get up, and go to the window; the poltroons, as if they had yielded to the entreaties of their wives, crept under the blankets again.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="107">
    <s id="107:1">The bold and the more curious ran for their pitchforks and harquebusses, to go to the parsonage, whilst others merely looked on.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="108">
    <s id="108:1">But before these people had got together, indeed before they were well awake, the noise had reached the ears of others who were watching, not far off, on foot, and in their clothes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="109">
    <s id="109:1">The Bravos in one place, Agnes and Perpetua in another.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="110">
    <s id="110:1">We will tell, first, what was done by those from the moment we left them, partly in the ruined house, and partly at the inn.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="111">
    <s id="111:1">The three, when they perceived all the cottages were closed, and the streets deserted, left the inn, as if they were going a considerable distance, making without any noise, a reconnoissance through the village, to ascertain if every body was retired; and in fact, they did not meet a living soul, or hear the slightest noise.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="112">
    <s id="112:1">They also passed, and still more softly, before our poor cottage, the most noiseless of them all, because there was nobody within.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="113">
    <s id="113:1">From thence they went straight to the ruin, to make their report to Griso.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="114">
    <s id="114:1">Immediately he placed on his head a large old hat, and upon his shoulders a pilgrim's cloak of waxed cloth, sprinkled over with cockle shells, took in his hand a pilgrim's staff, and saying, “Now let us go like brave fellows, silence, and attention to orders,” he moved, and the rest followed him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="115">
    <s id="115:1">In a short time they reached the cottage, by a road opposite to that by which our nuptial party went on their expedition.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="116">
    <s id="116:1">Griso kept his troop a little in the rear, preceding them himself, with a view to explore, and finding the street deserted, and every thing still out of doors, he made two of his ruffians come forward, ordered them to get over the wall quietly which enclosed the court yard, and when within, to conceal themselves in a corner behind a thick fig tree, which he had remarked in the morning.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="117">
    <s id="117:1">Having done this, he tapped gently at the door, intending to say that a pilgrim who had lost his way desired lodgings until morning.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="118">
    <s id="118:1">No one answering, he knocked a little louder, but all was still.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="119">
    <s id="119:1">He then called a third rogue, made him get into the court yard like the others, with directions to draw the nails from the chain that held the bolt within, that they might have free ingress and egress.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="120">
    <s id="120:1">Every thing was executed with great caution, and in the best way.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="121">
    <s id="121:1">Having gone to call the others, he made them enter with him, sent them to post themselves with the first, shut the door gently, placed two sentinels within, and goes straight to the door of the house.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="122">
    <s id="122:1">There, too, he knocked, waited —— he might well wait!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="123">
    <s id="123:1">Having opened this door likewise, still no one within says, who's there?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="124">
    <s id="124:1">No one moves; what a famous chance!</s>
    <s id="124:2">forwards, then.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="125">
    <s id="125:1">“St.” having called the men behind the fig tree, he walked with them into the room on the ground floor, where in the morning he had iniquitously begged their morsel of bread from them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="126">
    <s id="126:1">He now took out tinder, flint, steel and matches, and lit a small lamp he had brought, entered another room inside, to see if there was any one there, and found no one.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="127">
    <s id="127:1">He now went to the foot of the stairs, looked, listened; all was solitude and silence.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="128">
    <s id="128:1">Leaving two other sentinels below, he told Grignapoco to come with him; a Bravo of the Bergamasc country, who was to do all the threatening, the coaxing, the commanding, in fact who was to do all the talking of the party, so that his dialect might induce Agnes to believe the expedition came from those parts.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="129">
    <s id="129:1">With this fellow at his side, and the others behind, Griso mounted the staircase, softly, softly, cursing in his heart every step that made a noise, every tread of the ruffians that broke the silence.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="130">
    <s id="130:1">At length he reached the top.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="131">
    <s id="131:1">Here the hare lies.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="132">
    <s id="132:1">Gently he pushed the door of the first room he met, it opens a little, he looks in, all is dark: he applies his ear to discover if any one snores, breathes, or moves; he hears nothing.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="133">
    <s id="133:1">In he goes; placing the lantern before his face, that he may see without being seen; he opens the door wide, perceives a bed: the bed is made and quite smooth, the linen neatly turned down, and resting on the bolster.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="134">
    <s id="134:1">Shrugging his shoulders, he turns to his troop, and makes a sign to them that he is going to examine the other room, and that they keep behind him without making a noise: he goes there, examines in the same way, and finds exactly the same state of things.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="135">
    <s id="135:1">“What the devil is all this?” said he, then openly,, “has some rascally traitor been betraying us?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="136">
    <s id="136:1">All now, with less caution, began to examine, to fumble in every corner, and ended by turning the house topsy turvy.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="137">
    <s id="137:1">Whilst these matters were going on, the two, who were on guard at the gate of the court yard next the street, hear approaching, from a direction beyond the street, a light foot walking and drawing near; supposing that, whoever it was, they would pass straight on, they remained silent, and kept themselves diligently on the alert.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="138">
    <s id="138:1">The footstep ceased, as soon as it reached the gate.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="139">
    <s id="139:1">It was Menico, who came in haste, sent by father Christopher, to warn the two women for the love of Heaven to escape immediately from the cottage, and take refuge at the convent, because —— we know the because.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="140">
    <s id="140:1">Taking hold of the handle of the bolt to knock, he found it loose in his hand, broken, and the nails drawn.</s>
    <s id="140:2">—— What can this be? thought he, and thrusts the door quite frightened; it opens, he puts a foot cautiously within, and immediately feels himself seized by both arms, and hears two low voices say to him, right and left, “be silent, hold your tongue, or you die.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="141">
    <s id="141:1">He on the contrary screaming out, one of the villains, gave him a great slap on the mouth, whilst the other put his hand to his knife to frighten him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="142">
    <s id="142:1">The boy trembled like a leaf, and gave over screaming; but all at once, in his stead, and in a very different sort of tone, the first twang of the church bell broke out, followed up by that tempest of strokes that pealed upon the night after it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="143">
    <s id="143:1">He who is in the wrong box always knows it, says a Milanese proverb; each of these scoundrels thought he heard the bell repeat his name, his Christian name, and his family name; they let go the arms of Menico, draw back their own in a rage, open their hands and mouths wide open, look in each other's faces, and run to the house, where the major part of the troop was.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="144">
    <s id="144:1">Menico cleared out, and took to his legs in the direction of the steeple, where he had good reasons for supposing he should meet with some body or other.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="145">
    <s id="145:1">Upon the rest of the villains, who were roving about the house from top to bottom, the terrible sound of the church bell made the same impression: they confounded, they embarrassed, they rushed against each other, each one sought the shortest way to reach the door.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="146">
    <s id="146:1">And yet they were all proved men, and habituated to show their faces; still they could not hold up against an undefined danger, and of which they had not had the slightest glimpse before it had so suddenly come upon them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="147">
    <s id="147:1">All the superiority of Griso was necessary to keep them together, and prevent a retreat being turned to a flight.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="148">
    <s id="148:1">As a dog escorting a herd of swine, runs now here, now there, after those that are astray, bites one by the ear, and draws it back into the herd, seizes another by the snout, and barks at a third, that at the same moment is leaving the ranks, so the pilgrim seizes one of thein by the tuft, just as he was reaching the door, and drags him back; drives back with his staff first one and then another, that were near him, cries out to the rest that are running they know not where, so that at last he assembled them all in the centre of the court yard.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="149">
    <s id="149:1">“Halt! halt! pistols in hand, knives ready, all together, and then we go, that's the way.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="150">
    <s id="150:1">Who do you think will touch us, if we all keep together, you wicked devils, you?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="151">
    <s id="151:1">But if we let ourselves be caught one by one, why even these country bumpkins will give it to us.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="152">
    <s id="152:1">For shame! keep behind me, and keep close.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="153">
    <s id="153:1">After this short harangue, he placed himself in front, and went out first.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="154">
    <s id="154:1">The cottage, as we have stated, was at the end of the village, Griso took the road that led away from it, and all kept behind in good order.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="155">
    <s id="155:1">Let us let them go, whilst we turn back a step or two to take up Agnes and Perpetua, whom we have placed there behind a certain corner.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="156">
    <s id="156:1">Agnes had contrived to get her friend as far away from Don Abbondio's as it was possible, and up to a certain point the matter went on pretty well; but all at once, Perpetua recollected that the door was left open, and wanted to go back.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="157">
    <s id="157:1">There was no remedy; and Agnes, that she might create no suspicion, had been obliged to turn about also, and go behind her, endeavoring, nevertheless, to engage her attention, every time her imagination appeared warmed up with the story of the matrimonies of by-gone days.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="158">
    <s id="158:1">She pretended to give her the greatest attention, and from time to time to show her how much interest she felt in the affair, and to encourage this gossiping, said, “Certainly, now I understand, that is quite right, nothing can be clearer, and then? and he? and you?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="159">
    <s id="159:1">During this she held another colloquy with herself.</s>
    <s id="159:2">—— Have they got off by this time? or are they yet in the house?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="160">
    <s id="160:1">What boobies we were all three, not to have concerted some signal for me when the affair had succeeded!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="161">
    <s id="161:1">What a stupid mistake!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="162">
    <s id="162:1">But it is over; now it will be better to keep amusing her as well as I can, at the worst it will be a little time lost.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="163">
    <s id="163:1">Thus, sometimes stopping, sometimes going on, they at last got back not far from Don Abbondio's house, which, however, was not to be seen on account of the corner; and Perpetua, finding herself in a very important part of her narration, permitted herself to be detained without resistance, indeed, without being aware of it; when, suddenly, was heard echoing from above, in the immoveable void of the air, through the vast silence of night, that first enraged scream of Don Abbondio, “help! help!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="164">
    <s id="164:1">“Mercy! what has happened?” cried out Perpetua, and wanted to run.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="165">
    <s id="165:1">“What is it, what is it?” said Agnes, pulling her back by her gown.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="166">
    <s id="166:1">“Misery! hav'nt you heard?” answered she, getting away from her.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="167">
    <s id="167:1">“What is it, what is it,” repeated Agnes, grasping her by the arm.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="168">
    <s id="168:1">“Devil of a woman!” exclaimed Perpetua, flinging her off to get at liberty, and to be able to run.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="169">
    <s id="169:1">Just then, further off, in a finer key, and more instantaneous, the screaming of Menico was heard.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="170">
    <s id="170:1">“Mercy!” cried Agnes also now, and went full gallop after Perpetua.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="171">
    <s id="171:1">Scarce had they lifted their heels, when the church bell began, one, two, three, and kept pealing away: if they had wanted any spurs, these would have been sufficient.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="172">
    <s id="172:1">Perpetua arrived first by two paces; whilst she was reaching out her hand to the door to throw it open, it suddenly opened from within, and behold upon the threshold, Tonio, Gervaso, Renzo and Lucia, who, having found the stairs, had got down them by jumps, and hearing those strokes on the bell, were running off in a fright to put themselves in safety.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="173">
    <s id="173:1">“What is it? what is it?” asked Perpetua, out of breath, of the brothers —— who answered her by running against her, and pushing off “And you! how! what are you doing here?” she asked of the other couple as soon as she knew them; but they, too, went on without answering her.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="174">
    <s id="174:1">Perpetua, hastening where she was most wanted, asked no further; she pushed eagerly into the house, and groped her way to the staircase.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="175">
    <s id="175:1">The two lovers, who remained yet betrothed, found Agnes before them in an agony of vexation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="176">
    <s id="176:1">“Ah, here you are!” said she, bringing the words out with an effort.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="177">
    <s id="177:1">“How did the affair go? what is that bell about?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="178">
    <s id="178:1">I think I heard ———”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="179">
    <s id="179:1">“Let us go home, let us go home,” said Renzo, “before the people come.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="180">
    <s id="180:1">And on they went, when, lo!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="181">
    <s id="181:1">Menico, on the full run, comes up, recognizes them, stands before them, and yet trembling, with a voice half spent, cries out, “Where are you going? back, back —— this way, to the convent.”</s>
    <s id="181:2">“What is it thou that ———”began Agnes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="182">
    <s id="182:1">“What's the matter?” asked Renzo; Lucia, terrified, stood trembling and silent. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="183">
    <s id="183:1">“Why, the devil's got into your house,” answered Menico, out of breath;</s>
    <s id="183:2">“I have seen him myself —— they wanted to kill me —— father Christopher said so —— and you, too, Renzo, he said you must come directly.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="184">
    <s id="184:1">I saw them myself —— it's a providence that I find you all here.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="185">
    <s id="185:1">I'll tell you when we get out of town.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="186">
    <s id="186:1">Renzo, who had his wits about him more than any of them, thought either this way or that they must go immediately, before the people came up, and that the best way was to do what Menico advised; nay, commanded them to do, with the voice of one frightened out of his senses.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="187">
    <s id="187:1">On the road, then, and out of the confusion and danger, they could ask the little boy for a clearer explanation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="188">
    <s id="188:1">“Walk before,” said he; “let us go with him,” said he to the women.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="189">
    <s id="189:1">They turned, rapidly drew near to the church, passed the sacristy, where by the favor of Heaven there was not a living soul, entered a narrow street that separated the church and the house of Don Abbondio, and getting into the first lane they met with, took to the fields.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="190">
    <s id="190:1">They had perhaps not got fifty paces, when the people began to draw nigh to the sacristy, and were increasing in number.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="191">
    <s id="191:1">They looked in each other's faces, every one had something to ask about, no one an answer to give.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="192">
    <s id="192:1">The first who arrived ran to the church door —— it was shut.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="193">
    <s id="193:1">They ran to the belfrey, and one of them clapping his mouth to a sort of loophole there was in the wall, bawled out, “What the devil is the matter?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="194">
    <s id="194:1">Ambrosio, as soon as he heard a voice he knew, let go the rope, and hearing from the rumor that there was a concourse of people without, answered, “I'll come and open the door.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="195">
    <s id="195:1">In haste he slipped on the garment he had carried away under his arm, came through to the church door and opened it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="196">
    <s id="196:1">“What is all this uproar about?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="197">
    <s id="197:1">What's the matter?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="198">
    <s id="198:1">Where —— who is it?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="199">
    <s id="199:1">“How, who is it?” said Ambrosio holding the door with one hand, and with the other hitching up the article of dress he had put on in such a hurry, “What don't you know?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="200">
    <s id="200:1">There's some people in the curate's house, help, help.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="201">
    <s id="201:1">All run to the house, examine it, crowd near to it, look above, listen, every thing was quiet.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="202">
    <s id="202:1">Others go to the street door, find it shut and fastened, they look up, and don't find a window open, not the least movement is heard within.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="203">
    <s id="203:1">“Who is within?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="204">
    <s id="204:1">Hollo, hollo!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="205">
    <s id="205:1">Signor curate! signor curate!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="206">
    <s id="206:1">Don Abbondio, who, as soon as he was aware of the flight of the invaders, had closed the window and retired from it, and who at that moment was wrangling in an under tone with Perpetua, who had left him all alone in his state of trouble, was obliged, when he heard himself called by the people, to go again to the window, and beholding such powerful succor repented the having invoked it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="207">
    <s id="207:1">“What has happened?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="208">
    <s id="208:1">What have they done to you?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="209">
    <s id="209:1">Who are they?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="210">
    <s id="210:1">Where are they?” fifty voices cried out to him all at once.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="211">
    <s id="211:1">“Here's nobody here now.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="212">
    <s id="212:1">I thank you, return home again, therefore.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="213">
    <s id="213:1">“But who has been here?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="214">
    <s id="214:1">Where are they gone?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="215">
    <s id="215:1">What has happened?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="216">
    <s id="216:1">“Bad people, people that go about by night, but they are fled; go home again, it is nothing at all —— another time my children —— I thank you for your kind heartedness.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="217">
    <s id="217:1">Having said this he shut the window and retired.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="218">
    <s id="218:1">Now some began to grumble, others to joke, and some to curse; some again shrugged up their shoulders and went away, when a man arrived breathless, and endeavored to force out a few words.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="219">
    <s id="219:1">This man lived opposite almost to our women, and having, during the rumor, gone to the window, perceived in the court yard of their cottage, the disordered troop of Bravos, when Griso was worrying himself to bring them to order.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="220">
    <s id="220:1">As soon as he had recovered his voice, he exclaimed, “What are you doing here, my sons?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="221">
    <s id="221:1">The devil is not here, he is at the other end of the village, at the cottage of Agnes Mondella; armed men have got into it, and it seems they are going to murder a pilgrim —— who knows what the devil they are going to do!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="222">
    <s id="222:1">“What? what? what?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="223">
    <s id="223:1">And then began a tumultuous consultation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="224">
    <s id="224:1">“We must go there!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="225">
    <s id="225:1">We must go and see?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="226">
    <s id="226:1">How many of them are they?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="227">
    <s id="227:1">How many are we?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="228">
    <s id="228:1">Who are they?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="229">
    <s id="229:1">The consul!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="230">
    <s id="230:1">The consul!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="231">
    <s id="231:1">“Here I am,” answered the consul from the midst of the crowd, “Here I am, but you must give me assistance, and you must obey.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="232">
    <s id="232:1">Quick, where is the sacristan?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="233">
    <s id="233:1">Ring the bell, ring the bell.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="234">
    <s id="234:1">Let one of you immediately go to Lecco to seek assistance; come here all of you ———”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="235">
    <s id="235:1">Now some dart off through the crowd to the belfry, and pull away; great was the tumult, when another man arrives who had seen the enemy in full retreat, and screamed out in his turn, “Run, my sons, thieves or banditti are carrying off a pilgrim —— they have already left the village —— after them —— after them!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="236">
    <s id="236:1">Upon this information, without awaiting the orders of their leader, off they start in a mass, all mixed together, through the village.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="237">
    <s id="237:1">As the army proceeded, some of the vanguard slackened their pace, suffered themselves to be overtaken, and so fell into the centre of the body.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="238">
    <s id="238:1">Those in the rear pushed on before, and thus the confused swarm reached the indicated cottage.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="239">
    <s id="239:1">Traces of the invasion were recent and manifest; the gate open, the bolt wrenched off, but the invaders gone.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="240">
    <s id="240:1">They entered the court yard, and approach the house door, that too is open and the fastening broken; they call out, “Agnes, Lucia!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="241">
    <s id="241:1">The pilgrim!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="242">
    <s id="242:1">Where is the pilgrim?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="243">
    <s id="243:1">Stephano must have been dreaming about a pilgrim —— no, no, Carl Andrea saw him too.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="244">
    <s id="244:1">Hollo, pilgrim!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="245">
    <s id="245:1">Agnes!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="246">
    <s id="246:1">Lucia!” no one answers.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="247">
    <s id="247:1">“They have carried them off!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="248">
    <s id="248:1">They have carried them off!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="249">
    <s id="249:1">Some now raising their voices, proposed to follow the ravishers, it was a nefarious act, and would be the reproach of the whole country if every villain was to be suffered with impunity to carry off women, just as a kite does chickens from a deserted habitation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="250">
    <s id="250:1">A new and a more tumultuous consultation now began, but one (and it never was known exactly who it was) spread a report that Agnes and Lucia had taken refuge in one of the houses.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="251">
    <s id="251:1">This soon got into circulation, and was believed; a pursuit of the fugitives was no longer spoken of, and the multitude broke up, each one going to his own home.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="252">
    <s id="252:1">Then came whisperings, noises, knocking and opening of doors, the appearance and disappearance of lamps, questions asked by women from the windows, and answers given from the street.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="253">
    <s id="253:1">This having become once more deserted and silent, the conversations were revived in the houses, until they expired amidst a general gaping, to be resuscitated again the next day.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="254">
    <s id="254:1">No new facts, however, occurred, except that on the succeeding morning, the consul standing in his field, with his chin resting upon his hands, his hands upon the end of the handle of his spade, half buried in the ground, with his foot yet upon it, and musing within himself upon the mysteries of the past night, and of what might be expected of him, and of what it was his duty to do, saw two men approaching of a very lively presence, their hair combed out like two kings of France of the first race, and, in every thing else extremely resembling the two men, who five days before had stopped Don Abbondio, if they were not the very same persons.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="255">
    <s id="255:1">With still less ceremony they intimated to the consul, that he had better be careful how he made any depositions before the podesta of what had happened, of telling what had taken place, even if he should be interrogated; of gossiping about it, or encouraging any gossipings amongst the country people, if he entertained the slightest hope of regularly dying in a fit of sickness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="256">
    <s id="256:1">Our wanderers went on for some time at a good pace, in silence, first one and then another turning about to look if any body was following them, troubled what with the fatigue they endured, the struggle and suspense they had gone through, the vexation of their ill success, and the confused apprehension of this new inconceivable danger.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="257">
    <s id="257:1">Their distress too was increased by the tolling of the bell, as if in continual pursuit of them, and which, although, as the distance increased, it became weaker and more obtuse, seemed to assume a more lugubrious and ill-omened tone.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="258">
    <s id="258:1">At length it ceased.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="259">
    <s id="259:1">Finding themselves in an unfrequented plain, and perfectly alone, they slackened their pace, and Agnes was the first who, having recovered her breath, broke silence, asking Renzo how the affair had gone, and desiring Menico to tell her what devil he had seen at the cottage.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="260">
    <s id="260:1">Renzo briefly related his sorrowful story, and all three turned to the boy, who detailed to them more exactly the advice of the father, and narrated what he himself had seen, and the risk he had run, and which was too well confirmed by the friar's message.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="261">
    <s id="261:1">The listeners comprehended more than Menico knew how to tell them; at this discovery they were again seized with a shivering; all three stood for a moment in the middle of the road, and exchanged with each other a look of terror, and with an unanimous movement, all placed their hands on the boy, one on his head, another on his shoulders, as if to caress him, and tacitly thank him for having been a tutelar angel to them, to show him how they sympathized with him, and almost to ask him to forgive them for the anguish he had suffered on their account, and the danger he had incurred to save them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="262">
    <s id="262:1">“Now, go home, that thy friends may not be distressed any longer on thy account,” said Agnes to him; and remembering the two parpagliole she had promised him, she produced four and gave them to him, adding, “enough, pray to God that we may meet soon, and then ———”</s>
    <s id="262:2">Renzo gave him a new livre, and entreated him not to say any thing about the commission he had received from the friar.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="263">
    <s id="263:1">Lucia caressed him again, bid him good bye with a trembling voice, and the boy quite softened, saluted them and turned back.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="264">
    <s id="264:1">Onwards they went, quite thoughtful, the women before and Renzo in the rear, as if to guard them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="265">
    <s id="265:1">Lucia held closely to the arm of her mother, and gently and dextrously declined his proffered assistance in the awkward places they came to, in a journey so out of the common road.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="266">
    <s id="266:1">She was ashamed, even in her distress, at having been so often alone with him, and so familiarly, when she expected in but a few moments to be his wife;</s>
    <s id="266:2">now that vision having so sorrowfully passed away, she repented even this; and amongst so many causes of trepidation, she even trembled for that modesty which is not the result of the sad acquaintance with evil, but that delicate modesty which does not even know itself: like the fear of the child who trembles in darkness without knowing why.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="267">
    <s id="267:1">“And the cottage?” said Agnes, on a sudden.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="268">
    <s id="268:1">But although the care which produced that exclamation from her was an important one, no one replied, because no one could give her a satisfactory answer.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="269">
    <s id="269:1">They therefore continued their walk in silence, and soon after finally came out in a small square before the church of the convent. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="270">
    <s id="270:1">Renzo went to the door of the church and pushed it very hard.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="271">
    <s id="271:1">The door immediately opened, and the moonlight entering through the space, illuminated the pallid countenance and the silver beard of father Christopher, who was standing there waiting.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="272">
    <s id="272:1">As soon as he saw that no one was wanting, “God be blessed,” said he, and made them a sign to enter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="273">
    <s id="273:1">By his side was another capuchin, the lay sacristan, whom with entreaties and arguments he had pursuaded to watch with him, to leave the door ajar, and to remain there unguarded to receive those poor menaced people: and nothing less than the authority of the father, and his reputation as a saint, would have sufficed to determine the lay brother to a condescension, both inconvenient, dangerous, and irregular.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="274">
    <s id="274:1">As soon as they were within, father Christopher gently shut the door.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="275">
    <s id="275:1">Then the sacristan could no longer contain himself, and taking the father aside, he whispered in his ear, “but, father, father! at night —— in the church —— with women shut up —— the rules —— but father!” and he shook his head.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="276">
    <s id="276:1">Whilst he was articulating with effort these words —— now just see! thought father Christopher, if it was some ruffian parsued, friar Fazio would not oppose the least difficulty, and a poor innocent that is escaping from the claws of the wolf ——“omnia munda mundis,” he then said, suddenly turning to brother Fazio, and forgetting that he did not understand latin.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="277">
    <s id="277:1">But this forgetfulness was exactly what produced the effect.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="278">
    <s id="278:1">If the father had entered upon a course of argument, brother Fazio would not have been wanting in reasons to answer him, and Heaven knows when the dispute would have been terminated.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="279">
    <s id="279:1">But hearing these grave words, bearing so mysterious a sense, and uttered so resolutely, it appeared to him that they must contain the solution of all his doubts.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="280">
    <s id="280:1">He was satisfied, and said “ Very well, you know better than me, father.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="281">
    <s id="281:1">“Confide in me,” answered father Christopher; and by the faint light of the lamp which was burning before the altar, he drew near to the refugees, who were standing there waiting, and said to them, “My children! thank the Lord that he has delivered you from so great a danger.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="282">
    <s id="282:1">Perhaps at this moment ———!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="283">
    <s id="283:1">And here he began to relate to them the cause why he had despatched the little messenger, never suspecting that they knew more about it than he did himself, and supposing that Menico had found them quiet at home, before the Bravos had arrived.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="284">
    <s id="284:1">No one undeceived him, not even Lucia, although she had some secret remorse for dissimulating with a man of his character; but this was a night full of entanglement and duplicity.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="285">
    <s id="285:1">“After this,” continued he, “you see my children, that this part of the country is not safe for you.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="286">
    <s id="286:1">It is yours, you are born here, you have done wrong to no one, but God wills it so.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="287">
    <s id="287:1">It is a trial, my children; bear it with patience, with constancy, without rancor, and rest assured that the time will come when you will say that you are contented with what has happened.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="288">
    <s id="288:1">I have thought of a refuge for you in these first moments.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="289">
    <s id="289:1">Soon, I hope, you will be able to return in safety to your own homes; in every way God will provide for you for the best, and most certainly I will endeavor not to be found wanting for the favor I have found with him, choosing me, as he has done, as his minister, in the service of you his afflicted ones.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="290">
    <s id="290:1">You,” continued he, addressing himself to the women,“ can stop at —————.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="291">
    <s id="291:1">There you will be sufficiently out of danger, and at the same time, not too distant from your home.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="292">
    <s id="292:1">Inquire for our convent: ask for the father guardian, give him this letter, he will be to you another father Christopher.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="293">
    <s id="293:1">And thee, my poor Renzo, thou also must save thyself from the fury of another, as well as from thy own.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="294">
    <s id="294:1">Carry this letter to father Buonaventura du Lodi at our convent, at the eastern gate in Milan.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="295">
    <s id="295:1">He will be a father to thee, will give thee directions, will find thee work, until the moment when thou canst return here to live tranquilly.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="296">
    <s id="296:1">Go to the bank of the lake, near the mouth of the Bione,” a mountain stream not far from the convent, “there thou'lt find a boat; call out —— boat —— thou wilt be asked for whom; answer Saint-Francis.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="297">
    <s id="297:1">The boat will then take thee, transport thee to the other bank, where thou wilt find a wagon that will conduct thee straight on as far as —————”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="298">
    <s id="298:1">Whoever asks how father Christopher could so soon have at his disposition those means of transportation by water and by land, shows that he knows nothing of the influence a capuchin could acquire, who was reputed to be a saint.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="299">
    <s id="299:1">The next thing to think of was the custody of the cottages.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="300">
    <s id="300:1">The father received the keys, taking upon himself the charge of delivering them to those whom Renzo and Agnes indicated to him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="301">
    <s id="301:1">Agnes, when she gave up her own, brought out a great sigh, thinking, that at that very moment, the cottage was open, that the devil had been inside of it, and that there was no guessing what might be left in it to take care of.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="302">
    <s id="302:1">“Before you go,” said the father, “let us all put up supplications to the Lord, that he may be with you in your journey, and always, and above all, that he may fill you with strength, and with grace, to wish that his will may be done.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="303">
    <s id="303:1">Saying this, he knelt down in the middle of the church, and all did the same.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="304">
    <s id="304:1">As soon as they had prayed a few moments in silence, he, with a low, but distinct voice, articulated these words: “We pray thee, also, for that wretched being who has brought us to this pass.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="305">
    <s id="305:1">We should be unworthy of thy mercy, if we did not ask it for him from our hearts, for he has great need of it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="306">
    <s id="306:1">For us, in our tribulation, we have this comfort, Lord —— that we tread the path in which thou hast placed us.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="307">
    <s id="307:1">Our woes we can offer up to thee, and turn them into gain.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="308">
    <s id="308:1">But he! he is thy enemy.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="309">
    <s id="309:1">Unhappy man! he strives against his God!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="310">
    <s id="310:1">Have mercy upon him, Oh Lord! touch his heart, make him love thee, and grant to him all that happiness we would ask for ourselves.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="311">
    <s id="311:1">Then quickly rising up, he said, “Away, my children; there is no time to lose.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="312">
    <s id="312:1">God protect you; may his angel accompany you! go!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="313">
    <s id="313:1">As they departed, filled with emotions that cannot express themselves by words, and that manifest themselves without them, the father added, in a low tone, full of feeling, “My heart tells me we shall soon see each other again.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="314">
    <s id="314:1">Certainly, the heart, when one attends to it, has always something to say about the future.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="315">
    <s id="315:1">But what does the heart know?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="316">
    <s id="316:1">Scarce the least thing of the past.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="317">
    <s id="317:1">Without awaiting an answer, brother Christopher withdrew with a hurried step; the travelers left the church, and brother Fazio closed the door, saying adieu to them in a tone likewise of some feeling.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="318">
    <s id="318:1">Slowly they took the road to the bank that had been named to them, saw the boat there, and having interchanged the countersign, entered it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="319">
    <s id="319:1">The boatman thrust his oar against the bank, and shoved the boat off; then, taking the other, used both his arms to row them to the opposite shore.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="320">
    <s id="320:1">Not a breath of wind was stirring.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="321">
    <s id="321:1">The lake was reposing quietly and smoothly, and would have appeared immovable, but for the tremulous and slight waving motion of the light of a fine moon, that was admiring herself in the lake from the midst of the heavens.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="322">
    <s id="322:1">No sounds were heard save the dead and gentle flow of the water, breaking in ripples on the gravelly shore; its more distant murmuring, as it broke amidst the piles of the bridge, and the measured dashing of the two oars, which cutting the azure surface of the lake reappeared together, dropping with the fluid, again to be simultaneously buried beneath.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="323">
    <s id="323:1">The wave occasioned by the advancing boat reunited itself behind the stern, and formed a crested line, which prolonged itself as they receded from the shore.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="324">
    <s id="324:1">The passengers, mute, with their faces turned back, looked at the mountains and the country bathed in moonlight, and chequered here and there by strong shades.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="325">
    <s id="325:1">Villages, houses, cabins, were seen.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="326">
    <s id="326:1">The ample palace of Don Rodrigo, with its flat tower, elevated above the miserable and crowded cottages on the skirt of the promontory, seemed like some ferocious being standing in the darkness over a company recumbent and asleep, watching and meditating a crime.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="327">
    <s id="327:1">Lucia saw it and shuddered; she followed the slope of the country down with her eye as far as her own village; caught the extreme end of it; perceived her cottage, the thick foilage of the fig tree which almost shadowed the circuit of the court-yard, even the window of her own room; and thus seated in the bottom of the boat, leaning her elbow on the gunnel, she lowered her face as if to slumber, and wept in secret. </s>
  </p>
  <p id="328">
    <s id="328:1">Adieu, ye mountains, rearing yourselves from the waters erect unto heaven!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="329">
    <s id="329:1">Unequal summits, known to him who has been brought up amidst you, and impressed on his mind as vividly as the features of a familiar friend.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="330">
    <s id="330:1">Ye torrents, whose brawling sounds come upon his ear like well known domestic voices: ye scattered villages, blanching the steeps, like flocks of browsing sheep, adieu!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="331">
    <s id="331:1">How sorrowful is the tread of him, who, reared among you, must leave you behind.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="332">
    <s id="332:1">Even in the fancy of him who voluntarily goes, led on by the hopes of future prosperity, at that moment all the dreams of riches lose their influence; he wonders how he could have resolved, and would retrace his steps, were it not for the thought that another day shall see him return in opulence.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="333">
    <s id="333:1">The further he advances upon the plain, the more his eye becomes wearied and annoyed by the unvarying space: the air seems heavy and without elasticity; sad and inattentive he enters the tumultuous city; houses joined to houses —— streets terminating in streets, appear to impede his respiration; and standing before those edifices which are the admiration of the stranger, he recalls to his mind, with restless partiality, the little field of his native place, and that cottage he has had in his eye so long, the future acquisition when he returns enriched to his native mountains.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="334">
    <s id="334:1">But she who had never cast beyond her native mountains even a fugitive desire, who had formed all her plans for the future amongst them, and who is driven far away by a perverse fortune! torn away at once from the most endearing habits, disturbed in her sweetest hopes, leaving her own hills to tread those paths of the stranger, which she has never desired to know, and who cannot even in imagination fix upon a moment appointed for her return!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="335">
    <s id="335:1">Adieu, native cottage, where, seated, amidst her secret thoughts, she learnt to distinguish from the common tread, the footsteps of the one she awaited with a mysterious apprehension.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="336">
    <s id="336:1">Adieu, that yet unfrequented roof, where, passing, she had so often cast a fugitive look, and not without a blush: where her mind indulged in soft anticipations of a life spent in the tranquil and steady duties of a wife.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="337">
    <s id="337:1">Adieu, church, to which her serene soul had so often returned, to sing the praises of the Lord, where a holy rite had been promised and prepared; where the secret wish of the heart was to have been solemnly blessed, where she was to have been commanded to love, and where her love was to have been pronounced holy.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="338">
    <s id="338:1">Farewell!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="339">
    <s id="339:1">Yet know that he who placed you in this sweet existence, is every where; and that he never disturbs the contentment of his children, but to prepare a happiness for them that is purer, and less uncertain.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="340">
    <s id="340:1">Such was the nature, if not exactly thus, of the thoughts of Lucia, and not very dissimilar the reflections of the two other pilgrims, whilst the boat was drawing nigh to the right bank of the Adda.</s>
  </p>
</text>
