<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">"Carneades! who was this man?" said Don Abbondio to himself, seated in his great chair in an upper room, a great book open before him, when Perpetua entered to lay before him this embassy.</s>
    <s id="1:2">"Carneades! it seems to me that I have either heard or read this name; it must be a learned man, a wise man of ancient times; it is one of those names; but who the devil was this Carneades?" —— </s>
    <s id="1:3">So far was the poor man from foreseeing the tempest which was gathering over his head.</s>
    <s id="1:4">It is necessary to know that Don Abbondio amused himself with reading a little every day; a curate, his neighbour, who had a small library, lent him one book after another, the first which came to hand.</s>
    <s id="1:5">The one upon which in this moment Don Abbondio meditated, convalescent from the fever of fear, even more restored (as far as the fever was concerned than he wished to be imagined), was a panegyric in honour of San Carlo, pronounced with much emphasis, and listened to with much admiration in the cathedral of Milan two years before.</s>
    <s id="1:6">The saint was compared, on account of his passion for study, to Archimedes; so far Don Abbondio had found no difficulty, since Archimedes did such wonderful things, and made himself so much talked about, that to know some little about him it is not necessary to have a very vast erudition.</s>
    <s id="1:7">But after Archimedes, the orator called Carneades into the comparison; and it was here that the reader remained run aground.</s>
    <s id="1:8">At this moment Perpetua entered to announce the visit of Tonio.</s>
    <s id="1:9">"At this hour?" said also Don Abbondio, as was very natural.</s>
    <s id="1:10">"What would you have?" </s>
    <s id="1:11">People have no discretion; but if you don't catch him soaring————" </s>
    <s id="1:12">"If I don't catch him now, who knows when I shall be able to catch him?</s>
    <s id="1:13">Let him in.</s>
    <s id="1:14">Ah, ah! but are you quite sure that it is Tonio himself?"</s>
    <s id="1:15">"Diavolo!" replied Perpetua, who descended; then opened the door and said, "Where are you?" and at the same moment Agnese appeared also, and saluted Perpetua by her name.</s>
    <s id="1:16">"Good evening, Agnese," said Perpetua, " where do you come from, at this hour?"</s>
    <s id="1:17">"I come from ————," and here she named a neighbouring village; "and if you only knew," continued she, "I stayed there precisely on your account."</s>
    <s id="1:18">"Why?" demanded Perpetua, and turning towards the brothers, said, "enter, I shall come."</s>
    <s id="1:19">"Because," replied Agnese, "one of those women who know nothing, yet who must always be talking —— can you believe it? persisted in saying that you were not married to Beppo Suolavecchia or Anselmo Lunghigna, because they did not wish to have you.</s>
    <s id="1:20">I maintained that you had refused both one and the other————" </s>
    <s id="1:21">"Certainly.</s>
    <s id="1:22">O the liar! the great story-teller!</s>
    <s id="1:23">Who is this woman?" </s>
    <s id="1:24">"No, do not ask me, for I do not like to set people by the ears."</s>
    <s id="1:25">"You shall tell me,——you have to tell me.</s>
    <s id="1:26">O the liar!"</s>
    <s id="1:27">"Enough! but you cannot think how sorry I was not to know all the history, so as to be able to confound her."</s>
    <s id="1:28">"You see how people can invent in this world!" exclaimed again Perpetua, and immediately continued; "as to Beppo, every one knows, and has been able to see———— </s>
    <s id="1:29">O Tonio! approach the door and go up stairs, I shall come directly." </s>
    <s id="1:30">Tonio replied "Yes," from within, and Perpetua continued her impassioned narrative.</s>
    <s id="1:31">Facing Don Abbondio's door, opened between two low buildings, a little lane which ran in a right line the length of these two houses, and then turned off into a field.</s>
    <s id="1:32">Agnese took this road, as though she would draw Perpetua aside, so as to speak more freely, and Perpetua followed her.</s>
    <s id="1:33">When they had turned the corner, and were in a place from whence what passed before Don Abbondio's house could no longer be seen, Agnese coughed loudly; this was the signal, Renzo heard it, and encouraged Lucia, by pressing her arm; both on tip-toe came forth, creeping along the wall silently, silently; they arrived at the door, pushed it open slowly, slowly; softly, and bending themselves, they entered the corridor, where the two brothers were waiting for them.</s>
    <s id="1:34">Renzo reclosed very gently the door, and all the four began to mount the stairs, making noise only for two.</s>
    <s id="1:35">Arrived on the landing-place, the brothers neared the door of the chamber, which was on the side of the staircase; the Betrothed drew themselves up against the wall.</s>
    <s id="1:36">"Deo gratias!" said Tonio, with a loud voice.</s>
    <s id="1:37">"Tonio, enter," replied the voice from within.</s>
    <s id="1:38">The one who was called, opened the door scarcely enough to allow himself and his brother to pass in one by one.</s>
    <s id="1:39">The ray of light which suddenly issued through this aperture, and which painted itself on the dark pavement of the landing-place, made Lucia tremble as though she were discovered.</s>
    <s id="1:40">When the two brothers had entered, Tonio drew after him the door, the Betrothed remained immoveable in the darkness, all ear, their breath held back; the loudest noise was the beating of poor Lucia's heart.</s>
    <s id="1:41">Don Abbondio was, as we have said, seated by the miserable light of a little lamp in an old chair, wrapt in an old morning gown, with an old cap on his head, which made a frame round his face.</s>
    <s id="1:42">Two thick locks of air which escaped from under his cap, two thick eyebrows, a thick moustache, and a thick beard, all hoary, scattered over this brown and wrinkled face, resembled bushes covered with snow, jutting out over a precipice in the moonlight.</s>
    <s id="1:43">"Ah, ah!" was his salute, as he took off his spectacles, and laid them in his book.</s>
    <s id="1:44">"The Signor Curato will say that I am come too late," said Tonio bowing, as did also Gervaso, but more awkwardly.</s>
    <s id="1:45">"Certainly it is late; late in every manner.</s>
    <s id="1:46">Do you know that I am ill?"</s>
    <s id="1:47">"O!</s>
    <s id="1:48">I am sorry."</s>
    <s id="1:49">"You will have heard this said; I have fallen sick, and I do not know when I shall be able to be seen ————but why have you brought with you this ————this boy?" </s>
    <s id="1:50">" For company, Signor Curato."</s>
    <s id="1:51">"Enough, let us see."</s>
    <s id="1:52">"Here are five-and-twenty berlinghe quite new, those with Saint Ambrose on horseback," said Tonio, taking a little packet out of his pocket.</s>
    <s id="1:53">"Let us see" replied Don Abbondio; and having taken the packet, he put on again his spectacles, opened it, tried the berlinghe, counted them, looked at them again, and found them without defect.</s>
    <s id="1:54">"Now Signor Curato, you will give me the necklace of my Tecla."</s>
    <s id="1:55">"That is but just," replied Don Abbondio.</s>
    <s id="1:56">He went towards a press, put a key into the keyhole, and looking behind him as though to keep the spectators in the distance, opened one side of the door, filled up with his body the opening which he made, thrust his head in to look about, and an arm to take the necklace; he drew them back, closed the press, and gave the necklace to Tonio, saying—— "Is this it?"</s>
    <s id="1:57">"Now," said Tonio, "please to put a little black upon white." </s>
    <s id="1:58">"Also this?" said Don Abbondio, "they all know it.</s>
    <s id="1:59">Ah, how suspicious the world is grown!</s>
    <s id="1:60">Do you not trust me?"</s>
    <s id="1:61">"How, Signor Curato!</s>
    <s id="1:62">Whether I trust you?</s>
    <s id="1:63">You do me wrong; but as my name is in your big book, beside the debt,——since you have taken the trouble to write it once,——since from life to death ————" </s>
    <s id="1:64">"Good, good," interrupted Don Abbondio, and grumbling, he drew towards himself a drawer in the table, took out paper, a pen and an inkhorn, and began to write, repeating aloud the words one after the other, as they issued from his pen.</s>
    <s id="1:65">Then Tonio and Gervaso, at a sign which he gave him, planted themselves right before the little table, so as to impede the view of the door; and then, as in idleness, they began scraping the floor with their feet, as a signal to those without to enter, and also to confound at the same time the sound of their steps.</s>
    <s id="1:66">Don Abbondio, immersed in his writing, paid attention to nothing else.</s>
    <s id="1:67">At the scraping of the four feet, Renzo took one of Lucia's arms, pressing it to give her courage, and moved away, drawing her after him all trembling, since she would have been unable to walk there herself.</s>
    <s id="1:68">They entered very gently on tiptoe, holding their breath.</s>
    <s id="1:69">Don Abbondio having finished writing, read again attentively what he had written, without raising his eyes from the paper; then folded it in four, saying, "Now shall you be contented?" took his spectacles from his nose with one hand, and with the other presented the writing to Tonio, raising his head at the same time.</s>
    <s id="1:70">Tonio, advancing his hand to take it, retired a little on one side, and Gervaso, at a sign which was given him, retired to the other; and then in the midst, as by a coup-de-théâtre, appeared Renzo and Lucia!</s>
    <s id="1:71">Don Abbondio saw confusedly, saw clearly, became terrified, stupefied, grew enraged, reflected, took a resolution; all in the time that Renzo pronounced the words "Signor Curato, in presence of these witnesses, this is my wife!" </s>
    <s id="1:72">His lips were not yet closed, before Don Abbondio let fall the receipt he had taken, raised the lamp with his left hand, seized with his right the cloth which covered the table, and drawing it towards him in a rage, threw to the ground, book, paper, inkhorn and sand; then rushing between the chair and the table, he approached Lucia.</s>
    <s id="1:73">The poor child, with her gentle and now trembling voice, had scarcely pronounced, "And here ————," than Don Abbondio had roughly thrown the cloth over her head, so as to prevent her pronouncing the entire formula.</s>
    <s id="1:74">And suddenly letting fall the lamp which he held in the other hand, assisted himself also with this in wrapping her head up in the cloth until she was nearly suffocated, all the time crying out at the pitch of his voice——"Perpetua! Perpetua! help!" </s>
    <s id="1:75">The wick of the lamp dying on the pavement, threw a languid and unequal light upon Lucia, who, perfectly disheartened, did not endeavour to disengage herself, and seemed a statue moulded in clay, over which the artist has cast a damp cloth.</s>
    <s id="1:76">All light extinguished, Don Abbondio left the poor girl, and went groping about after the door which led into an inner room, found it, entered, shut himself in, still crying, "Perpetua! help! treason! out of this house! out of this house!" </s>
    <s id="1:77">All was conftision in the other apartment, Renzo seeking the Curate, and feeling about with his hands, as one does in blindman's buff, had reached the door and knocked, crying out, "Open! open! don't make such a noise."</s>
    <s id="1:78">Lucia called to Renzo in a stifled voice, and supplicated him, saying, "For the love of God, let us go, let us go." </s>
    <s id="1:79">Tonio on all fours, sought on the pavement after his receipt, and frightened, cried, and jumped about, trying to find the staircase, so as to get out and save himself.</s>
    <s id="1:80">In the midst of all this uproar, we cannot prevent ourselves pausing one moment to make a reflection.</s>
    <s id="1:81">Renzo, who caused all this terror in a strange house, where he had secretly introduced himself, where he kept the master himself besieged in his chamber, has all the appearance of an oppressor, Don Abbondio surprised, put to flight, terrified whilst he was tranquilly attending to his own affairs, appears the victim, and yet in reality, it was he who was the injurer.</s>
    <s id="1:82">Thus it often happens in the world.</s>
    <s id="1:83">I would say this, it happened in the seventeenth century.</s>
    <s id="1:84">The besieged, seeing that the enemy gave no sign of retiring, opened a window which looked into the church-yard, and began to cry, "help! help!" </s>
    <s id="1:85">It was the most beautiful moonlight.</s>
    <s id="1:86">The shadow of the church, and further out the long and sharp shadow of the belfry, extended itself, black and distinct, upon the grassy and brilliant church-yard.</s>
    <s id="1:87">Eyery object might be distinguished almost as clearly as by day.</s>
    <s id="1:88">But as far as the eye could reach, no sign of a living creature could be perceived.</s>
    <s id="1:89">Adjoining, however, the wall of the church, which looked towards the parochial house, was a little habitation, a tiny hut, where slept the sacristan.</s>
    <s id="1:90">He, awakened by this lamentable cry, made a spring out of his bed, got up in haste, opened one of the panes in his little window and put forth his head, his eyes still closed with sleep, and said, "What is the matter?"</s>
    <s id="1:91">"Run, Ambrogio! help!</s>
    <s id="1:92">There are people in the house!" cried Don Abbondio to him.</s>
    <s id="1:93">"I'll come immediately," replied he, and drew back his head, shut the window, and although half asleep, and more than half frightened, discovered on the spot an expedient for assisting the one who called him, without getting himself into the tumult, whatever this might be.</s>
    <s id="1:94">He seizes his breeches, which he kept on his bed, tucks them under his arm like a hat of ceremony, and now springs up the wooden staircase, he runs to the belfry, seizes the cord of the largest of the two bells which hang there, and tolls.</s>
    <s id="1:95">Dong, dong, dong, dong! the peasants start up and sit in their beds, the lads lying in the hayloft listen, and spring to their feet.</s>
    <s id="1:96">"What is it?</s>
    <s id="1:97">What is it?</s>
    <s id="1:98">The bell tolls! fire? thieves? bandits?" </s>
    <s id="1:99">Many women counsel, beseech their husbands not to move, to let others go; some get up, and run to the window; the cowards, as though persuaded by these prayers, return and lie down; the more curious and the brave descend to seize forks and arquebuses, and to run to the quarter from whence the noise proceeds.</s>
    <s id="1:100">But before they were ready, before even they were well awake, the noise had reached the ears of other people, who watched not far off, dressed and on their legs; the bravoes in one place, Agnese and Perpetua in another.</s>
    <s id="1:101">We will say first of all, in a few words, what these have been doing since the moment we left them, some in the hostelry, the others in the demolished house.</s>
    <s id="1:102">When the three saw all the doors closed and the street deserted, they went out in haste, as though they perceived it had grown late, saying they would go quickly home, took a walk through the village to assure themselves that every one had retired, and, in fact, did not meet a single living sold, or hear the slightest sound.</s>
    <s id="1:103">They passed on very very silently before our poor cottage, the quietest of all, since no one was there.</s>
    <s id="1:104">They then went straight to the desolate house, and made their relation to Griso.</s>
    <s id="1:105">Immediately he put on his head a large hat, threw over his shoulders a frock of waxed cloth covered with cockle-shells, took a pilgrim's staff in his hand, and said, "Let us go, bravoes; be silent, and attend to my orders." </s>
    <s id="1:106">He marched off the first, and the others followed him.</s>
    <s id="1:107">They arrived in a short time at the cottage, by a road opposite to the one by which our little troop set out on its expedition.</s>
    <s id="1:108">Griso made his band halt a few paces from the cottage, and went on alone to explore, and seeing all deserted and quiet outside, made two of these wicked ones come on before, and gave them the order to scale the low wall which enclosed the little court, and descended into it to hide themselves in an angle behind a thick fig-tree upon which he had fixed his eyes in the morning.</s>
    <s id="1:109">That done, he knocked very gently, with the intention of saying he was an unfortunate pilgrim who petitioned for shelter until day; no one answered; he knocked again even more loudly, not even a "hush!" </s>
    <s id="1:110">Then he went and called a third villain, and made him descend like the first two into the court, with the order to remove the bolt gently, so as to have the free power of going in and out.</s>
    <s id="1:111">All this was executed with much address and perfect secresy.</s>
    <s id="1:112">He goes and calls the others, makes them enter with him, sends them to conceal themselves with the three, opens the street door very gently, posts two sentinels inside, and then goes straight to the door of the cottage; he knocks again, he waits,——he might well wait!</s>
    <s id="1:113">Then he unnails also this lock without any noise.</s>
    <s id="1:114">No one said from within, "who's there?" no one was heard; things could not go on better.</s>
    <s id="1:115">Having done this, "hist," he calls to those under the tree, and enters with them the rooms on the ground-floor, where in the morning he had so hypocritically begged the morsel of bread.</s>
    <s id="1:116">He takes out tinder, a flint, a steel and matches, lights his lantern, and enters an inner room to see if any one is there.</s>
    <s id="1:117">There is no one.</s>
    <s id="1:118">He returns, and he goes to the door of the staircase, looks up, listens; every where solitude and silence.</s>
    <s id="1:119">He leaves two other sentinels on the ground-floor, takes with him Griguapoco, who was a bravo from the neighbourhood of Bergamo, who alone must menace, soothe, and command, in short, be the orator, to the end that his dialect should make Agnese believe the expedition came from that quarter.</s>
    <s id="1:120">With this man at his side, and the others behind, Griso mounted slowly, slowly up the stairs, cursing in his heart every step which creaked, every tread of these scoundrels which made a noise.</s>
    <s id="1:121">At length he is at the top.</s>
    <s id="1:122">Here is the hare's form!</s>
    <s id="1:123">Gently he pushes the door which leads into the first room, it gives way, he opens it slightly, he looks in, all is dark, he lays his ear to the crevice, to hear if any one breathes, no one moves; nothing!</s>
    <s id="1:124">Forward then.</s>
    <s id="1:125">He places the lantern before his face, so as to see without being seen, and opens the door quite wide.</s>
    <s id="1:126">He touches a bed, he throws himself upon it; the bed is made and smooth, with the coverlet well turned down over the pillow.</s>
    <s id="1:127">He shrugs his shoulders, turns towards his followers, makes a sign that they shall go into the next chamber, and follows them softly.</s>
    <s id="1:128">He goes there, performs the same ceremony, finds the same thing.</s>
    <s id="1:129">"What the devil is this?" said he then in his loudest voice, "there must be some dog of a traitor who has played the spy." </s>
    <s id="1:130">They all begin to look about with less precaution, and to search in all the corners, they turn the house topsy-turvy.</s>
    <s id="1:131">Whilst they are thus occupied, the two who watch at the doorhear a noise of quick footsteps, as of some one who hastens from the fields towards the village; the noise approaches; the bravoes imagine, whoever this may be, he will pass on without stopping; they remain quiet, and stand on their guard.</s>
    <s id="1:132">But, in fact, the footsteps stop precisely before the door.</s>
    <s id="1:133">It was Menico, who came in haste, sent by Father Cristoforo, to inform the two women that for the love of heaven they should escape out of their house immediately, and come and take refuge in the convent, since ———— he knew the wherefore.</s>
    <s id="1:134">He takes hold of the hasp of the door to knock, and feels it move in his hand unnailed and loose.</s>
    <s id="1:135">"What is this?" thinks he, and pushes the door, somewhat frightened ——it opens.</s>
    <s id="1:136">Menico steps in with great suspicion.</s>
    <s id="1:137">He feels himself suddenly seized by the arms, and two low voices, one on either side of him, say in a very menacing tone——"Silence, or thou art dead!" </s>
    <s id="1:138">He, however, sends forth a loud cry; one of those who hold him, places a large hand over his mouth, the other menaces him with an immense knife, so as to frighten him.</s>
    <s id="1:139">The little boy trembles like a leaf, and attempts no longer to cry; but all at once, instead of him, the first tolling of the bell, and following it a continuous tempest of sound, is heard. </s>
    <s id="1:140">'Who is in fault, is in fear,' says a Milanese proverb; both one and the other of these wicked wretches seem to hear in this tolling, his name, surname, and cognomen.</s>
    <s id="1:141">They let go Menico's arms, draw back theirs in a hurry, raise their hands, open their mouths, gaze at each other, and run to the house where was the greater part of the company.</s>
    <s id="1:142">Menico begins running at full speed towards the belfry, where at all events some one must be.</s>
    <s id="1:143">Upon the wretches who were groping about from the top to the bottom of the house, this terrible bell made the same impression; they were confounded; they were terrified; they ran against each other, each one sought the nearest way to arrive at the door.</s>
    <s id="1:144">They were all people tried and accustomed to brave difficulties, but they could not stand calm before an uncertain danger, before a danger which had not shewn itself in the distance, but had suddenly burst over them.</s>
    <s id="1:145">All Griso's superiority was necessary to keep them together, so that it should be a retreat and not a flight.</s>
    <s id="1:146">Like a dog guarding a herd of hogs, running here and running there, after those which are disbanding, seizing one by the ear, and drawing him back, pushing another with his nose, and barking at a third, which this moment leaves the ranks; so the Pilgrim seized by his ciuffo one of his companions, who had already touched the threshold, and draws him in; drives back with his staff two others who are ready to escape, shouting to the rest, who are running about here and there, without knowing where to go, until he at length gathers them all together in the middle of the little court ——</s>
    <s id="1:147">"Quick, quick! pistols in your hands, your knives ready, all together; and then let us set off; thus we shall manage.</s>
    <s id="1:148">Who do you think will touch us if we all keep together; great cowards, that you are?</s>
    <s id="1:149">But if we let ourselves be taken one by one, these villains will give it us,——shame!</s>
    <s id="1:150">Behind me, and be united." </s>
    <s id="1:151">After this short harangue he placed himself at their head, and issued forth the first.</s>
    <s id="1:152">The house was as we have said, at the beginning of the village.</s>
    <s id="1:153">Griso took the road which led towards the fields, and they all followed him in good order.</s>
    <s id="1:154">We will leave them to continue their march, and retrace our steps, and find again Agnese and Perpetua where we have left them in a certain little road.</s>
    <s id="1:155">Agnese had tried to remove the other as much as possible from Don Abbondio's house, and until a certain point all had gone on well.</s>
    <s id="1:156">But suddenly the housekeeper recollected that the door was left open, and wished to turn back; Agnese, not to excite suspicion, was obliged to return with her, and followed, trying to hold her back each time she saw her get warm in the relation of these numerous marriages.</s>
    <s id="1:157">She appeared to pay great attention, and from time to time to shew she was attentive, or to keep the conversation in a right channel, she said, "Certainly, now I comprehend, that's very good; it's clear; and then? and he? and you?" </s>
    <s id="1:158">But at the same time she held another discourse with herself—— </s>
    <s id="1:159">"Will they be come out now, or will they still be within?</s>
    <s id="1:160">How stupid we have all three of us been, not to concert some signal to tell me when all has succeeded!</s>
    <s id="1:161">It is a great folly, but it is now done; the best thing now, is to amuse this creature as much as I can.</s>
    <s id="1:162">At the worst it will only be a little lost time." </s>
    <s id="1:163">Thus with many pausings and hurryings on again, they had returned to within a short distance of Don Abbondio's house, which, however, was not visible to them, on account of this corner; and Perpetua finding herself at a very important part of her recital, had let herself be stopped without making any resistance, and even without being aware of it herself, when all at once was heard echoing from above in the immoveable void of the air, and in the dead silence of night, that first fearful cry of Don Abbondio—— "Help! help!"</s>
    <s id="1:164">"Mercy! what has happened?" cried Perpetua, and wished to run towards the house.  </s>
    <s id="1:165">"What is it? what is it?" said Agnese, holding her by her petticoat.</s>
    <s id="1:166">"Mercy! have you not heard?" replied the other, disengaging herself.</s>
    <s id="1:167">"What is it? what is it?" repeated Agnese, seizing her by the arm.</s>
    <s id="1:168">"Fiend of a woman!" cried Perpetua, pushing her away so as to liberate herself; and she set off running.</s>
    <s id="1:169">At the same instant was heard, but further off, sharper, more urgent, the cry of Menico.</s>
    <s id="1:170">"Mercy!" cried Agnese also, and she began to gallop behind the other.</s>
    <s id="1:171">They had scarcely raised their heels, than the bell tolled, one stroke—two—three, and many following ones.</s>
    <s id="1:172">These would all have been spurs to her, had she been in need of such.</s>
    <s id="1:173">Perpetua arrived in advance of Agnese a step or two; and whilst waiting to open the door, it opens of itself from within, and Tonio, Gervaso, Renzo, Lucia, appear upon the threshold, who, having found the staircase, had come leaping down, and hearing this terrible uproar, ran in the greatest haste to save themselves.</s>
    <s id="1:174">"What is it? what is it?" demanded Perpetua, panting, from the two brothers, who replied by running against her and escaping.</s>
    <s id="1:175">"And you?——how?——what are you doing here?" demanded she from the other couple, when she had recognised them; these also went out without a reply.</s>
    <s id="1:176">But Perpetua, running where the need was greater, asked nothing more, entered in haste the corridor, and ran as well as she could in the darkness towards the staircase.</s>
    <s id="1:177">The two who still remained——the Betrothed——found themselves opposite to Agnese, who arrived quite distressed and alarmed.</s>
    <s id="1:178">"Ah! you here?" said she speaking with difficulty.</s>
    <s id="1:179">"How has it gone on? what is this bell?</s>
    <s id="1:180">I seem to have heard————" </s>
    <s id="1:181">"Home, home!" exclaimed Renzo, "before people arrive;" and they set out; but Menico appeared runnings,——he recognises them, he stops them, and still trembling, with a weak voice says, "Where are you going?</s>
    <s id="1:182">Back, back! on to the convent!"</s>
    <s id="1:183">"Is it thou who ————?" commenced Agnese.</s>
    <s id="1:184">"What is it, then?" demanded Renzo.</s>
    <s id="1:185">Lucia, disheartened, was silent, and trembled.</s>
    <s id="1:186">"The devil is in your house!" replied Menico, panting.</s>
    <s id="1:187">"I have seen them myself; they wanted to murder me,——Father Cristoforo has said so.</s>
    <s id="1:188">And Renzo, he has said that you also should come directly ——and then I have seen them myself.</s>
    <s id="1:189">It is a providence that I have found you all here.</s>
    <s id="1:190">I will tell you all when we have got away." </s>
    <s id="1:191">Renzo, who had more presence of mind than the others, thought that they must go quickly somewhere before the people arrived, and that the safest was to do as Menico counselled, dictated to as he was by the strength of his fear.</s>
    <s id="1:192">Then on their way, and out of all danger, they could demand from the little boy a clearer explanation.</s>
    <s id="1:193">"Go first," said he to him; "go with him," said he to the women.</s>
    <s id="1:194">They turned back and directed their steps towards the church, crossed the church-yard, where, by the grace of heaven, no living soul had yet appeared, entered a little road which ran between the church and Don Abbondio's house, and at the first gap they saw in the hedge, through it and away for the fields.</s>
    <s id="1:195">They were not perhaps distant fifty paces, when the people began to arrive in the churchyard; the crowd increased every moment.</s>
    <s id="1:196">They gazed in each other's faces; every one had a question to ask, no one an answer to give.</s>
    <s id="1:197">The first who arrived ran to the church door,——it was shut.</s>
    <s id="1:198">They ran to the outside of the belfry, and one of them having placed his head at one of the little windows, a species of loophole, shouted, "What the devil is this?" </s>
    <s id="1:199">When Ambrogio heard a familiar voice, he let go the cord; and being assured by the noise that many people had arrived, he replied, "I am coming to open the door." </s>
    <s id="1:200">He put on in haste the harness which he had carried under his arm, and came through the interior to the door of the church, and opened it.</s>
    <s id="1:201">"What is all this noise?</s>
    <s id="1:202">What is it? where is it? who is it?"</s>
    <s id="1:203">"How? who is it?" said Ambrogio, holding with one hand the door, and with the other a corner of the harness which had thus been put on in such haste.</s>
    <s id="1:204">"How, don't you know?</s>
    <s id="1:205">There are people in the house of the Signor Curato.</s>
    <s id="1:206">Courage, children, help!" </s>
    <s id="1:207">They turn towards the house, they rush there in a crowd, they look up, they listen,——all is quiet; others run to the door,——it is closed, and does not appear to have been moved; they look up again,——there is not a single window open, they do not hear a sound.</s>
    <s id="1:208">"Who is there within—— ohe! —— ohe!</s>
    <s id="1:209">Signor Curato!</s>
    <s id="1:210">Signor Curato!" </s>
    <s id="1:211">Don Abbondio, who, scarcely assured of the flight of the invaders, had retired from the window, closed it, and who now was quarreling with Perpetua in an under-tone, because she had left him alone in this embarrassment, was obliged, when he heard himself called by the voice of the people, again to come to the window.</s>
    <s id="1:212">When he saw this overpowering assistance, he repented of having called it.</s>
    <s id="1:213">"What has happened?</s>
    <s id="1:214">What have they done?</s>
    <s id="1:215">Who are they?</s>
    <s id="1:216">Where are they?" was shouted from fifty voices all at once.</s>
    <s id="1:217">"There is no longer any one here; I thank you; only return home."</s>
    <s id="1:218">"But who was it?</s>
    <s id="1:219">Where are they gone?</s>
    <s id="1:220">What has happened?"</s>
    <s id="1:221">"Bad people, people who rove about by night; but they have taken flight, there is nothing more; another time, my children; I return you thanks with all my heart;" and having said this, he retired, and closed the window.</s>
    <s id="1:222">Here some began to grumble, others to joke, others to swear, others shrugged their shoulders and turned homewards, when a man arrived so out of breath that he could scarcely bring forth a word.</s>
    <s id="1:223">He inhabited the house opposite the cottage of our women; and on hearing the noise, having gone to the window, had seen in the court the disorder and tumult of the bravoes when Griso endeavoured to rally them.</s>
    <s id="1:224">When he had recovered breath, he cried, "What are you about children?</s>
    <s id="1:225">The devil is not here, he is down at the bottom of the village in Agnese Mondella's house; armed men are inside, it seems that they wish to murder a pilgrim,——who knows what devil it is?"</s>
    <s id="1:226">"What? </s>
    <s id="1:227">—— What? </s>
    <s id="1:228">—— What?" </s>
    <s id="1:229">And a tumultuous consultation commenced.</s>
    <s id="1:230">"We must go——we must see.</s>
    <s id="1:231">How many are they?</s>
    <s id="1:232">—— How many are we? </s>
    <s id="1:233">—— Who are they?</s>
    <s id="1:234">—— The consul!</s>
    <s id="1:235">—— The consul!"</s>
    <s id="1:236">"I am here" replied the consul from the midst of the crowd.</s>
    <s id="1:237">"I am here; but it is necessary to assist me, to obey me.</s>
    <s id="1:238">Quick; where is the sacristan?</s>
    <s id="1:239">To the bell, to the bell!</s>
    <s id="1:240">Quick; one to run to Lecco to fetch help; come here all ————" </s>
    <s id="1:241">How they run, how they glide between man and man, how they steal away: the tumult was at its height, when another villager arrived who had just seen the bravoes depart in haste, and cried, "Run, children; thieves, or bandits, who escape with a pilgrim; they are already out of the village; after them! after them!" </s>
    <s id="1:242">At this news, without waiting the orders of the captain, they moved off in a mass, and precipitated themselves into the street; gradually as the troop advanced, some one of the vanguard would slacken his pace, would let himself be overtaken, and place himself in the body of the battalion; those behind pushed on; and thus the confused swarm at length arrived at the indicated spot.</s>
    <s id="1:243">The traces of invasion were fresh and manifold, the door open, the lock loosened, but the assailants were gone.</s>
    <s id="1:244">They enter the court, they go to the house-door; it is also broken in.</s>
    <s id="1:245">They call, "Agnese! Lucia! the pilgrim! where is the pilgrim?</s>
    <s id="1:246">Stefano must have dreamed about the pilgrim; no, no, Carlandrea has seen him also.</s>
    <s id="1:247">Ohe!</s>
    <s id="1:248">Pilgrim!</s>
    <s id="1:249">Agnese!</s>
    <s id="1:250">Lucia!"</s>
    <s id="1:251">No one answers.</s>
    <s id="1:252">They must have carried them off.</s>
    <s id="1:253">——There were then some among the crowd, who, raising their voices, proposed pursuing the robbers; this was an infamous thing, and it would be a disgrace to the whole country if any thief might come with impunity and carry off women, as a kite does chickens from a deserted barn.</s>
    <s id="1:254">A new deliberation, still more tumultuous; but some one (and it has never been well known who this was) gives out in the assembly, that Agnese and Lucia have taken refuge in a house in the village.</s>
    <s id="1:255">The report rapidly circulates, obtains credit; they speak no longer of giving chase to the brigands; the troop disbands itself, and each one returns home.</s>
    <s id="1:256">There was a murmur, a hum, a continual noise of knocking and an opening of doors, an appearing and disappearing of lights, a questioning of women from the windows, and an answering from the street below.</s>
    <s id="1:257">The public way became silent and deserted, the dicourses were continued within doors, and died away in yawns, to be continued next morning.</s>
    <s id="1:258">In the mean time, nothing new happened, except that this same morning, the consul being in his field, his chin supported upon his hand, his elbow upon the handle of his spade which was half dug into the earth, and with his foot on the iron part, ——being there, as I said, reflecting alone upon the mysteries of the past night, and upon the compound question of that which he ought to do, and that which it would be expedient, he saw two men of a sufficiently bold bearing approach, with hair like two French kings of the first race, and resembling for the rest those two who five days before had accosted Don Abbondio, if they were not perhaps the very same.</s>
    <s id="1:259">These, with an air even less ceremonious, intimated to the consul that he should take good care not to report to the Podestà what had happened, nor speak the truth in case he should be questioned, nor gossip, nor foment the gossip of others; forasmuch as he held dear the hope of dying in his bed.</s>
    <s id="1:260">Our fugitives travelled on a considerable way in silence, turning round now one, now another, to see if any one followed them; they were wretched and dispirited from the fatigue of the flight, the torment and suspense in which they had been, the grief of their ill-success, and the confused apprehension of this new and obscure danger.</s>
    <s id="1:261">And yet more did the continued pursuit of this ever-tolling bell distress them, which the farther they removed came upon their ear more hoarse and dull, and seemed to assume an indescribable something of sinister and mournful.</s>
    <s id="1:262">The fugitives found themselves here in a desolate abandoned field, and Agnes having taken breath, broke silence, asking Renzo how things had gone on, and Menico, what devil this was in her house.</s>
    <s id="1:263">Renzo related briefly his sad history; and then the three turned towards the child, who repeated more exactly the information given him by the Father, and related what he himself had seen, and the dangers which he had run, all of which only too well confirmed this information.</s>
    <s id="1:264">His auditors comprehended more than Menico had been able to tell; at this discovery they were again seized with horror, and stopped suddenly all three, looking each other in the face terrified, then with a unanimous movement, they placed each a hand upon the poor boy's head or shoulder to caress him, to demand pardon, to render him silent thanks for having thus been their guardian angel, and at the same time to shew the sympathy they felt for the agony he had suffered, and the danger he had run, in order to insure their safety.</s>
    <s id="1:265">"Now return home, so that thy parents may no longer be in trouble about thee," said Agnese to him, and remembering the two parpagliole she had promised him, took four out of her pocket, and gave them to him, adding——"Enough——pray the Lord that we may soon meet again, and then ————" here Renzo gave him a new berlingha, and recommended him strongly to say nothing of the commission the Friar had intrusted him with; Lucia again caressed him, and bade him adieu, with a sorrowful voice: the boy, who was also affected, saluted the three and turned back.</s>
    <s id="1:266">Our travellers recommenced their march, all of them sad and thoughtful, the women in front, and Renzo following them as a guard.</s>
    <s id="1:267">Lucia remained close to the arm of her mother, and refused sweetly, yet with firmness, the assistance which the youth offered her in the difficulties of this journey performed out of the beaten road; ashamed in her heart, even in so terrible and perplexing a moment, to have remained so long and so familiarly with him, although she expected in a few moments to become his wife.</s>
    <s id="1:268">And now this dream having vanished thus sorrowfully, she repented of having gone so far; and amidst so many subjects of alarm, alarmed herself by this modesty which is not born from the sad knowledge of evil,——by this modesty, ignorant of its own existence, like to the terror of a child, who trembles in the dark, without knowing wherefore.</s>
    <s id="1:269">"And the house?" demanded Agnese suddenly.</s>
    <s id="1:270">But, however important this question was, no one replied to it, because no one could give a satisfactory answer.</s>
    <s id="1:271">They continued their way in silence, and soon after arrived at the esplanade before the church of the convent.</s>
    <s id="1:272">Renzo approached the door of the church, and pushed it with force.</s>
    <s id="1:273">It opened, and the moonlight entering through the aperture illumined the pale face and silver head of Father Cristoforo, who stood there awaiting them.</s>
    <s id="1:274">Seeing that no person was wanting, "God be praised!" said he, and made them a sign to enter.</s>
    <s id="1:275">Beside him stood another Capuchin; this was the lay sacristan, who by prayers and reasonings he had persuaded to stay up, leave the door half open, and watch with him, to receive these poor persecuted ones; and it did not require less than the Father's authority, and his reputation as a saint, to obtain from the lay-brother a condescension thus fatiguing, dangerous, and irregular.</s>
    <s id="1:276">When they had entered, Father Cristoforo closed the door very gently.</s>
    <s id="1:277">Here the sacristan could bear no more, and drawing the Father aside, said in his ear, "but, Father, Father —— the night —— in the church —— with women —— locked up —— the rule, —— but Father ————" and he shook his head, pronouncing with great difficulty these words.</s>
    <s id="1:278">Only see! thought Father Cristoforo, if this were a pursued robber, Fra Fazio would not make the slightest difficulty in the world; and a poor innocent who escapes from the clutches of the wolf!</s>
    <s id="1:279">——"Omnia mundo mundis," he then said, turning all at once round towards Fra Fazio, forgetting that he did not understand Latin.</s>
    <s id="1:280">But it was precisely such a forgetfulness which produced the desired effect.</s>
    <s id="1:281">If the Father had begun to dispute with arguments, it would not have failed Fra Fazio in others to oppose him, and heaven only knows how and when the affair would have been ended.</s>
    <s id="1:282">But hearing these words full of a mysterious sense, pronounced with so much resolution, it seemed to him that they must contain the solution of all his doubts.</s>
    <s id="1:283">He tranquillized himself, and said "enough, you know more than I do."</s>
    <s id="1:284">"Confide in me" replied Father Cristoforo; and by the uncertain light of the lamp which burnt before the altar, he approached the fugitives, who stood waiting in doubt, and said to them, "My children, thank God, who has delivered you from a great danger;" and here he began to explain fully to them what he had before only hinted to the little messenger, since he did not suspect that they knew more of this than he, but supposed Menico had found them quietly at home before the robbers had arrived.</s>
    <s id="1:285">No one undeceived him, not even Lucia, who, however, felt a secret remorse for such an act of dissimulation towards such a man; but this was the night of embarrassment and subterfuge.</s>
    <s id="1:286">After this,"continued he, "you see well, my children, that now this country is no longer safe for you.</s>
    <s id="1:287">It is your country; you were born here, you have done evil to no one; but God wills this.</s>
    <s id="1:288">It is a trial, my children; support it with patience, with confidence, without hatred, and rest assured that the time will come in which you will find yourselves satisfied with all that now happens.</s>
    <s id="1:289">I have thought where to find you a place of refuge for the present.</s>
    <s id="1:290">Soon I hope you will be able to return in security to your home; but in every case God will direct all for the best; and I certainly will endeavour not to be unworthy of the favour which he shews me in thus selecting me as his minister in the service of you, his poor dearly beloved afflicted ones.</s>
    <s id="1:291">You," continued he, turning towards the two women, "you will be able to stop at ————, there you will be removed from every danger, and yet at the same time not too far removed from your home.</s>
    <s id="1:292">Go to the convent there, ask to see the Superior, he will be another Fra Cristoforo for you.</s>
    <s id="1:293">And thou also, thou oughtest now to save thyself from thy own rage and from the rage of others.</s>
    <s id="1:294">Carry this letter to the Father Buonaventura da Lodi, in our convent of the Porte Orientale at Milan.</s>
    <s id="1:295">He will be a father to thee, he will guide thee and provide thee with work until thou canst return again to live tranquilly here.</s>
    <s id="1:296">Go to the shore of the lake near the mouth of the Bione (a torrent a few paces distant from Pescarenico), you will see there a boat moored, you must say, 'the boat', they will say, 'for whom?' you must answer, 'San Francesco.' </s>
    <s id="1:297">The boat will receive and transport you to the other shore, where you will find a cart which will conduct you straight to ————"</s>
    <s id="1:298">Whoever should demand how Fra Cristoforo had thus immediately at his disposal these means of transport by land and water, will shew that he is not aware what was then the power of a Capuchin who enjoyed the reputation of a saint.</s>
    <s id="1:299">It now only remained to think about the preservation of the house; the Father received the keys, engaging himself to consign them to those persons whom Renzo and Agnese indicated to him.</s>
    <s id="1:300">Agnese raised hers out of her pocket with a sigh, thinking that in this moment the house was open, that the devil had been there, and who knew whether there remained anything to guard!</s>
    <s id="1:301">"Before departing," said the Father, "let us pray all together to the Lord, that He will give you strength, give you love to desire that which He has willed." </s>
    <s id="1:302">Saying this he knelt down in the middle of the church, and all did the same.</s>
    <s id="1:303">After they had prayed some moments in silence, he in a low but distinct voice, pronounced these words, "we pray to Thee, for this unhappy one who has reduced us to this extremity; we should be unworthy of Thy mercy, did we not demand this from the bottom of our hearts, of this indeed he has much need!</s>
    <s id="1:304">We in the midst of our tribulation have this comfort, that we are in the path where Thou hast placed us; we can offer Thee our woes, and they become a gain.</s>
    <s id="1:305">But he—— he is Thy enemy!</s>
    <s id="1:306">O the unfortunate one!</s>
    <s id="1:307">He struggles against Thee.</s>
    <s id="1:308">Have pity for him, O Lord! touch his heart, render him Thy friend, grant him all the blessings which we could desire ourselves!" </s>
    <s id="1:309">Raising himself then in haste, he said, "Come children, there is no time to lose; God will watch over you, his angels will accompany you; go," and whilst he moved away with that emotion which does not find words, but which manifests itself without, the Father added in a sorrowful voice, "My heart tells me that we shall soon see each other again." </s>
    <s id="1:310">Certainly, the heart has always something to say upon that which is to be.</s>
    <s id="1:311">But what does the heart know?</s>
    <s id="1:312">Scarcely a little of that which has already happened.</s>
    <s id="1:313">Without waiting for a reply, Fra Cristoforo moved towards the vestry, the travellers issued forth from the church, and Fra Frazio closed the door, bidding them adieu with a voice which also betrayed some emotion.</s>
    <s id="1:314">They set forth silently towards the shore which had been indicated to them; they see there the boat, and having given and received the pass-word, stept into it.</s>
    <s id="1:315">The boatman pushing with one of his oars at the prow, detaches the boat from the shore; then seizes the other, and rows with both arms, taking the width of the lake towards the opposite bank.</s>
    <s id="1:316">Not a breath of wind stirred, the lake lay smooth and calm, and would have appeared immoveable but for the trembling and floating of the moon, which reflected itself from mid-heaven.</s>
    <s id="1:317">You only heard the wave break itself gently upon the gravel of the shore, the more distant murmur of the water round the arches of the bridge, and the measured fall of those two oars, which cut the azure surface of the lake, issuing at once, all dripping, then suddenly diving under again.</s>
    <s id="1:318">The wave cut by the boat re-uniting itself behind the poop, formed a curling line, which continued ever removing itself from the shore.</s>
    <s id="1:319">The passengers silent, their heads turned back, contemplated the mountains and the country illuminated by the moon, and varied here and there by deep shadows.</s>
    <s id="1:320">The villages, the houses, the cottages, were to be distinguished; and the great palace of Don Rodrigo, which, with its flat roof elevated above the miserable huts heaped up on the edge of this promontory, seemed a ferocious man who, surrounded by gloom, erect in the midst of a company of sleepers, watches meditating a crime.</s>
    <s id="1:321">Lucia saw it and trembled; she followed with her eye the declivity of the mountain as far as her village, gazed earnestly in the distance, perceived her cottage, perceived the thick foliage of the fig-tree which projected beyond the wall of their little court, perceived the window of her chamber; and seated as she was in the bottom of the boat, placed her arms upon the side, placed upon her arm her forehead as though to sleep, and wept secretly.</s>
    <s id="1:322">Adieu mountains, source of waters, and elevated to the heavens; unequal summits, known so well to him who is grown up among you, and impressed in his mind not less than is the aspect of his most familiar friends; torrents, whose rush he distinguishes like the sound of the domestic voices; houses, scattered and white upon the slopes, like herds of sheep at pasture; adieu!</s>
    <s id="1:323">How sad is the departing step of him grown up among you!</s>
    <s id="1:324">Even he who quits you voluntarily, driven by caprice and the hope of making elsewhere his fortune, feels at this moment his dreams of riches vanish, he is astonished how he could even have resolved upon this departure, and would turn back, did he not think one day he should return enriched.</s>
    <s id="1:325">The farther he advances into the plain, the more his eyes shrink away disgusted and wearied; the air appears to him sad and dead; he advances melancholy and listless into tumultous cities; houses adjoining houses, streets opening into streets, seem to take away his breath; and standing before edifices admired by strangers, he thinks with an uneasy desire of the belfry of his village, and of the little house upon which he has had his eyes already a long time, and which he will buy when he shall return rich to his mountains.</s>
    <s id="1:326">But what a moment for the one who has never carried her thoughts, even the most fugitive, beyond these mountains; who has formed among them all her dreams of the future, and is cast away by a perverse power!</s>
    <s id="1:327">Who, torn suddenly from her dearest occupations, and disturbed in her dearest hopes, abandons these mountains, to wander in the footsteps of strangers whom she has never desired to know, and who even in imagination cannot arrive at a fixed moment for return.</s>
    <s id="1:328">Adieu! home of her birth, where governed by a secret thought she learned to distinguish from the sounds of common footsteps, the sound of a step expected with a mysterious fear.</s>
    <s id="1:329">Adieu! house still strange to her, house so often secretly looked at in passing, and yet never without a blush; in which the mind pictured to itself, the tranquil and enduring life of a wife.</s>
    <s id="1:330">Adieu! the church where the soul has so many a time become serene, singing the praises of God; where was promised and prepared a holy rite, where the secret desire of the heart should be so solemnly blessed, and love be commanded and pronounced holy; adieu!</s>
    <s id="1:331">He who gives you so much joy is everywhere, and He never disturbs the joy of His children, but to prepare and assure a greater joy for them.</s>
    <s id="1:332">Of this kind, if not precisely such, were the thoughts of Lucia; and but little different were those of the two pilgrims, whilst the boat approached the right bank of the Adda.</s>
  </p>
</text>
