<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">― CARNEADES! </s>
    <s id="1:2">Who was he ? ― </s>
    <s id="1:3">Thus ruminated Don Abbondio, seated on his chair, in an apartment of the upper story, with a small book open before him, when Perpetua came in with her message. </s>
    <s id="1:4">― Carneades! </s>
    <s id="1:5">I think I have heard of this name, or read of it.</s>
    <s id="1:6">He must be a man of learning-a scholar of the olden time.</s>
    <s id="1:7">It is the name of one of these ― but who the deuce was he? ― </s>
    <s id="1:8">So far was the poor man from fore-seeing the tempest that was brooding over head! </s>
    <s id="1:9">It should be known that Don Abbondio loved to read a few lines every day; and a curate his neighbour, who had a small library, lent him a book every now and then, the first that came to haud.</s>
    <s id="1:10">That on which Don Abbondio then meditated, after recovering from his fever of fear; more cured (so far as the fever went) than he wished to be known ― was a panegyric in honor of San Carlo, spoken with much emphasis, and heard with high admiration, in the Duomo of Milan, two years before.</s>
    <s id="1:11">The saint was there likened for his love of study to Archimedes.</s>
    <s id="1:12">And up to this point, Don Abbondio did not find himself at a loss.</s>
    <s id="1:13">Because Archimedes has done so many famous things - has said so much of himself, that to know something of him, does not require very profound erudition.</s>
    <s id="1:14">But after Archimedes, the orator likened him also to Carneades; and here the reader was run aground.</s>
    <s id="1:15">At this moment, Perpetua announced the visit of Tonio.</s>
    <s id="1:16">"At this hour?" said Abbondio, very naturally.</s>
    <s id="1:17">"Just so.</s>
    <s id="1:18">They have no thought, but if you dont take it instantly... ." </s>
    <s id="1:19">"If I dont take it now, who knows when I shall get it? let him come ....</s>
    <s id="1:20">Ehi!</s>
    <s id="1:21">Ehi! are you sure that it is Tonio himself? </s>
    <s id="1:22">"Diavolo!" answered Perpetua, and descended; opened the gate, and said ― "Where are you ?"</s>
    <s id="1:23">Tonio shewed himself; and Agnes appearing also at the same moment greeted Perpetua by name.</s>
    <s id="1:24">"Good evening, Agnes," replied Perpetua. </s>
    <s id="1:25">"Where are you coming from at this hour?"</s>
    <s id="1:26">"From.... " (mentioning a small village in the neighbourhood) </s>
    <s id="1:27">"And if you must know.... she continued, "I have been kept so late on your account. </s>
    <s id="1:28">"How!" inquired Perpetua; and turning to the two brothers desired them to enter.</s>
    <s id="1:29">"Why," returned Agnes," one of those women who fancy that they know every thing, and will speak.... would you believe it? obstinately persisted that you are not married to Beppo Suolavecchia, nor to Anselmo Lunghigna because they would not have you.</s>
    <s id="1:30">I maintained that you had refused them both...."</s>
    <s id="1:31">"To be sure.</s>
    <s id="1:32">Oh the liar, the infamous liar!</s>
    <s id="1:33">Who is she?"</s>
    <s id="1:34">"Dont ask me; I dont like to make mischief."</s>
    <s id="1:35">"But tell me, you ought to tell me.</s>
    <s id="1:36">Oh the liar!"</s>
    <s id="1:37">"Say no more...; but you cant think how unfortunate it was that I didn't know all the story, to confound her."</s>
    <s id="1:38">"She is an infamous liar," said Perpetua, "a most infamous liar!</s>
    <s id="1:39">As for Beppo, every body knows and may see....</s>
    <s id="1:40">Ehi, Tonio, shut to the door, and go up; I am coming directly."</s>
    <s id="1:41">Tonio answered from within in an affirmative; and Perpetua continued her tormenting story.</s>
    <s id="1:42">In front of Don Abbondio's door, a lane opened between two small cottages ― running in a direct line not more than their length, and then turning into the fields.</s>
    <s id="1:43">Agnes moved forward, as if she would have drawn her apart, in order to speak more freely; and Perpetua followed.</s>
    <s id="1:44">When they had turned the corner, and were so situated as not to observe what passed at the house of Don Abbondio, Agnes coughed loudly.</s>
    <s id="1:45">That was the signal.</s>
    <s id="1:46">Renzo heard it and encouraged Lucia with a pressure of his arm.</s>
    <s id="1:47">They then both turned on tiptoe the corner where they had stood, and crept quietly along the wall, approached the door, and gently opened it.</s>
    <s id="1:48">They stooped and entered in silence; here the brothers waited for them.</s>
    <s id="1:49">Renzo softly dropped the latch and all four ascended the stair-case; not making more noise than might have been made by two.</s>
    <s id="1:50">On the landing-place, the of two brothers went to the door of an apartment which stood by the side of the stair-case: the betrothed fixed themselves close to the wall.</s>
    <s id="1:51">"Deo gratias," said Tonio, in a sort of preparatory tone. </s>
    <s id="1:52">"Tonio, eh?</s>
    <s id="1:53">Come in," answered the voice from within.</s>
    <s id="1:54">The summoned opened the door scarcely enough to admit Gervase and himself, one after the other.</s>
    <s id="1:55">The ray of light which suddenly issued from the aperture, and glanced across the dark pavement of the landing-place, made Lucia tremble, as though she had been discovered.</s>
    <s id="1:56">When the brothers had entered, Tonio shut the door behind him, the lovers remained in the dark without motion, with attentive ears, and repressed breathing.</s>
    <s id="1:57">The loudest noise was the beating of poor Lucia's heart.</s>
    <s id="1:58">Don Abbondio, was seated, as we have said; wrapped up in an old night-gown, hooded in an old cap, after the fashion of the Pope's triple crown, which made his face resemble that of a raven, by the scant light of a little candle.</s>
    <s id="1:59">Two bushy locks of hair escaping out of his cap; two thick eye-brows, two thick mustaches, a thick tuft along the chin, all grey, and scattered over a swarthy and wrinkled face, ― might be resembled to those snowy bushes jutting from a rock in the splendour of a moon-light night.</s>
    <s id="1:60">"Ah! ah!" was his salutation, as he took off his spectacles, and placed them on the little book.</s>
    <s id="1:61">"You will say that I come late, Master Curate," said Tonio, bowing.</s>
    <s id="1:62">Gervase imitated him, but more awkwardly. </s>
    <s id="1:63">"You are certainly late; late in every respect.</s>
    <s id="1:64">Dont you know that I am unwell?"</s>
    <s id="1:65">"Oh I'm very sorry."</s>
    <s id="1:66">"You must have heard that I am unwell, and I dont know how I suffered you to see me....</s>
    <s id="1:67">But why have you brought him with you ― that boy?"</s>
    <s id="1:68">"For company, Master Curate."</s>
    <s id="1:69">"Well, let us see."</s>
    <s id="1:70">"Here are twenty five new berlingas-those with Saint Ambrosio on horse-back, said Tonio taking a number from his pocket.</s>
    <s id="1:71">"Let us see," replied Don Abbondio; and grasping the coin, he took up his spectacles, opened them, examined the pieces, turned and re-turned them, counted, and found them without fault.</s>
    <s id="1:72">"Now, Master Curate, will you give me my wife's necklace.</s>
    <s id="1:73">"It is just," answered Abbondio.</s>
    <s id="1:74">He went to a cabinet, and hunted after a key, moving himself round, so as to keep the spectators at a distance.</s>
    <s id="1:75">He opened a part of the furniture, filled up the aperture with his person, introduced his head to look for, and an arm to draw out the pledge.</s>
    <s id="1:76">He then withdrew it, closed the cabinet, unrolled the paper and said, "There it is." ― folded it up again, and consigned it to Tonio.</s>
    <s id="1:77">"Now," said the latter," will you please to put it in black and white?"</s>
    <s id="1:78">"This too," exclaimed Don Abbondio" ― they know every thing: Ih! how suspicious the world is become!</s>
    <s id="1:79">Dont you trust me?"</s>
    <s id="1:80">"What, Master Curate! ― do I trust you?</s>
    <s id="1:81">You do me wrong.</s>
    <s id="1:82">But, as my name is on the debtor side in your rogue of a book there,..... then since you have already had the trouble to write once, so..... from life to death ...."</s>
    <s id="1:83">"Well, well," interrupted Don Abbondio; and grumbling he brought near him a writing-desk, drew forth paper, pen and ink, and began to write; repeating aloud the words, as they proceeded from his pen.</s>
    <s id="1:84">In the mean while, Tonio, and Gervase at a hint from the other, approached the table so as to prevent the writer from observing the door; and, as if out of idleness, they rubbed the floor with their feet ― a signal to those without that they might enter; and to hide, at the same time, the sound of their advance.</s>
    <s id="1:85">Don Abbondio immersed in his writing, thought of nothing else.</s>
    <s id="1:86">At the noise of the four feet, Renzo took the arm of Lucia, grasped it to encourage her, and then moved on, drawing her in tremor after him, and scarcely able to stir.</s>
    <s id="1:87">They entered softly, on tip-toe, withholding respiration, and stationing themselves behind the two brothers.</s>
    <s id="1:88">During this period, Don Abbondio finished his writing, read it over attentively, without lifting his eyes from the paper.</s>
    <s id="1:89">He then folded it up, remarking, "You will be satisfied now!"</s>
    <s id="1:90">With one hand, drawing the spectacles from his nose, he extended with the other, the paper to Tonio, and raised his face.</s>
    <s id="1:91">Tonio, put forth his right hand to take it, and drew back on one side.</s>
    <s id="1:92">Gervase, at his nod, drew back on the other ― and lo, as at the division of a scene, Renzo and Lucia appeared in the midst.</s>
    <s id="1:93">Abbondio saw, was terrified, stupified, infuriated; he reflected, and determined how to act.</s>
    <s id="1:94">All this he did in the time that Renzo took to utter the words, "Master Curate, in presense of these witnesses, this is my wife."</s>
    <s id="1:95">His lips scarcely closed before Don Abbondio let go the acquittance which he had held in his left hand, and lifting up the light, snatched the table-cloth with his right, and drew it furiously toward him, throwing down book, paper, inkstand and powder-box.</s>
    <s id="1:96">Then jumping between the seat and the table, he made toward Lucia.</s>
    <s id="1:97">The poor girl in her soft, sweet voice, then quivering with terror, had scarcely said. </s>
    <s id="1:98">"And this is....." ― than Don Abbondio uncivilly cast the cloth over her head and face, to stop the utterance of the whole formula.</s>
    <s id="1:99">Letting fall the light, which he had held, he brought the disengaged hand to the assistance of the other in rolling the cloth about her face.</s>
    <s id="1:100">The operation was almost suffocating and in the mean while be bawled out like a wounded bull, "Perpetua, Perpetua, treason, help! </s>
    <s id="1:101">"The candle, dying on the floor, sent forth a faint and wavering light on Lucia; who, utterly disheartened, attempted not to disengage herself; and might have been taken for a statue roughly sketched in chalk, over which the workman had thrown a wet cloth.</s>
    <s id="1:102">The light extinguished, Don Abbondio left the poor girl, and went cautiously to seek the door that led to an inner apartment; he found it, entered, and closed it after him, exclaiming continually, "Perpetua, treason, help, ― out ofthis house, out of this house." </s>
    <s id="1:103">In the other room all was confusion.</s>
    <s id="1:104">Renzo, striving to overtake the Curate, and rowing with his hands, like a blind cat, reached the place where Abbondio had ensconced himself; and beating with great clamour, vociferated, "Open the door, open the door, dont make this noise."</s>
    <s id="1:105">Lucia, in a feeble voice of earnest entreaty, said to Renzo ― "Let us go, let us go, for the love of heaven."</s>
    <s id="1:106">Tonio, creeping on his knees, groped about the floor for his acquittance.</s>
    <s id="1:107">Gervase like one possessed, shouted and leapt, and hunted about for the door of egress, in order to provide for his own safety. </s>
    <s id="1:108">In the midst of this hubbub, we must pause a moment to enunciate a reflection.</s>
    <s id="1:109">Renzo who was the occasion of all this nocturnal bustle, in the house of another; who had conveyed himself there by a deceit, and besieged the master himself in his chamber, has all the appearance of an oppressor.</s>
    <s id="1:110">Don Abbondio, surprized, put to flight, terrified in his most tranquil moments, seems a victim.</s>
    <s id="1:111">But in reality, it was he who did the wrong.</s>
    <s id="1:112">Thus the world often goes.....</s>
    <s id="1:113">I mean, so it went in the seventeenth century.</s>
    <s id="1:114">The besieged, observing that the enemy gave no sign of dislodging himself, opened a window that looked into the church-yard, and bawled out "Help! help!"</s>
    <s id="1:115">He battered the finest moon in the world.</s>
    <s id="1:116">The shade of the church, and further out, the long and narrow shade of the belfry, stretched its dark form, motionless, and distinct on the shining green sward of the sacred ground.</s>
    <s id="1:117">Every object could be distinguished as clearly as at noon-day.</s>
    <s id="1:118">But so far as the eye reached, there was no indication of a living person.</s>
    <s id="1:119">Contiguous, however, to the lateral wall of the church, and on the same side that looked toward the parochial mansion, was a small habitation, a hiding-hole where the Sacristan slept.</s>
    <s id="1:120">He was awoke by that extraordinary cry; he leapt out of bed, descended in haste, opened the paper casement of his window, and stuck out his head and eye-lids perfectly glued together. </s>
    <s id="1:121">"What is the matter?" shouted he. </s>
    <s id="1:122">"Run, Ambrose! help! people in the house," shrieked Don Abbondio. </s>
    <s id="1:123">"Directly," returned he, drawing back his head, and closing the casement.</s>
    <s id="1:124">Although half stupid, and more than half terrified, he hit upon an expedient to summon a mightier aid than could have been required of such as he.</s>
    <s id="1:125">He seized the breeches which lay on his bed, flung them under his arm like an opera hat, and leaping down a wooden ladder, ran to the belfry, pulled the rope fastened to the largest of the two bells, and sounded a fearful alarum.</s>
    <s id="1:126">Ton, ton, ton, ton: the folks of the country bolted upright in bed; the lads sleeping in the hay-loft listened, and rose up. </s>
    <s id="1:127">"What is the matter?</s>
    <s id="1:128">What is the matter?</s>
    <s id="1:129">The great bell rings!</s>
    <s id="1:130">Fire?</s>
    <s id="1:131">Thieves?</s>
    <s id="1:132">Banditti?"</s>
    <s id="1:133">Some of the women advised, implored their husbands not to stir, but let others go.</s>
    <s id="1:134">Part of these got up, and went to the window.</s>
    <s id="1:135">The cowards, as though they respected the entreaty, wrapped themselves under the bed clothes.</s>
    <s id="1:136">The more curious, and courageous, ran out with forks and arquebusses to the place of alarm: others stopped to see the event. </s>
    <s id="1:137">But before these persons were in order, before they were well awake, the sound had reached the ears of other persons who watched not far off, up and dressed: ― the bravoes in one place; Agnes and Perpetua in another.</s>
    <s id="1:138">We will briefly mention what the former had done since the moment that we left them ― part in the ruined house, and part in the hostel.</s>
    <s id="1:139">The three, when they saw all the doors closed, and the path deserted, set out under the appearance of leaving the place.</s>
    <s id="1:140">But they turned afterwards into the village, perceiving that every one had retired.</s>
    <s id="1:141">In fact, they met not a living soul, nor heard the slightest noise.</s>
    <s id="1:142">They passed even yet more gently before our poor cottage ― the most quiet of all, because nobody was in it.</s>
    <s id="1:143">They then proceeded direct to the ruined building, and made their report to Griso.</s>
    <s id="1:144">This personage instantly put on a large hat, threw an oiled frock over his shoulders sprinkled with muscle shells, and took a pilgrim's staff in his hand. </s>
    <s id="1:145">"Let us go," said he to his bravoes; "move softly and in order."</s>
    <s id="1:146">He led, and the others followed.</s>
    <s id="1:147">In a short time they reached the cottage, by a road opposite to that pursued by Renzo and his company.</s>
    <s id="1:148">Griso halted the troop a few paces from the house, and went alone to explore.</s>
    <s id="1:149">Seeing that all was deserted and tranquil without, he caused two of his rogues to advance; bade them quietly scale the wall that inclosed the area, and dropping down, hide themselves in a corner, behind a large fig-tree which he had remarked in the morning.</s>
    <s id="1:150">That done he gave a low knock, intending to call himself a pilgrim who had lost his way, and entreat permission to rest there till day-light.</s>
    <s id="1:151">But no one answers; he knocks a little louder ― not a whisper.</s>
    <s id="1:152">He then went to call a third of his rascals, and caused him to drop into the area as the others had done ― giving them directions to extract the bolt of the gate, and thus gain free ingress and egress.</s>
    <s id="1:153">All was accomplished with due caution, and the desired success.</s>
    <s id="1:154">He called the rest, and when they had entered, ordered them to the side of the first; half closed the gate, and placed two sentinels within.</s>
    <s id="1:155">He then went straight to the entrance of the ground-floor; knocked, waited ― and might have continued to wait.</s>
    <s id="1:156">He softly removed the bolt of this door also; but no one cried within, ― who's there? ― no one is heard ― it cannot go better.</s>
    <s id="1:157">Forward then: ― "st," ― </s>
    <s id="1:158">He calls those in the fig-tree, enters with them the ground-floor, where in the morning he had wickedly received the portion of bread.</s>
    <s id="1:159">He takes out tinder, flint, a steel and match; he lights a lantern, proceeds into an inner room, in order to ascertain that no one is there ― there is no one.</s>
    <s id="1:160">He returns, ascends the staircase, looks, listens: all is solitude and silence.</s>
    <s id="1:161">He leaves two other sentinels on the ground-floor, and takes along with him, Grignapoco, a bravo of the country of Bergamo, who alone was to threaten, appease, command-to be, in short, the general orator; in order that his speech might make Agnes believe the villainy to have risen from that quarter.</s>
    <s id="1:162">With this fellow at his side, and the rest behind, Griso slowly ascended, cursing in his heart every step of the stairs that creaked ― every foot of his ruffians, that made a noise.</s>
    <s id="1:163">At last he reaches the top.</s>
    <s id="1:164">Here lies the hare.</s>
    <s id="1:165">He gently pushes aside the door that leads to the first apartment; the door yields, and supplies a breathing space.</s>
    <s id="1:166">He looks in; it is dark: he listens if any one snores, breathes, or stirs within: there is nothing.</s>
    <s id="1:167">Forward then: he lifts the lantern before him, so as to see without being seen; he bursts open the door, and remarks a bed; touches it ― the bed is made, and smooth, with the upper part turned down and adjusted on the bolster.</s>
    <s id="1:168">He shrugs his shoulders, and looks at his companions; signifies to them that he will examine the other rooms, and directs them to remain quiet.</s>
    <s id="1:169">He goes, uses the same ceremony, and finds the same results. </s>
    <s id="1:170">"What the d-l does this mean?" said he aloud. </s>
    <s id="1:171">"What traitor dog has played the spy?"</s>
    <s id="1:172">With less precaution, they all bastened to examine and try every corner ― to turn the house upside down.</s>
    <s id="1:173">While they were at this business the two who watched by the street-door, heard on the way from the village, the frequent tramp of a little foot.</s>
    <s id="1:174">Imagining, that some one was passing by, they remained still, and stood upon their guard.</s>
    <s id="1:175">The foot stopped precisely at the door.</s>
    <s id="1:176">It was Menico who came in great haste on a mission from father Christopher, to warn the two females to quit the house immediately, and escape to the convent; because .... you know the reason.</s>
    <s id="1:177">He takes the chain of the bolt to knock with, and feels it give way, unnailed and broken.</s>
    <s id="1:178">What means this? thinks he, and in great alarm pushes at the gate.</s>
    <s id="1:179">It opens, and he enters very suspiciously.</s>
    <s id="1:180">At the same instant, he is griped by two arms; and two low voices on his right and left, say to him in a menacing tone. </s>
    <s id="1:181">"Gently; silence or you are dead."</s>
    <s id="1:182">He raises a cry however, and one of the two gripers, drives his fist into his mouth, and the other draws out his dagger to intimidate him.</s>
    <s id="1:183">The lad trembles like a leaf, and no longer exclaims; but on a sudden, in its turn, and in a very different tone breaks forth the first sound of the bell, and presently a storm of tones in succession.</s>
    <s id="1:184">He who is guilty is suspicious, says the Milanese Proverb; and both the rogues seemed to hear in these tones, their own names articulated.</s>
    <s id="1:185">They let go the arm of Menico, withdrew theirs in great perturbation, set both hand and mouth wide open, looked at one another, and ran into the house to their comrades.</s>
    <s id="1:186">Menico, at liberty, took to his legs, and made all haste to the belfry, where some one must necessarily be.</s>
    <s id="1:187">On the other rogues who were ferretting up and down the house that stroke of the bell produced a similar impression.</s>
    <s id="1:188">They were alternately confounded, and terrified; and jostled one another at every step: each sought out the shortest way to the door.</s>
    <s id="1:189">They were all approved men, and unaccustomed to fear; but they were unable to stand firm against an undefined peril, ― against that which they could not see at a short distance before it came upon them.</s>
    <s id="1:190">It required all the address of Griso to keep them together, so that it might be a retreat and not a flight.</s>
    <s id="1:191">As a dog that has the charge of a herd of swine, runs here and there, after those that are scattered; bites one by the ear and brings him back to the company; thrusts another in the face, barks at a third who ventures out of the line ― so, the pilgrim caught one by the hair, who had already reached the threshold and pulled him back; drove two others into the rear with his staff as they approached the door, and called lustily to the others who ran without knowing where ― until at length he assembled them, in the midst of the little court. </s>
    <s id="1:192">"Up, up! pistols in hand and cutlasses ready, let us all march together: so let us proceed.</s>
    <s id="1:193">What think ye can touch us if we stand by one another, ye cowards?</s>
    <s id="1:194">But if we let ourselves be taken one by one, even the villagers will be too much for us.</s>
    <s id="1:195">Shame!</s>
    <s id="1:196">Behind me, and stand firm."</s>
    <s id="1:197">After this brief harangue he placed himself at their head, and advanced the first.</s>
    <s id="1:198">The cottage, as we have said, was at the head of the village.</s>
    <s id="1:199">Griso took the outward road; and the rest followed in good order.</s>
    <s id="1:200">We will here leave them, and turn a step backward to take up Agnes and Perpetua, whom we placed in a particular corner.</s>
    <s id="1:201">Agnes had contrived to remove the other as far as possible from the house; and up to a certain point the thing had gone well.</s>
    <s id="1:202">But, on a sudden, the servant recollected that the door remained open, and thus became anxious to turn back.</s>
    <s id="1:203">There was nothing left but to talk.</s>
    <s id="1:204">Agnes, to avoid suspicion, returned with her; endeavouring, however, to detain her, every time that Perpetua seemed warm with the relation of such marriages as were the subject of consideration.</s>
    <s id="1:205">She appeared to give them great attention; and from time to time in order to make her observe that she was attentive, or to promote her garrulity, said ― "Certainly ― now I understand ― excellent ― and then? ― and he? ― and you?" ― </s>
    <s id="1:206">But to herself she made speeches of another kind.</s>
    <s id="1:207">― Will they have gone out now? or, are they yet within?</s>
    <s id="1:208">What owls we all three have been, not to concert some signal for giving notice when it has succeeded!</s>
    <s id="1:209">This is too bad!</s>
    <s id="1:210">But it is done: it is better now to keep this woman at bay as long as I can: at the worst, it will only be a little time lost. ― </s>
    <s id="1:211">Thus, quietly and progressively they arrived a short distance from the house of Don Abbondio.</s>
    <s id="1:212">They saw it not, on account of the corner; and Perpetua, finding herself at an important part of the story, suffered herself to be detained without resistance, and even without remark.</s>
    <s id="1:213">Suddenly burst forth through the dead silence of the night, that first extraordinary cry of Don Abbondio — "</s>
    <s id="1:214">Help, help! </s>
    <s id="1:215">"Mercy! what is the matter?" cried Perpetua, beginning to run.</s>
    <s id="1:216">"What is it? what is it?" said Agnes, holding her by the gown.</s>
    <s id="1:217">"Mercy! dont you hear?" replied she, liberating herself.</s>
    <s id="1:218">"What is the matter? what is the matter?" continued Agnes, catching her by the arm.</s>
    <s id="1:219">"Devil of a woman!" exclaimed Perpetua, pushing her back in order to escape.</s>
    <s id="1:220">At this moment, more remote, more shrill, more instantaneous, they heard the cry of Menico.</s>
    <s id="1:221">"Mercy! "shrieked Agnes also; and set off after the other.</s>
    <s id="1:222">They had hardly moved, when the bell sounded: one stroke ― two, three; and then a series.</s>
    <s id="1:223">This would have added spurs to their haste had there been need.</s>
    <s id="1:224">Perpetua arrived two paces before the other; and while she attempts to lay her hand on the door to open it ― behold, it is opened from within, and on the threshold stand Tonio, Gervase, Renzo, and Lucia.</s>
    <s id="1:225">They had come jumping down the stairs; and having heard that terrible clamour, hastened to put themselves in safety. </s>
    <s id="1:226">"What is the matter? what is the matter?" inquired the panting Perpetua of the two brothers, who answered with a huge push and broke away.</s>
    <s id="1:227">"And you!</s>
    <s id="1:228">How! what are you doing here?" she then demanded of the other pair, whom she recollected.</s>
    <s id="1:229">But they brushed past without reply.</s>
    <s id="1:230">In order to go where there was the most necessity, Perpetua asked no further questions, but rushed furiously into the passage, and with more caution, hurried up the stairs.</s>
    <s id="1:231">The two Lovers, still only The Betrothed, met Agnes who was in great affliction. </s>
    <s id="1:232">"Ah, you are here!" she said, speaking with difficulty. </s>
    <s id="1:233">"How have matters gone?</s>
    <s id="1:234">What does that bell signify?</s>
    <s id="1:235">I think I have understood."</s>
    <s id="1:236">"Home, home," said Renzo, "before the people collect."</s>
    <s id="1:237">They set forward; but here, Menico came running up: they recognized the boy who yet trembled, and stopped him.</s>
    <s id="1:238">With a voice half smothered, he said "Where are you going? back, back ― go to the convent."</s>
    <s id="1:239">"Art thou....?" began Agnes.</s>
    <s id="1:240">"What is the matter?" asked Renzo.</s>
    <s id="1:241">Lucia utterly dispirited, trembled and said nothing.</s>
    <s id="1:242">"The devil is in the house, "replied Menico, gasping for breath. </s>
    <s id="1:243">"I have seen them, and they wanted to murder me: father Christopher said so.</s>
    <s id="1:244">And you too Renzo ― he said you must come directly.</s>
    <s id="1:245">And then I have seen them.</s>
    <s id="1:246">It's a great providence that I find you all here.</s>
    <s id="1:247">I'll tell you about it, when we get away.</s>
    <s id="1:248">Renzo, who had more brain than the rest, on considering all that had occurred, immediately determined to proceed before the people should assemble; and at the same time to adopt the advice of Menico as the safer course, although recommended through the influence of terror.</s>
    <s id="1:249">By this means, apart from the confusion and danger, they might obtain a clearer explanation from the boy.</s>
    <s id="1:250">"Walk forward," said he; and then to the women, "We will accompany him. </s>
    <s id="1:251">"They turned, and moved hastily toward the church, crossed the church-yard, where, by the favor of heaven, no one appeared; and entered a narrow path that lay between the house of Don Abbondio and the church.</s>
    <s id="1:252">Then pursuing the course of a lane they got into the fields.</s>
    <s id="1:253">They had not proceeded above fifty paces, before the people began to enter the churchyard; every moment their numbers increased.</s>
    <s id="1:254">They looked one at the other each asking a question which no one could answer.</s>
    <s id="1:255">The first comers ran to the door of the church: it was locked.</s>
    <s id="1:256">They ran to the belfry without; and one of them, putting his mouth to a little window, a kind of loop-hole in the wall, sent in a "What the hangment is all this?"</s>
    <s id="1:257">When Ambrose recognized the voice he let go the cord; and assured by the humming, that the concourse of people was large, he answered ― "I'm going to open the door."</s>
    <s id="1:258">Hastily slipping on the dress which he carried under his arm, he came to the church-door, and set it cautiously open.</s>
    <s id="1:259">"What is the meaning of all this hubbub? </s>
    <s id="1:260">― What is the matter? </s>
    <s id="1:261">― Where is it?</s>
    <s id="1:262">Who is it?"</s>
    <s id="1:263">"How, who is it?" said Ambrose, holding the door in one hand, and in the other, the dress which he had slipt on so precipitately: ― "How! dont you know? people are: in the house of the curate?</s>
    <s id="1:264">Up, children; help."</s>
    <s id="1:265">They all turned to the house, looked and advanced together; looked again and listened.</s>
    <s id="1:266">All was quiet.</s>
    <s id="1:267">Some went to the street-door; it was closed and barricaded.</s>
    <s id="1:268">They looked up; there was not a window open: there was not a whisper heard.</s>
    <s id="1:269">"Who is within there? ohe, ohe, ― Master Curate!</s>
    <s id="1:270">Master Curate!"</s>
    <s id="1:271">Don Abbondio, who had no sooner got rid of his invaders, than he withdrew from the window, and made it fast, was at that moment engaged in a whispering battle with Perpetua who had left him alone in this affray.</s>
    <s id="1:272">But hearing himself thus called by the villagers, he was obliged to return; and observing such a great concourse, repented of having called them.</s>
    <s id="1:273">"What has been the matter? </s>
    <s id="1:274">― What have they done? </s>
    <s id="1:275">― Who are they?</s>
    <s id="1:276">Where are they," cried fifty voices at once.</s>
    <s id="1:277">"There is nobody here now, I thank you.</s>
    <s id="1:278">Go to your houses."</s>
    <s id="1:279">"But who has there been ? </s>
    <s id="1:280">― Where are they gone? </s>
    <s id="1:281">― What has happened?" </s>
    <s id="1:282">"Bad people ― people that wander about by night; but they have fled.</s>
    <s id="1:283">Go home, there is nothing the matter now.</s>
    <s id="1:284">Once more, sons, I thank you for your kindness."</s>
    <s id="1:285">Thus saying, he drew in his head, and closed the window.</s>
    <s id="1:286">Upon this some began to grumble, some to jeer, and some to curse.</s>
    <s id="1:287">Others shrugged their shoulders, and went away.</s>
    <s id="1:288">At this crisis arrived a person entirely exhausted, and with difficulty able to speak.</s>
    <s id="1:289">This man occupied a house nearly opposite to that of our two females, and being aroused by the noise, had remarked in the courtyard the disorder of the bravoes, whom Griso laboured to rally.</s>
    <s id="1:290">When he had taken breath, he cried ― "What do ye here, sons? the devil is not here; he is down at the bottom of the street ― in the house of Agnes Mondella: people armed are within; I think they want to murder a pilgrim.</s>
    <s id="1:291">Who knows what devil it is!"</s>
    <s id="1:292">"What? </s>
    <s id="1:293">― What? </s>
    <s id="1:294">― What?"</s>
    <s id="1:295">Then began a tumultuous consultation. </s>
    <s id="1:296">"We must go.</s>
    <s id="1:297">We must see.</s>
    <s id="1:298">― How many are there? </s>
    <s id="1:299">― How many are we?</s>
    <s id="1:300">Who are they? </s>
    <s id="1:301">― The consul, the consul!"</s>
    <s id="1:302">"I am here, "answered the consul from the middle of the crowd.</s>
    <s id="1:303">"I am here; but you must help me, you must obey.</s>
    <s id="1:304">In a minute there; where is the sacristan?</s>
    <s id="1:305">To the bell, to the bell.</s>
    <s id="1:306">Let one go instantly to Lecco for assistance.</s>
    <s id="1:307">All come here."</s>
    <s id="1:308">Some begin to run; some slipping from man to man, make good a retreat.</s>
    <s id="1:309">The tumult was great, when another person arrived who had seen the troop set out in haste ― "Run, sons; there are thieves, or banditti making away with a pilgrim: they are already out of the country: behind, behind. </s>
    <s id="1:310">"At this information, without waiting for the orders of the Captain, they moved in a confused mass down the street.</s>
    <s id="1:311">As the army proceeds, many of the vanguard slacken their pace, and hang back; fixing themselves in the body of the battalion.</s>
    <s id="1:312">The rear push forward; and at last the disorderly crowd arrives at the place indicated.</s>
    <s id="1:313">The trace of invasion was recent and manifest.</s>
    <s id="1:314">The door was open, and the bolts removed; but the assailants had disappeared.</s>
    <s id="1:315">They enter the area, and approach the entrance of the ground-floor: it is open and deprived of its bolt also.</s>
    <s id="1:316">They call ― "Agnes!</s>
    <s id="1:317">Lucia! pilgrim!</s>
    <s id="1:318">Where is the pilgrim?</s>
    <s id="1:319">Stephen has dreamt it ― Pilgrim!</s>
    <s id="1:320">No, no: Carlo Andrea has seen him also.</s>
    <s id="1:321">Ohe, pilgrim!</s>
    <s id="1:322">Agnes!</s>
    <s id="1:323">Lucia!"</s>
    <s id="1:324">No one answered. </s>
    <s id="1:325">"They have carried them away! they have carried them away!"</s>
    <s id="1:326">Some of the crowd raising their voices, proposed to follow the ravishers: it was such an atrocious action; such a shame to the country, if every knave might securely carry off the women, as a kite catches up chickens from the barndoor.</s>
    <s id="1:327">They consulted anew, and with greater tumult: but somebody (the person was never known), exclaimed, that Agnes and Lucia were safely lodged in a certain house.</s>
    <s id="1:328">The voice was rapidly caught up, and obtained instant belief.</s>
    <s id="1:329">They no longer thought of pursuing the fugitives; the crowd scattered, and each went to his own home.</s>
    <s id="1:330">There was a hum, a din, a knocking and opening of doors; lights glanced and disappeared ― women questioned from the window, and the other answered from the street; which then became deserted and silent.</s>
    <s id="1:331">Conversation proceeded in the houses, and died in yawns, to recommence on the morrow.</s>
    <s id="1:332">Nothing however was done; except that on the morning of that morrow, the consul standing in his field; propping his chin with his hands, and his hands with the handle of the spade half pushed into the soil, his foot resting upon its edge: standing, I say, to speculate with himself on the mysteries of the previous night, and on the compound reason of what concerned himself, and what it was convenient for him to do ― he saw coming towards him, two men of a tolerably impudent presense; their hair arranged like two French kings of the first race, and in the rest, resembling the two, who five days before, had confronted Don Abbondio ― if they were not the very same.</s>
    <s id="1:333">With little ceremony, they intimated to the consul, that he must take care to make a deposition of what had happened before the Podestà; to answer truly, in case he should be questioned-to beware of prating, or of encouraging prate in the villagers, if he ever hoped to die of a disease. </s>
    <s id="1:334">Our party walked for some distance at a good round pace in silence; first one and then the other turning to observe if any one followed them.</s>
    <s id="1:335">They all suffered from the fatigue of the escape ― from the heart-beating and suspense ― the vexation of bad success, ― the confused apprehension of new peril.</s>
    <s id="1:336">And yet more afflicting was the continual pursuit of those tolls of the bell, which the farther they removed, became more faint and dull, and seemed to speak the more of grief and misfortune.</s>
    <s id="1:337">At last the tolling ceased.</s>
    <s id="1:338">Then, finding an unoccupied field, and not hearing the least noise in the neighbourhood, they slackened their pace; and Agnes being the first who took breath, broke the silence by asking Menico, what devil there was in the house.</s>
    <s id="1:339">Renzo told his sad story; and all three turned to the boy, who related more exactly the warning of the father, and then what he himself had seen and risked.</s>
    <s id="1:340">This account but too well confirmed the warning.</s>
    <s id="1:341">The hearers comprehended more than Menico could, and were seized with a new shivering.</s>
    <s id="1:342">They all stood a moment in the midst of the way; and exchanged with one another a look of fear.</s>
    <s id="1:343">With a general movement all laid a hand upon the head and shoulders of the boy, as if to caress him ― to thank him tacitly who had been their tutelar angel ― to signify the pity which they felt; and ask pardon as it were for the suffering he had undergone, and the danger hazarded for their security. </s>
    <s id="1:344">"Now go home; thy parents ought not to be in longer distress about thee," said Agnes; and recollecting the two promised parpagliole, she gave him four, adding ― "That will do; pray the Lord that we may soon meet again; and then...."</s>
    <s id="1:345">Renzo gave him a new berlinga, and earnestly entreated him to say nothing of the commission which he had received from the father.</s>
    <s id="1:346">Lucia caressed him anew, and bade him farewell in a voice of sorrow.</s>
    <s id="1:347">The lad took a tender leave of them all, and turned back.</s>
    <s id="1:348">They set forward overwhelmed in thought; the women before, and Renzo behind, as a guard.</s>
    <s id="1:349">Lucia clung to her mother's arm, and softly, and dexterously avoided the help which the youth offered in the rough parts of the road; ashamed, though in such trouble, to have been alone with him so long, and so familiarly ― even when she had expected in a few minutes to be his wife.</s>
    <s id="1:350">That dream had disappeared so woefully that she deeply repented of having acted in so irregular a mode; and amongst many causes of tremor, trembled yet more from that modesty which springs not out of the sorrowful knowledge of evil ― from that modesty which is ignorant of its ownself; resembling the fear of a child which trembles in darkness without knowing why.</s>
    <s id="1:351">"And the house?" said Agnes.</s>
    <s id="1:352">But important as the care was, which drew forth this exclamation, no one answered; because no one could give a satisfactory answer.</s>
    <s id="1:353">They continued their way in silence; and before long, stopped at a little square opposite the church of the convent.</s>
    <s id="1:354">Renzo approached the door of the church, and gently pushed at it.</s>
    <s id="1:355">It was open, in fact; and the moon, entering at the aperture, illumined the pale face, and silver beard of father Christopher, who here awaited them.</s>
    <s id="1:356">Observing that they were all there, he exclaimed ― "</s>
    <s id="1:357">God be thanked," and beckoned them to enter.</s>
    <s id="1:358">By his side stood another Capuchin ― the lay-sacristan, whom he had persuaded by entreaties and reasons to watch with him; to leave the door half closed, and to stand on the look out for the poor creatures who were menaced.</s>
    <s id="1:359">But it required nothing less than the authority of the father, and his fame for holiness, to induce the laic to acquiesce in so perilous and irregular a service.</s>
    <s id="1:360">When they had entered, father Christopher softly shut the door.</s>
    <s id="1:361">The sacristan could contain himself no longer; and drawing the father apart, buzzed in his ear ― "But father, father! at night..... in a church.... with women.... to shut..... the rules.... but father!"</s>
    <s id="1:362">And he shook his head.</s>
    <s id="1:363">Whilst he slowly articulated these words ― Just observe! thought the father; if there were a ruffian pursued, brother Fazio would not have the slightest difficulty; and yet a poor innocent who has escaped from the claws of the wolf...</s>
    <s id="1:364">Suddenly turning toward brother Fazio, he said "Omnia munda mundis," forgetting that the brother did not understand Latin.</s>
    <s id="1:365">But this forgetfulness was precisely what produced the effect.</s>
    <s id="1:366">If the father had reasoned with him, brother Fazio would not have failed to oppose him with reasons; and heaven only knows when and how it would have finished.</s>
    <s id="1:367">But on hearing these grave words, of a mysterious sense, and uttered so resolutely, he thought that certainly they must contain the solution of all his doubts.</s>
    <s id="1:368">He was appeased, and said ― "Very well; you know better than I.</s>
    <s id="1:369">"Trust to me, "replied father Christopher; and by the doubtful rays of the lamp that burned before the altar, he approached the rescued, who stood in suspense, and said ― "My children! thank the Lord that you have escaped so great a peril.</s>
    <s id="1:370">Perhaps at this moment....!"</s>
    <s id="1:371">And here he stated the warning which he had sent by the little messenger.</s>
    <s id="1:372">He suspected not that they knew much more than he did; and supposed that Menico had found them at peace in their own house, before the arrival of the ruffians.</s>
    <s id="1:373">No one undeceived him-not even Lucia; who, however, felt secret remorse at thus dissimulating with such a man.</s>
    <s id="1:374">But it was the night of confusion and duplicity.</s>
    <s id="1:375">"After this," continued he, "you perceive clearly, my children, that this country is no longer a secure asylum for you.</s>
    <s id="1:376">It is yours; you were born here ― you have done wrong to nobody: but God will have it so.</s>
    <s id="1:377">It is to prove ye, my children; support it patiently ― support it with confidence, and without rancour; and be sure that the time will come when you will esteem yourselves happy in what now befalls.</s>
    <s id="1:378">I have thought of a refuge for the present.</s>
    <s id="1:379">I hope you may soon return in safety to your homes; at all events, God will provide every thing for the best.</s>
    <s id="1:380">I also will endeavour not to fail in that grace which He gives me; He who has selected me as His minister in the service of His poor and distressed children.</s>
    <s id="1:381">You ―" he pursued, turning to the women ―"may remain at ****.</s>
    <s id="1:382">Here you will be sufficiently out of every danger; and at the same time, not too far from your house.</s>
    <s id="1:383">Seek out there a convent of our order; ask for the father Custodian; give him this letter; he will be to you another friar Christopher.</s>
    <s id="1:384">And you, Renzo, must avoid others' fury, and your own.</s>
    <s id="1:385">Carry this letter to father Bonaventura da Lodi, in a convent of our order, at the eastern gate of Milan.</s>
    <s id="1:386">He will be as a father to you; he will advise you, and find you employment till you can again return here, in peace.</s>
    <s id="1:387">Go to the shore of the lake near the discharge of the Bione", (a torrent not far from the convent) "There you will find a boat made fast.</s>
    <s id="1:388">Call ― "boat"; and you will be asked, "for whom?"</s>
    <s id="1:389">Answer, "San Francesco".</s>
    <s id="1:390">The boat will receive, and transport you to the other shore.</s>
    <s id="1:391">There you will find a cart, which will conduct you immediately to ****.</s>
    <s id="1:392">He who should ask how father Christopher had so soon provided the means of conveying them by land and water, would shew, that he knew nothing of the power of a Capuchin who had the reputation of being a Saint.</s>
    <s id="1:393">The care of the houses was the next consideration.</s>
    <s id="1:394">The father received the keys, taking upon himself the charge of sending them, where Agnes and Renzo appointed.</s>
    <s id="1:395">The former as she delivered up hers, sighed bitterly; remembering at the moment that the house was open; that the devil had been there, and who could tell, what there now remained to take care of!</s>
    <s id="1:396">"Before you depart" said the father ― "let us all unite in imploring the Lord that He may be always with you in the way; above all, that He may give you strength ― supply you with the desire of willing what He has willed."</s>
    <s id="1:397">So saying, he kneeled in the middle of the church, and all did the same.</s>
    <s id="1:398">When they had prayed a few minutes in silence, in a low but distinct voice, he uttered these words ― "We implore thee also unhappy man who has brought us to this condition: we should be unworthy of thy benevolence if we asked it not heartily for him: for him, who has so much need of it!</s>
    <s id="1:399">We, in tribulation, have this comfort ― we are in the way where thou hast placed us; we may offer thee our afflictions, and they turn to our advantage.</s>
    <s id="1:400">But he! he is thy enemy.</s>
    <s id="1:401">Unhappy being! he contends with thee!</s>
    <s id="1:402">Have pity on him, O Lord ― touch his heart, render him thy friend, concede to him all those blessings which we may ask for ourselves.</s>
    <s id="1:403">Rising hastily, he added, "Go, my children; there is no time to lose.</s>
    <s id="1:404">God preserve you; may his Angel accompany you: ― go."</s>
    <s id="1:405">They set out filled with that emotion which finds not words, and which is developed without them. </s>
    <s id="1:406">"Go," said the father ― "my heart tells me that we shall soon meet again.</s>
    <s id="1:407">To him who listens, the heart has always something to say relative to the future.</s>
    <s id="1:408">But what does the heart know?</s>
    <s id="1:409">Scarcely a minute portion of what has already happened.</s>
    <s id="1:410">Without waiting a reply, brother Christopher hastily withdrew.</s>
    <s id="1:411">The travellers went forth; and brother Fazio closed the door, bidding them farewell in a voice which was altered even in him.</s>
    <s id="1:412">They quietly approached the shore indicated; they distinguished the boat, and gave the appointed challenge.</s>
    <s id="1:413">They then entered.</s>
    <s id="1:414">The boatman, pushing with one oar against the bank, detached the vessel from the strand, and catching up another, rowed with both arms toward the opposite shore.</s>
    <s id="1:415">There was not a breath of air.</s>
    <s id="1:416">The lake lay smooth and clear, and would have seemed motionless but for the tremulous and wavy light of the moon, which glassed itself from the midst of heaven.</s>
    <s id="1:417">The pale and sluggish wave was only heard to break upon the gravelled beach ― the more distant gurgle of the water, interrupted by the pillars of the bridge ― and the measured fall of the two oars that cut the blue surface of the lake, dripping at every stroke, and again disappearing.</s>
    <s id="1:418">The wave parting as the boat advanced, and re-uniting at her stern, disclosed an undulated track extending from the shore.</s>
    <s id="1:419">The passengers spoke not; but with reverted head, looked upon the mountains and country lighted by the moon, and here and there variegated with broad shadows.</s>
    <s id="1:420">They distinguished villages, houses, and cottages.</s>
    <s id="1:421">The palace of Don Rodrigo, with its flat tower, lifted above the mass of small buildings on the side of the promontory, appeared like some fierce creature standing amid the darkness over a company of prostrate sleepers, and watching to perpetrate a crime.</s>
    <s id="1:422">Lucia saw it, and shuddered; her eye passed along the declivity to her own homestead; she looked fixedly at the extreme point ― singled out her own abode, and the thick leaves of the fig-tree that peered above the enclosure of the court-yard: singled out the window of her own apartment; and then, seated as she was at the bottom of the boat, leaned her elbow on its side, bent her head as if to sleep, and wept in secret.</s>
    <s id="1:423">Farewell, ye mountains rising from the waters and elevating yourselves to heaven; irregular summits, the marks well-known to him who has grown up among ye, and impressed ye on his mind not less than the aspect of his most familiar friends: torrents, of which he distinguishes the boil, as the sound of domestic voices: villas sprinkled and whitening on the declivity, like flocks of sheep in the pasture, ― farewell!</s>
    <s id="1:424">How much is his step saddened, who, reared among ye is violently torn away.</s>
    <s id="1:425">In the fancy even of him who leaves you willingly, allured by the prospect of better fortunes in another land, ― how, in that moment, are the dreams of wealth disfigured!</s>
    <s id="1:426">He wonders that he could resolve to quit ye; and would then return, if he did not imagine that he should one day return enriched.</s>
    <s id="1:427">As he advances over the plain, his eye withdraws, loathing and weary of that uniform extension.</s>
    <s id="1:428">The air seems heavy and lifeless; he enters sad and inattentive, the tumultuous cities; houses joined to houses; streets that lead into streets obstructive of respiration.</s>
    <s id="1:429">And even before edifices wondered at by the stranger, he remembers with unsatisfied longing the little field of his country ― the little hut on which he has long placed his eyes, and which he will purchase when he returns with riches to his mountains.</s>
    <s id="1:430">But he who has never been impelled from thence, even by a fugitive desire; who has there planned all his designs for the future, and yet is cast forth by a malicious power!</s>
    <s id="1:431">Who, plucked at once from the pursuits, and disturbed in his dearest warmest hopes, leaves these mountains to follow in the footsteps of strangers who have never wished to know him; and cannot, even in imagination, pass to the decreed moment of his return! </s>
    <s id="1:432">― Farewell, the natal home where sitting in secret thought, she learnt to discriminate the tread of common steps, from a step expected with mysterious apprehension.</s>
    <s id="1:433">Farewell the home, yet strange ― a home so often in passing regarded by stealth, and not without a blush; a home which the mind pleased itself by depicting as the constant and calm abode of married love.</s>
    <s id="1:434">Farewell the church, whence the heart so often turned to chant the praises of the Lord; where the sacred rite was promised, was prepared; and where the soul's hidden sigh ought to have been solemnly blessed, and love commanded, and pronounced holy; farewell!</s>
    <s id="1:435">He who imparted to you so much delight is every where; and He never troubles the joy of his children, except to prepare for them that which is greater, and more secure.</s>
    <s id="1:436">Of such a nature, if not precisely the same, were the thoughts of Lucia; and very little unlike, the thoughts of the other two wanderers, as the boat approximated the right shore of the Adda.</s>
  </p>
</text>
